  <chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <title xml:id="commands">Commands</title>
    <para>You enter the command mode by typing '/' when you are in the Ready mode. When you do this, you will notice that the Ready message is replaced on line 2 of the display by the main command menu, which consists of a number of single letters, each representing a command:</para>
    <screen>A B C D E F I L M P Q R S T W ?</screen>
    <para>You can then select any one of the commands by typing the letter associated with it. This will lead to another menu or other message, which will be described under the headings of individual commands. If you don&#x2019;t remember what the letters stand for, type &#x2018;?&#x2019; for HELP, which is a summary of instructions for the main command level. Each subsequent command menu also has its own HELP, which is called up by typing '?' in response to the menu prompt.</para>
    <sect1>
      <title>Attributes</title>
      <para>Attributes (/A) should really be listed last, since it is a catch-all for miscellaneous commands that don&#x2019;t fit under any other heading, but we will defer to the alphabetic sequence and tell you DYNACALC attribute commands here.</para>
      <para>The attributes command menu is obtained by typing /A when you are in the Ready mode. The menu consists of these single-letter commands:</para>
      <screen>B D G H L M O P R S T W ?</screen>
      <para>Attribute B (<userinput>/AB</userinput>) is a good one to start with, since it is very simple. Each time you type <userinput>/AB</userinput> you 'toggle' (reverse) a switch which controls whether or not the bell ('bell' is a carryover from the mechanical teletype - terminals normally use an electronic beeper) is sounded to indicate operator error. If you get tired of hearing the beeper all the time, turn it off! (or stop making errors). This switch is saved by <userinput>/SS</userinput>.</para>
      <para>Attribute D (<userinput>/AD</userinput>) toggles the degrees/radians switch for trigonometric functions. This switch defaults to 'degrees', but its current state is saved with <userinput>/SS</userinput>. Whenever trig calculations are made, the current state of this switch is used to determine whether to use degrees or radians to represent angles.</para>
      <para>Attribute G (<userinput>/AG</userinput>) is used to change the character used for plotting histograms (see plot format - <userinput>/FP</userinput> or <userinput>/WFP</userinput>). The default value is the hash or pound symbol (#). You can change it to any other printing character. Hit RETURN when the character is what you want it to be. This command affects future printing only - not what is already on the screen. To re-write the screen with the new character, type <userinput>/AM</userinput>. The selected character is saved with <userinput>/SS</userinput>.</para>
      <para>Attribute H (<userinput>/AH</userinput>) is a command which you may execute to delete all HELP messages from memory. The memory formerly used by HELP is then available for user space. Since the HELP messages can be very handy, don&#x2019;t turn them off unless you really need the space.</para>
      <para>If you frequently need lots of workspace, you can permanently turn off HELP with an option in the 'install.dc' command (see the section on <xref linkend="system.configuration">System Configuration</xref>). If you need to call up a very large worksheet on the OS-9 command line when you call DYNACALC, you must permanently disable HELP messages with the 'install.dc' command.</para>
      <para>To restore HELP messages you must leave DYNACALC and re-enter from OS-9. Don&#x2019;t forget to save your worksheet!</para>
      <para>Attribute L (<userinput>/AL</userinput>) toggles the 'Label entry mode' flag (defaults to off). When label entry mode is on, labels typed in one cell will automatically continue across the row, and will be entered into following cells as necessary. To use this mode, simply point to the cell where you wish the label to begin, then start typing. The cell address will be automatically incremented as soon as you type one character more than will fit in the current column. If you later change any of these column widths, you will have to adjust your labels (retyping an entire long message may be the easiest method in this case).</para>
      <para>Attribute M (<userinput>/AM</userinput>) is a command used to re-write (Modify) the screen at any time. Its main use is with the graph character command (<userinput>/AG</userinput>).</para>
      <para>Attribute O (<userinput>/AO</userinput>) - note the O is a letter, and not the number zero - toggles the switch that decides the order of calculation. Either the columns are done first (default), as A1, A2, A3...B1, B2, B3 or the rows are done first as A1, B1, C1....A2, B2, C2... The current setting is displayed as &#x2018;C&#x2019; or 'R' after 'Mode=' on line 2 of the display. This switch can be very important on some worksheets, and of no concern at all on others. Just don&#x2019;t forget about it. The C/R switch setting is saved by <userinput>/SS</userinput>. See <xref linkend="operating.tips">Operating Tips</xref>for further considerations.</para>
      <para>Attribute P (<userinput>/AP</userinput>) allows you to examine and/or change the setting of printer attributes, and will lead to another menu consisting of:</para>
      <screen>B C L P S W ?</screen>
      <para>(You can choose to send the 'printer' output to a text file on disk for later printing). Command B (<userinput>/APB</userinput>) toggles the flag that decides whether or not to print DYNACALC&#x2019;s borders on the printer/textfile (default is 'off'). Command C (<userinput>/APC</userinput>) closes the current printer device or file (if any). The next time you request a printout of the worksheet (/P), you will be prompted for a device or file name. You would then respond with the name of a printer port (eg "/p" or "/p1") or a disk file (eg &#x201C;fred&#x201D; or &#x201C;/d1/myfile&#x201D;). Command L (<userinput>/APL</userinput>) lets you change the number of lines per page (default is 58). Command P (<userinput>/APP</userinput>) toggles the flag which decides whether or not to paginate the output (default is 'on'). Command S (<userinput>/APS</userinput>) allows you to use single (1) or multiple (2-8) spacing for the printed or textfile output. Command W (<userinput>/APW</userinput>) lets you change the printer line width (default is 80 characters). If you find yourself frequently changing to a particular configuration, remember that all DEFAULT values can be changed using &#x201C;install.dc&#x201D;. See the <xref linkend="system.configuration">System Configuration</xref>section for details. All printer/textfile parameters are saved by <userinput>/SS</userinput>.</para>
      <para>Attribute R (<userinput>/AR</userinput>) toggles the flag which controls DYNACALC&#x2019;s automatic recalculate feature. When the flag is on (default), an 'A' is displayed after 'Mode=x', on line 2, and the worksheet is automatically recalculated after any value is changed. If you turn off the flag, an 'M' is displayed to indicate manual recalculate. Now the sheet will be recalculated only when you type '!' in the Ready mode. This flag is also saved by <userinput>/SS</userinput>.</para>
      <para>Attribute S (<userinput>/AS</userinput>) reports the highest column/row address in use in your current worksheet. This is an easy way to keep track of the size or your sheet, and avoid forgetting about tables, etc., which might be hidden from view. <userinput>/AS</userinput> is also very helpful in managing available memory allocation in the <xref linkend="operating.tips">Operating Tips</xref>section.</para>
      <para>Attribute T (<userinput>/AT</userinput>) toggles the Type protection flag. When type protection is turned on, DYNACALC will ask 'Are you sure?' if you attempt to change a label or an expression. The idea is to prevent accidental changing of the 'guts' or your worksheet when you are typing in data. This feature defaults to 'off'. Its setting is saved by <userinput>/SS</userinput>.</para>
      <para>Attribute W (<userinput>/AW</userinput>) lets you change displayed column width, and leads to another menu:</para>
      <screen>C W ?</screen>
      <para>which lets you elect to change the width of only the current column (<userinput>/AWC</userinput>) or or the entire current window (<userinput>/AWW</userinput>). The default width for individual columns is the current window column width, and the default width for all columns in a window is 9. All column width information is saved by <userinput>/SS</userinput>.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Blank Cell</title>
      <para>This is an easy one. DYNACALC asks you if you really want to blank out the current cell. Answer "Y" or "N". Only the data in the cell is erased. The format of the cell is preserved.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Clear worksheet</title>
      <para>Another easy one (maybe we should make it harder). This command /C deletes the entire worksheet. Make sure the worksheet is saved on diskette if it&#x2019;s of any value to you. Then answer "Y" or "N".</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Delete</title>
      <para>The delete command lets you delete an entire column or row. DYNACALC asks you:</para>
      <screen>C R ?</screen>
      <para>to find out whether you want to delete a column or a row. If you can&#x2019;t make up your mind, hit ESCAPE and think about it for a while (sorry, there is no 'un-delete' command). After the column or row has been removed from your worksheet, any references (in expressions) to cells in the deleted part are flagged with &gt;ER&lt; errors. You can tell whether an &gt;ER&lt; was caused by the delete or by operator error by pointing the cursor to the error cell in question. If a machine-generated error is present, the top line of the screen will display @ERROR? instead of the &gt;ER&lt; shown in the cell. Any references to cells beyond the deleted area are automatically adjusted to take into account the new column letters or row numbers . Don&#x2019;t forget to take this into account yourself when typing in new expressions!</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Edit cell</title>
      <para>The edit cell command (/E) allows you to edit the contents of any cell. See the full description under Error Correction on page <xref linkend="error.correction">6</xref>.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Format</title>
      <para>DYNACALC offers a number of display formats, and the format command allows you to select the one(s) to use. If entered directly from the main command menu (/F). the format selected applies ONLY to the current cell. If entered through the window command (<userinput>/WF</userinput>), the format applies to ALL cells in the current window, except cells with explicit format set individually. All window and cell format information is saved by <userinput>/SS</userinput>.</para>
      <para>When you enter the format command, you will be prompted with:</para>
      <screen>C D G I L P R $ ?</screen>
      <para>Each of these letters represents a format to be described below.</para>
      <para>Format C (<userinput>/FC</userinput> or <userinput>/WFC</userinput>) is continuous format, and is valid only for cells containing labels. Continuous format uses the character or characters entered in repetition to fill the width of the cell, regardless of how wide it may be now or later. A typical use for continuous format is to create borders between rows. For example, you might enter a dash ('-) as a label, and select continuous format for that cell (<userinput>/FC</userinput>). This would fill the cell with dashes (--------). Now use the replicate command (see below) to copy this cell into several others on the same row, and you have a nice border, and with only a few keystrokes. Other useful characters are period (enter as '.) and equals (=).</para>
      <para>Format D (<userinput>/FD</userinput> or <userinput>/WFD</userinput>) is the default format. If the command is entered directly from the Ready mode (<userinput>/FD</userinput>), the current cell&#x2019;s format will default to the format of the current window. If entered through the window command (<userinput>/WFD</userinput>), the default format of all the cells in the current window will be the system default format, which is the same as the General format (see below).</para>
      <para>Format G (<userinput>/FG</userinput> or <userinput>/WFG</userinput>) is the general format. This format causes labels to be left-justified and numbers to be right-justified within each cell.</para>
      <para>Format I (<userinput>/FI</userinput> or <userinput>/WFI</userinput>) is the integer format. Cells formatted this way will be rounded to the nearest whole number, and right justified within the cell. The rounding affects only the display, and not the internal representation of the number. If the cell is referenced in an expression, the cell&#x2019;s original, unrounded, value is used.</para>
      <para>Format L (<userinput>/FL</userinput> or <userinput>/WFL</userinput>) means left-justify. Numbers and/or labels will start at the left end of the cell.</para>
      <para>Format P (<userinput>/FP</userinput> or <userinput>/WFP</userinput>) is the plotting format, which is used to create horizontal bar graphs (histograms) within your worksheet. The number in the cell is rounded to the nearest integer. and the resulting number is used to count graph characters as they are printed. For example, if a cell has a value of 2.4, its integer value is 2, so 2 graph characters will be printed in the cell. If the number is subsequently increased to 5.1, a total of 5 graph characters will be seen. The <userinput>/AP</userinput> command can be used to change the graph character.</para>
      <para>Format R (<userinput>/FR</userinput> or <userinput>/WFR</userinput>) means right-justify. Numbers and/or labels will end exactly at the right end of the cell.</para>
      <para>Format $ (<userinput>/F$</userinput> or <userinput>/WF</userinput>$) is the money format, used mainly for representing money in pounds and pence. In this format. the cell&#x2019;s value is rounded to the nearest penny, (0.01), and displayed with a decimal point and two following digits, even if they are zero. The rounding affects only the display, and not the internal representation or the number. If the cell is referenced in an expression, the cell&#x2019;s original, unrounded value is used.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Insert</title>
      <para>The insert command (/I) lets you insert a new (blank) column or row into an existing worksheet. Simply move the cursor to the column or row where you want the new one to be, and type the command. The new column or row will appear, and any references to cells beyond the inserted area will be automatically adjusted to take into account the new addresses. Remember this yourself when you type in new expressions.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Locate label</title>
      <para>
  The locate label command lets you quickly determine the
location of a specified label. This is very useful, especially
with large worksheets extending over several screens.
      </para>
      <para>
When you type /L to enter this command, DYNACALC will ask
you for the text string (sequence of characters) for which to
search. Enter the desired string and hit (ENTER). Now DYNACALC
searches your worksheet for any occurrence on a LABEL of the
specified string. This is a substring search, so the target
label does not have to contain only the search string, DYNACALC
might report the existence of labels 'bathroom' and 'bathtub'
(but not 'bat').
      </para>
      <para>
When locate finds a match, it displays the address of the
cell containing the found label, and the entire contents of that
cell, on the top line of the screen. On line two the prompt
'Move?' is displayed. Answer this prompt with 'N' to continue
searching, or 'Y' to move the cursor to the displayed cell.
      </para>
      <para>
Locate starts at the current cell, and goes vertically
through the worksheet in its search for a match. If no match is
found before it returns to the starting cell, the command is
aborted.
      </para>
      <para>
There are two special characters that can be included in
the search string. A question mark (?) at any position in the
search string serves as a wild card. Thus a search string of
'c?t' might result in finding 'cat', 'cot', or 'cut'. Any
number of wild card characters can be included in the search
string. The other special character is the at-sign (@). This
character, when used in the FIRST character position of the
search string, causes DYNACALC to require an exact match
(including case) between search and target strings. Normally
case (the difference between 'a' and 'A') is ignored.
      </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Move</title>
      <para>The move command (/M) lets you move rows and columns from one place to another within your worksheet. You can do this manually, or with DYNACALC&#x2019;s built-in sort feature.</para>
      <para>The ascending sort command (<userinput>/MA</userinput>) causes DYNACALC to sort all or part of your worksheet in ascending numeric and/or alphabetic order. When you type this command, DYNACALC will ask you 'Range?'. Respond with the address of the first and last cells you wish to use as the sort key, separated by a period (.), and ending with RETURN. If you give two cells in a single column, that range of cells will be used as the key to sort all rows between the first and last addresses given (inclusive). In other words, the row whose cell in that column has the lowest value moves to be the first row in the chosen range, followed below it by the row whose cell in that column has the next lowest value, and so on. If you give two cells in a single row, that range of cells will be used as the key to sort all columns between the first and last addresses given (inclusive). Note that all cells in the same row (same column for row key) will be moved by the sort. If the sheet is laid out appropriately, this fact can be very useful.</para>
      <para>The sort may be on numbers (values or expressions) or strings (labels), or both. Sequence is: alphabetic (case is ignored), numerics in label cells, and finally numbers (in alphabetic order). You can force a label to sort first by preceding it with '@' (enter as '@).</para>
      <para>The descending sort command (<userinput>/MD</userinput>) works the same as <userinput>/MA</userinput>, but the order of the sort is reversed.</para>
      <para>The manual move command (<userinput>/MM</userinput>) allows you to move an existing column or row to a new location in your worksheet. After you type this command, DYNACALC will ask you 'From...to?'. Respond by typing the address of any cell in the column or row to be moved, a period (.), then the equivalent address in the destination column or row. For example to move column C to column F, you could type 'C1.F1' or 'C3.F3' but not 'C1.F3' or 'C3.F1'. If you are moving columns, the row specified must be the same in each case; if you are moving rows, the same column must be specified. (That is how DYNACALC knows whether you want to move a row or a column).</para>
      <para>As in the case of the Delete and Insert commands, any references to cell addresses changed by the move commands will be automatically adjusted by DYNACALC. When you type in new expressions, remember that some things have been moved around.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Printer Output</title>
      <para>The printer output command (/P) is used to send a copy of your worksheet, or any part of it, to your system printer or to a textfile.</para>
      <para>After you enter the /P command, DYNACALC will ask you for the name of the printer device or textfile to which output should be routed, but only if such a name has not already been entered. The default name is '/p' the parallel printer port. You can clear the name with the command <userinput>/APC</userinput>; the next time you use /P, you will again be asked for the output pathname. Once that question is dispensed with, DYNACALC will ask you 'Range?'. Respond with the cell addresses of the top-left and bottom-right corners of the area you want to send to the printer, separated by a period (.). Note that DYNACALC cannot print out a section of worksheet that is wider than your printer. If your worksheet is wider than your printer, you must print it out in separate parts.</para>
      <para>In addition to the printer output name, there are five parameters that you can adjust to alter the way DYNACALC outputs to the printer: Borders (no/yes), number of lines per page, pagination (yes/no), multiple spacing (1-8), and page width. See attributes (<userinput>/AP</userinput>) section for details. Current settings are displayed before continuing.</para>
      <para>If pagination is enabled, DYNACALC will ask you for a title. The string that you type in (terminate with RETURN) will be placed at the top of each page of the printout.</para>
      <para>You can make the printer pause with the ESCAPE key. To resume printing, hit ESCAPE again. You can abort the printer operation by hitting RETURN while the printer is pausing.</para>
      <para>If the output is sent to a textfile, the textfile created is in standard OS-9 format, with a single CARRIAGE RETURN character ($0D) at the end of each line. The file can be listed out to the printer when you are back in OS-9:</para>
      <screen>OS9: list myfile &gt;/p</screen>
      <para>Maximum line length is 255 characters. Keep in mind that other OS-9 utilities may have further restrictions on maximum line length. The output will default to the working data directory, but of course you may specify a complete pathname if you wish.</para>
      <para>Once you get the desired part of the worksheet written to the textfile, you may use <userinput>/SX</userinput> command to initiate a printer spooling operation, according to standard practice for your system. For example:</para>
      <screen>OS9&gt; list myfile &gt;/p&amp;</screen>
      <para>Note that the <userinput>/SX</userinput> command displays the prompt "OS9&gt;" rather than OS9&#x2019;s own prompt &#x201C;OS-9:&#x201D;. The '&amp;' at the end of the command line is an instruction to OS-9 to print out the file in the background while returning you to DYNACALC to get on with your worksheet.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Quit</title>
      <para>The quit command (/Q) is used to exit DYNACALC. The normal exit is to OS-9 (<userinput>/QO</userinput>). Exiting DYNACALC will or course destroy your current worksheet, so make sure it&#x2019;s saved on diskette if it&#x2019;s of any value. DYNACALC will ask 'Are you sure?'. Answer "Y" or "N". You can also put your computer 'to sleep' (<userinput>/QS</userinput>). This will blank the screen until you hit any key to restore normal operation. You will find that your worksheet is intact.</para>
      <para>You can also exit to OS-9 by typing a log-off character (CONTROL-D on most keyboards). If you do this, the current worksheet is automatically saved as 'dyna.xxxxx.cal' (xxxxx is your user id number) in your working data directory.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Replicate</title>
      <para>The replicate command (/R) lets you copy the contents or a cell or range of cells into another part of the worksheet. This means that you can avoid re-typing long expressions, etc., and thus spend more of our valuable time on other things.</para>
      <para>When you type /R, DYNACALC will prompt you for a range of source cells (the source means the cell or range of cells to be copied). If you want to copy just a single cell, enter its address and hit 'RETURN' If the single cell you want to copy happens to be the current cell, just hit RETURN. Or, if the first of several cells you want to copy is the current cell, just hit '.' and the address of the last source cell, followed by 'RETURN'. For a range of cells, enter the first cell, a period (.), and the last cell, then hit 'RETURN'. If a range or cells is to be copied, they must all be in the same column or In the same row. You cannot replicate multiple columns or rows with a single command. You can transfer blocks of data with /S#S and /S#L (see the section on the /S command).</para>
      <para>DYNACALC will now ask you for the destination. If the destination is a single cell, column, or row, type its address (not necessary if it happens to be the current address) and hit RETURN. If the source is to be copied a number of times, enter the first address, a period (.), and the last address, followed by 'RETURN'.</para>
      <para>Next you are asked '(S)ame or (R)elative' <emphasis>for each value reference in the source.</emphasis> If you answer 'S', that reference will be copied literally into the destination cell(s). However, if you answer 'R', all occurrences of that value reference will be modified according to the position or the destination within your worksheet. For example. if you want to copy @SUM(A1...A5) from A7 to B7...F7, and you want separate sums to represent individual column totals, you would specify 'R' so that in cell B7 you would wind up with @SUM(B1...B5). and so on. If this seems confusing at first, try it. After a few times it will make sense, and you will develop the ability to get a significant amount of work done with just a few keystrokes.</para>
      <para>You can copy all or part of any column or row to one or more places on your worksheet. To continue the example above, let&#x2019;s say that there is data (values) in cells A1 through A5. We want to copy this data and the sum in A7 to another column. To do this, type &#x201C;/R A1.A7 B1 'RETURN'&#x201D; Now you will see a replica of column A in column B. Move the cursor to B1 and type <userinput>/DC</userinput> to delete column B. Then type "/R A1.A7 B1.F1 R". The contents of column A now fill columns B through F. Pretty neat, eh?</para>
      <para>You should also be aware that when Replicate copies the contents of a cell, not only does it copy the label, value, or expression contained in the cell, but also its format. Therefore you can use replicate to change the format of a large number of cells at one time, without changing the window format.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>System</title>
      <para>The system command (/S) lets DYNACALC communicate with the rest of your computer, through the OS-9 operating system. Using /S, you can save and load worksheets, and do other system-related tasks.</para>
      <para>The change-directory command (<userinput>/SC</userinput>) allows you to change the current data directory without leaving DYNACALC. <userinput>/SC</userinput> will ask you for the new directory name. Enter the name, then hit 'RETURN'.</para>
      <para>The worksheet load command (<userinput>/SL</userinput>) loads a previously-saved worksheet into your computer&#x2019;s memory. It DOES NOT CLEAR THE CURRENT WORKSHEET. Instead, the file being loaded overlays cells on an individual basis. Any cell that was unused (blank) on the sheet when it was saved will have no effect on the contents of the worksheet when it is re-loaded (if a cell had a specific format when it was saved, however, that will become the format of the target cell). Cells that are non-blank in the file will over-write existing cells. This gives you the powerful ability to combine worksheets. For example, you might have a pricing table in a diskette file, and then use that one table to overlay a variety of worksheets based on it. Then, when prices change (translated: increase), you have only one file to change. All <userinput>/SL</userinput> operations default to the working data directory. The file to be loaded must reside in the current working directory.</para>
      <para>
        If you do not want to overlay the present worksheet, type 
        <userinput>
          /C
        </userinput>
         (and answer 
        <userinput>
          Y
        </userinput>
        ) to clear the sheet before loading a new one.
      </para>
      <para>DYNACALC can automatically load a worksheet on startup. See the section &#x2018;<xref linkend="__RefHeading___Toc2817_3093686648">Calling DYNACALC</xref><xref linkend="__RefHeading___Toc2817_3093686648"/>&#x2019; on page <xref linkend="__RefHeading___Toc2817_3093686648">6</xref>.</para>
      <para>The worksheet save command(<userinput>/SS</userinput><userinput>)</userinput><userinput> </userinput>saves the entire current worksheet on diskette. When you type this command, DYNACALC will ask for a filename, which defaults to the working data directory. If the file already exists, DYNACALC will ask if it should be deleted. If you don&#x2019;t want to delete the old file, type &#x2018;N&#x2019; and then /SS and a different filename.</para>
      <para>
        When you save a worksheet, all cells in the sheet are written to diskette, even if they are currently 
        
        out of sight. Column widths, windows, titles, cursor location, graph character selection, printer attributes, formats, and the type protection, auto/manual, key click, degrees/radians, label entry mode, and column/row order flags are also saved, and will be restored when the file is loaded. Physical printer parameters (the ones set by /SP) are 
        <emphasis>
          not
        </emphasis>
         saved with the worksheet. To save a partial worksheet, refer to /S#S.
      </para>
      <para>The execute OS-9 command (/SX) makes it possible to execute OS-9 commands. Any legal OS-9 command can be executed, even one ending in '&amp;', which will start a background task. Just be careful to avoid starting tasks which send later output to your terminal, as that would spoil the appearance of DYNACALC&#x2019;s screen.</para>
      <para>When the OS-9 command is completed, DYNACALC will give you another 'OS9&gt; ' prompt. At this point you can type another OS-9 command, or just hit 'RETURN' to return to DYNACALC, with your worksheet undisturbed.</para>
      <para>The data storage command (/S#L and /S#S) allow you to save part (or all) of a worksheet in a text file format compatible with other OS-9 software, such as BASIC09, COBOL, PASCAL, RMS, and so on.</para>
      <para>When you type /S#L, DYNACALC will ask you for a filename, then it will load the data from the specified file into your worksheet, beginning at the current cell. This means that you must position the cursor to the desired spot before typing /S#L. Before the data transfer occurs, DYNACALC will ask you if the data is to be loaded by column or by row. To load the data the same way as it was saved, type D for default. The load operation will usually affect only those cells being loaded whose new contents are non-blank. This permits you to overlay a worksheet with data tables prepared previously with DYNACALC or other system programs. See &#x2018;Using Data Files&#x2019; for more information.</para>
      <para>The data save command, /S#S, will also ask for a filename, and whether data is to be saved by column or by row. The default option (D) will choose whichever direction was used last; in the case of the first /S#S operation after loading DYNACALC , the default is by column. The cursor location is unimportant, however, since DYNACALC will ask you for a range of cells to save. Respond with the addresses of the top-left and bottom-right cells in the rectangular area you wish to save. Hitting (ENTER) without entering a range will cause the entire worksheet to be sent.</para>
      <para>Only value and label information may be saved and loaded. Cells containing expressions will be evaluated and their current value saved. If you want to save expressions, use the worksheet save and load commands (/SS and /SL). Also note that /S#S does not save anything other than the data in the cells. Any cells containing errors are saved as blank cells in the data file. Widths, formats, etc. are lost. To save these use /SS.</para>
      <para>DYNACALC examines each line of incoming data during a /S#L operations to determine if it contains value or label information. If the line looks like a number (begins with 0-9, minus, plus, or decimal point), it will be treated as a value. Other lines will be treated as labels. To input a number something that looks like a number as a label, precede it with a single-quote character (&#x2018;). DYNACALC will swallow the quote, and treat the cell as a label.</para>
      <para>
        The data storage commands /S#L and /S#S default to the working data directory. For formatting information, see the section &#x2018;
        
          <xref linkend="__RefHeading___Toc2819_3093686648">Using Data Files</xref>
        
        &#x2019;.
      </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Titles</title>
      <para>The Titles command (/T) controls the operation of horizontal and/or vertical titles. Titles are columns and/or rows set aside by the DYNACALC user (that means you) to identify important areas of your worksheet at all times. Titles do not scroll off the screen when the displayed area changes. This lets you easily see, for example, the name of the salesman who did so well in October, even though the salesmen names are in column A, and October is in column L.</para>
      <para>When you call up /T, you get another menu:</para>
      <screen>B H N V ?</screen>
      <para>to which you respond with one of the title command letters, described in the following paragraphs.</para>
      <para>Title command B (<userinput>/TB</userinput>) turns on both horizontal and vertical titles together. Before you type this command, place the cursor just below and just to the right of the intersection of the horizontal and vertical titles.</para>
      <para>Title command H (<userinput>/TH</userinput>) turns on horizontal titles. Before you type this command, move the cursor just below the title row (below the bottom title row if you are using more than one). After you type <userinput>/TH</userinput>, try scrolling your data off the screen, and watch what happens to the title row(s). If vertical titles are already turned on, they will be left undisturbed.</para>
      <para>Title N (<userinput>/TN</userinput>) selects No titles, and disables any that might be turned on.</para>
      <para>Title command V (<userinput>/TV</userinput>) turns on vertical titles. Before you type this command, move the cursor just to the right of the title column (to the right of the rightmost title column if you are using more than one). After you type <userinput>/TV</userinput>, try scrolling your data off the screen, and watch what happens to the title column(s). If horizontal titles are already turned on, they will be left undisturbed.</para>
      <para>Whenever the titles feature is in use, you will find that you are unable to move the cursor to any column and/or row being used as a title. To get the cursor into these areas, turn off titles (<userinput>/TN</userinput>), do what you have to do, then turn the titles back on. All title information is saved by <userinput>/SS</userinput>.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Windows</title>
      <para>The windows command (/W) is one or the primary screen formatting controls. Normally, the screen displays a single window, or portions of the total worksheet. With the cursor movement controls you can move the window to any part of the worksheet. However, sometimes it is very handy to be able to see two widely separated areas of the worksheet at the same time. This is what the windows command allows.</para>
      <para>In addition, there are two formatting commands built into the window menu: Display and format. These don&#x2019;t really have much to do with the idea of two separate windows, but are at this command level because they each affect all cells in the current window.</para>
      <para>When you type /W, you will be prompted with this menu:</para>
      <screen>D F H N S U V ?</screen>
      <para>to which you should respond with one of the following single-letter commands:</para>
      <para>Window command D (<userinput>/WD</userinput>) toggles the value/formula display flag. This flag, which defaults to 'value' decides whether to print calculated values or actual data as entered. The primary use of the formula display mode is to tell at a glance whether a cell contains a formula or a constant. Of course, you could examine each cell by pointing to it, but the formula display mode gives you a whole window-full at a time. This mode affects the entire current window, and only the current window. That means that the other window can be set to the opposite display mode, and you can thus see the same area of your worksheet displayed both ways at the same time.</para>
      <para>Window command F (<userinput>/WF</userinput>) is used to change the default display format for all the cells in the current window. See the format command (/F) for details.</para>
      <para>Window command H (<userinput>/WH</userinput>) is used to create horizontal separation between the upper and lower portions of the screen. Each portion is then a separate window into the worksheet, and each can be moved and formatted independently of the other. Use the JUMP key (see '<xref linkend="key.assignment">Key Assignment Summary</xref>') to jump back and forth between the two windows. When you type <userinput>/WH</userinput>, the screen is split horizontally at the current row, so you may divide the screen into equal or unequal sections. The window in which the cursor resides is considered the 'current window'. Commands which affect a window will affect only the current window.</para>
      <para>Window command N (<userinput>/WN</userinput>) selects no splitting of the screen, and returns to a single window display. The current window is unchanged.</para>
      <para>Window command S (<userinput>/WS</userinput>) causes the two windows displayed to scroll synchronously. If the windows are divided horizontally, synchronization is in the horizontal direction; if they are divided vertically, they will then scroll vertically together. If there is only a single window this command is ignored.</para>
      <para>Window command U (<userinput>/WU</userinput>) Unsynchronizes the motion or the two displayed windows. If there is only a single window, this command is ignored.</para>
      <para>Window command V (<userinput>/WV</userinput>) is used to create a vertical separation between the left and the right portions of the screen. Each portion is then a separate window into the worksheet, and each can be moved and formatted independently of the other. Use the JUMP key (see '<xref linkend="key.assignment">Key Assignment Summary</xref>') to jump back and forth between the two windows. When you type <userinput>/WV</userinput>, the screen is split vertically at the current column, so you may divide the screen into equal or unequal sections. The window in which the cursor resides is considered the 'current window'. Commands which affect a window will affect only the current window.</para>
      <para>Note that it is not possible to have both vertical and horizontal window division at the same time; only two display windows are allowed.</para>
      <para>All information pertaining to window settings is saved by <userinput>/SS</userinput>, and will be restored upon loading a file with <userinput>/SL</userinput>.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Help</title>
      <para>The help command (<userinput>/?</userinput>) lets DYNACALC tell you all about itself. Most of the important information about DYNACALC in this manual can be displayed on your screen while you are using DYNACALC; in other words, the information is right there where you need it.</para>
      <para>The main help command gives you information about the main command menu, and then lets you choose to ask for more information, or return to normal operation. Just follow the prompts at the bottom of each Help screen.</para>
      <para>As you can imagine, all this text takes up quite a bit of room in your computer. If you need all the space you can get for a large worksheet, type <userinput>/AH</userinput> to delete all the Help messages from memory. Subsequent requests for Help will be ignored, unless you exit to OS-9 and reenter DYNACALC.</para>
      <para>Whenever helps are enabled, any OS-9 error messages required will be printed in English. If helps are disabled, only the OS-9 error number will be displayed. Refer to your OS-9 User&#x2019;s Manual for the error description.</para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>
