<?xml version="1.0"?>
<appendix xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Modifying Stylograph for Non-supported Serial Terminal</title>
  <para>
      If you have a serial terminal which is not listed in appendix C, then
      you should return your STYLOGRAPH disk to GREAT PLAINS COMPUTER
      COMPANY INC. for modification. When you return your disk, also
      include a copy of the portion of the manual which includes the control
      codes that it uses, or preferably, you may send a copy of the manual.
      Terminal updates will be done for a $50.00 charge.
  </para>
  <para>
      If you wish, and are capable of assembly code work, you may do the
      modifications yourself. The terminal driver consists of two different
      parts: a stack of pointers located $20 bytes above TRMBEG, and a
      stack of ASCII control sequences located at TRMSEQ. The source code
      for three different terminal drivers are included on you disk. They
      may be used as models for constructing your own terminal driver. The
      easiest course of action is to edit one of these files to create your
      own file.
  </para>
  <para>
      The first byte of the stack of pointers consists of the sum of some
      constants indicating the characteristics of the terminal. Those
      constants are listed in the source code. They specify the following
      characteristics:
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
              The dimensions of the screen. These are the "D"
              constants. If your terminal scrolls up whenever a character
              is put in the bottom right hand corner of the screen, you
              must specify the D2479 rather than the D2480 screen size.
              STYLOGRAPH only supports the screen sizes listed in the
              constants shown in the source code.
          </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
              Whether the cursor is addressed X (Column) then Y (Row),
              or, Y then X. If it is Y then X, then you must sum in the
              CYX constant.
          </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
              Whether $20 must be added to the cursor address. If your
              terminal requires that the lowest cursor address is a SPACE
              ($20) rather than a NUL ($00) then you must sum in the
              "CAD20" constant.
          </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
              Whether your terminal can scroll down. Many terminals
              can be made to scroll down by putting the cursor at the top
              of the screen and using the "insert line" function of the
              terminal. Other terminals have a scroll down function.
              Some will scroll down by moving the cursor to the top and
              bumping the cursor up. If your terminal can scroll down by
              using one of the sequences, you should sum in the "SSCD"
              constant.
          </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
          If our terminal has a line erase function, you should
          sum in the "LERF" constant. The next 13 bytes consist of
          pointers to the ASCII control sequences that are listed at
          TRMSEQ. A number <quote>1</quote> points to the first sequence. A number
          <quote>4</quote> points to the fourth sequence, etc. A zero indicates
          that the terminal does not have that function. The only
          functions that STYLOGRAPH absolutely requires are the
          cursor-move and the clear-screen functions.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <para>
    The actual sequences that are sent to the terminal are listed starting
    at TRMSEQ. They are listed in order and the last byte that is sent
    has the <quote>N</quote> bit set. The <quote>N</quote> bit is set by
    adding the constant <quote>N</quote> to the last character in the sequence.
</para>
  <para>
    Whenever a new terminal driver is made, all other terminal drivers are
    destroyed. That is, after these modifications are made you may no
    longer specify the terminal type on the calling line. Also, the
    terminal number must now be a <quote>1</quote>. The is normally set by an FCB in
    the source code, but can also be set by STYFIX. The FCB is at the
    beginning of the example terminal drivers.
</para>
  <para>
    After this new code has been assembled and a binary file created, it
    may be appended to STYLOGRAPH.
</para>
</appendix>
