<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <articleinfo>
    <title>OS9 OPERATING SYSTEM</title>
  </articleinfo>
  <section>
    <title>STYLOGRAPH OPERATION UNDER OS9</title>
    <para>
        Stylograph can be used very effectively under a multi-user
        environment such as OS9. Since Stylograph is highly interactive and
        uses dynamic screen formatting there are a couple of things to keep in
        mind. First of all, Stylograph is much easier to use at higher baud
        rates. Also, since OS9 is very I/O bound and Stylograph is constantly
        outputting characters to the screen, you should develop some operator
        habits which will reduce the demand on OS9. You should do most of
        your editing on the bottom of the screen since that reduces the amount
        that Stylograph has to update the screen. Also, if you operate in the
        insert mode with a RETURN on the right side of the insert line, this
        will reduce the updating that is required on that line. Scrolling and
        paging through the text also consume a lot of computer time so this
        should be kept to a minimum. None of these things will hurt the
        operation of Stylograph but if too many operators are scrolling or
        paging at the same time, the operation of the entire system will be
        slowed down. These considerations need not apply if you are using
        level one of OS9 and only have one operator on the system.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>INITAL SETUP</title>
    <para>
          When you receive the disk the following files should be on the root
          directory of the disk:
      </para>
    <informaltable frame="none" rowsep="0" colsep="0">
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1in"/>
        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="4in"/>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>FILE NAME</entry>
            <entry>FUNCTION</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>readme</entry>
            <entry>initial setup and description of file on this disk</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>stylo</entry>
            <entry>Stylograph program</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>styfix</entry>
            <entry>program for configuring Stylograph</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>styappen</entry>
            <entry>program for appending binary files to Stylograph</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>history</entry>
            <entry>text file listing previous updates and fixes to system</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>sty</entry>
            <entry>directory holding various Stylo related files</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>intro</entry>
            <entry>test file of part of manual for practice editing</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>styhlp1-6</entry>
            <entry>6 text files for assistance command</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>styps.d</entry>
            <entry>proportional spacing table for DIABLO</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>styps.b</entry>
            <entry>for Brother HR-15</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>styps.n</entry>
            <entry>proportional spacing table for NEC</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>styps.7</entry>
            <entry>proportional spacing table for 737/9</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>stytext</entry>
            <entry>source code of stylograph prompts and constants</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>sty.130</entry>
            <entry>source for SOROC IQ-130 terminal driver</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>sty.adm3</entry>
            <entry>source for ADM-3 terminal driver</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>sty.ct82</entry>
            <entry>source for CT-82 terminal driver</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
    <para>
          To set up Stylograph on your system, first establish a directory that
          contains the files contained in the Sty directory as received from
          GPCCI. The only files that are required in the Sty directory are:
          Styhp1-6. Styerr (COCO only), Stystat (COCO only). The rest of the
          files in the Sty directory are only for certain applications as
          needed. The Sty directory is a good place to keep them, however.
          Stylograph assumes that this directory will be called /D0/Sty, but
          this can be changed by using Styfix with option #6.
      </para>
    <para>
          If you are doing proportional spacing, rename the proper proportional
          spacing table (Styps.d, Styps.7, Styps.n, Styps.b (COCO only), to
          <quote>Styps</quote> and move it into your <quote>Sty</quote> directory or its equivalent.
          Then establish the Stylo file in your <quote>CMDS</quote> directory.
      </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>PRINTER DRIVERS</title>
    <para>
        Stylograph looks for a printer descriptor by the name /p1 by default.
        If you wish to change the default descriptor name, see the
        instructions under the STYFIX command.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>THE STYFIX PROGRAM</title>
    <para>
        STYFIX is an executable program and should be put in the CMDS
        directory of your disk. To execute STYFIX type the following:
    </para>
    <screen>
        styfix filename
    </screen>
    <para>
        where filename = stylo or mm or spell. STYFIX will use the program
        name to determine which of the three menus (STYLO, MM or SPELL) to bring
        up. The following explanations describe each of the three menus.
    </para>
    <section>
      <title>STYFIX STYLO</title>
      <para>
            This is the menu that appears if the filename is STYLO:
        </para>
      <screen>
------- STYLOGRAPH configuration program -------
        1. Set default terminal type.
        2. Printer menu.
        3. Set proportional table load at startup.
        4. Set maximum pages.
        5. List memory boundaries.
        6. Set default STY directory pathname.
        7. Set default data buffer size (work area).
        8. Return to OS-9.
        Choice?
    </screen>
      <para>
        Select the proper choice by typing the corresponding number followed
        by a carriage return (CR).
    </para>
      <para>
        If the choice is #1 of the STYLOGRAPH MENU the following prompt will appear:
    </para>
      <screen>
             Terminal number?
    </screen>
      <para>
        These numbers can be found on Appendix C PRINTER AND TERMINAL NUMBERS
        in the manual. Type the number followed by a carriage return and the
        MAIN MENU will appear ready for the next choice.
    </para>
      <para>
        If the choice is #2 of the STYLOGRAPH MENU the following menu will
        appear:
    </para>
      <screen>
        ------- PRINTER menu -------
             1. Set default printer type.
             2. Set default printer pathname.
             3. Return to main menu.
             Choice?
     </screen>
      <para>
         These options have to do with printer defaults.
     </para>
      <para>
         If the choice is #1 of the PRINTER MENU the following prompt will appear:
     </para>
      <screen>
                  Printer number?
     </screen>
      <para>
         These numbers can be found in Appendix C PRINTER AND TERMINAL NUMBERS
        in the manual. Type the number followed by a carriage return and the
        PRINTER MENU will appear ready for your next choice.
    </para>
      <para>
        If the choice is #2 of the PRINTER MENU the following prompt will
        appear:
    </para>
      <screen>
        Pathname(/p,/p1,/H0/STY/DICT etc.30 chars max)?
    </screen>
      <para>
        This prompt expects an OS9 pathname of not more than 30 characters
        giving the path (complete OS9 pathlist) of the desired printer.
    </para>
      <para>
        If the choice is #3 of the PRINTER MENU the program will return to the
        MAIN MENU.
    </para>
      <para>
        If the choice is #3 of the STYLOGRAPH MENU the following prompt will
        appear:
    </para>
      <screen>
        Load STYPS proportional spacing table at startup (Y/N)?
    </screen>
      <para>
        This prompt wants to know if the proportional spacing table should be
        loaded with STYLO to do proportional spaced printing. Type a Y or an N accordingly.
    </para>
      <para>
        If the choice is #4 of the STYLOGRAPH MENU the following prompt will appear:
    </para>
      <screen>
        This is the maximum number of printed pages
        that STYLO can edit or print at a given time.
        The number of characters or lines on each
        printed page is not critical. Typically 10
        to 40 pages. Numbers higher than necessary
        may waste data space!
        
        Maximum pages that Stylograph can edit?
    </screen>
      <para>
        The default value for STYLO is 20 (COCO OS9 STYLO 10) until changed by
        the user. This selection determines the number of printed pages that
        STYLO can work with at one time. The default value should normally be
        enough for working with text files. If there is more text in memory
        than will fit on the specified number of pages then you may not move
        the cursor below the last page. No other operations are affected,
        however, and no text is lost or destroyed.
    </para>
      <para>
If the choice is #5 of the STYLOGRAPH MENU the following table will appear:
    </para>
      <screen>
        LABEL     FUNCTION                         ADDRESS
        
        TXTBEG    Beginning of text area ----------- $0123
        TXTEND    End of text area ----------------- $4567
        BINEND    End of Stylograph binary code ---- $89AB
        TRMBEG    Beginning of terminal driver ----- $CDEF
        TRMSEQ    Beginning of terminal sequence --- $0123
        TRMEND    End of terminal driver ----------- $4567
    </screen>
      <para>
        This table displays various addresses for use with the STYAPPEN
        command (not available in COCO STYLO).
    </para>
      <para>
        If the choice is #6 of the STYLOGRAPH MENU the following prompt will appear:
    </para>
      <screen>
        Pathname(/p,/p1,/H0/STY/DICT etc.30 chars max)?
    </screen>
      <para>
        This prompt expects an OS9 pathname of not more than 30 characters
        giving the path (complete OS9 pathlist) of what is sent to you as the
        STY directory (for example on the disk received from GPCCI the
        complete pathlist for the STY directory is /d0/STY or /D1/STY 
        depending on the disk drive used). This directory (no matter what its
        name) should contain those files specified in the README file on the
        GPCCI supplied disk. These files include: styhlp_6, styerr(coco only),
        stypstat(coco only), styps_b, styps_d, styps_n, styps_7, intro,
        sty_ct82(not on coco), sty_adm3(not on coco), sty_130(not on coco),
        stytext(not on coco).
    </para>
      <para>
        If the choice is #7 of the STYLOGRAPH MENU the following prompt will appear:
    </para>
      <screen>
        This size is the default module permanent
        storage requirement. It has the same
        effect as the command line:
        
                  STYLO MYFILENAME #nk
        
        where n=number of kilobytes etc. This
        size can be increased from the command
        line but not decreased except from STYFIX.
        Minimum data buffer size in bytes?
        
        (Min = 6144 bytes Max = 65535 bytes)
    </screen>
      <para>
        This choice allows the module header of permanent storage requirement to
        be increased or decreased in size to adapt STYLO to use the amount of
        memory that is best suited to any specific system. The minimum is set
        due to the fact that STYLO requires approximately that amount for its
        own uses. The maximum is only limited by the largest contiguous memory
        block available on a system.
    </para>
      <para>
        If the choice is #8 of the STYLOGRAPH MENU then STYFIX will complete
        its task and return to the operating system.
    </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>STYFIX MM</title>
      <para>
        This is the menu that appears if the filename is MM:
    </para>
    <screen>
        ------- MAILMERGE configuration program -------

                1. Set default printer type.
                2. Set default STYPS pathname.
                3. Return to OS-9.
    </screen>
    <para>
        If the choice is #1 of the MAILMERGE MENU the following prompt will appear:
    </para>
    <screen>
        Printer number?
    </screen>
    <para>
        These numbers can be found in the Mail Merge Manual on page 4. Type the number
        followed by a carriage return and the MAILMERGE MENU will reappear ready for your
        next choice.
    </para>
    <para>
        If the choice is #2 of the MAILMERGE MENU the following prompt will appear:
    </para>
    <screen>
        Pathname(/p,/p1,/H0/STY/DICT etc. 30 chars max)?
    </screen>
    <para>
        This prompt expects an OS9 pathname of not more than 30 characters giving
        the path (complete OS9 filename) of the STYPS proportional spacing table file.
    </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>STYFIX SPELL</title>
      <para>
        This is the menu that appears if the filename is SPELL:
    </para>
    <screen>
        ------- SPELL CHECKER configuration program -------

                1. Set default primary dictionary path(DICT).
                   (/D1/STY/DICT, /h0/mydir/sam/dict, etc.)
                2. Set default secondary dictionary path(SUPP).
                   (/D1/STY/SUPP, /h0/mydir/sam/supp, etc.)
                3. Return to OS-9.
    </screen>
    <para>
        If the choice is #1 of the SPELL CHECKER MENU the following prompt will appear:
    </para>
    <screen>
        Pathname(/p,/p1,/H0/STY/DICT etc. 30 chars max)?
    </screen>
    <para>
        This prompt expects an OS9 pathname of not more than 30 characters giving
        the path (complete OS9 filename) of the DICT main directory file.
    </para>
    <para>
        If the choice is #2 of the SPELL CHECKER MENU the following prompt will appear:
    </para>
    <screen>
        Pathname(/p,/p1,/H0/STY/DICT etc. 30 chars max)?
    </screen>
    <para>
        This prompt expects an OS9 pathname of not more than 30 characters giving
        the path (complete OS9 filename) of the SUPP secondary or supplimentary directory file.
    </para>
    <para>
        If the choice is #2 of the SPELL CHECKER MENU then STYFIX will complete
        its task and return to the operating system.
    </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>MODIFYING STYLOGRAPH FOR NON-SUPPORTED SERIAL TERMINALS</title>
      <para>
      If you have a serial terminal which is not listed in appendix C, then
      you may return your Stylograph disk to us for modification. When
      you return your disk, also include a copy of terminal user's
      manual which includes the control codes. Terminal updates will be done
      for a $50.00 charge.
  </para>
      <para>
      If you wish, and are capable of assembly code work, you may do the
      modifications yourself. The terminal driver consists of two different
      parts: a stack of pointers located $20 bytes above TRMBEG, and a
      stack of ASCII control sequences located at TRMSEQ. The source code
      for two different terminal drivers, a CT-82 and an ADM-3A are
      included on you disk. They
      may be used as models for constructing your own terminal driver. The
      easiest course of action is to edit one of these files to create your
      own file. The method of modifying one of these drivers is explained in
      the Appendix D --- "MODIFYING STYLOGRAPH FOR NON-SUPPORTED SERIAL TERMINALS".
  </para>
      <para>
      After the new source code has been created, the binary file must be appended
      to the present Stylograph file by using the "styappen" program.
      Assuming that the new terminal driver is name "styterm" and the
      "styappen" file has been put in the "cmds" directory, the 
      following command should cause Stylograph to work with the new terminal:
  </para>
      <screen>
      styappen cmds/stylo styterm
  </screen>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>CHANGING TEXT CONSTANTS</title>
      <para>
        A text file by the name "stytext" is supplied on your disk. This file
        may be modified, assembled and appended to Stylograph to change any of
        the text constants. The procedures for changing this text file are
        explained in Appendix E of this manual.
    </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>PRINTING SPOOLED FILES</title>
      <para>
        Files that have been spooled to a disk for later printing, by means of
        the "SPOOL" command, can be printed as follows:
    </para>
      <para>
        For example suppose you have spooled a file "MYFILE" to "MYDIR" on
        drive /d1. This spooled file can be printed using the OS-9 "COPY"
        command as shown below:
    </para>
      <screen>
        chd /d1/mydir
        copy myfile /p
    </screen>
      <para>
        Do <emphasis>not</emphasis> use the right arrow (&gt;) symbol.
    </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</article>
