<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <articleinfo>
    <title>STYLOGRAPH USER'S MANUAL</title>
    <titleabbrev>STYLOGRAPH</titleabbrev>
  </articleinfo>
  <section>
    <title>AN OVERVIEW OF THE STYLOGRAPH WORD PROCESSING SYSTEM</title>
    <titleabbrev>OVERVIEW</titleabbrev>
    <para>The STYLOGRAPH text processing system is a very easy to use but
powerful method of creating and printing text. It allows you to
type text on a video terminal, modifying and correcting it as you
go, and then print it out when the complete text is finished. The
STYLOGRAPH system is cursor-orientated with dynamic screen
formatting. Cursor-based editing means that you may work on any
portion of the text by moving the cursor to that point. Dynamic
screen formatting means that the text is formatted on the screen in
the same way it will appear on the printed copy. The display is
continuously updated to show you how the text will appear. This is
a very important feature normally available only on very expensive
commercial word processing systems. It significantly reduces the
time that it takes to produce finished copy.</para>
    <section>
      <title>FULL FEATURE TEXT EDITING</title>
      <para>There is a full array of commands to help in the creation and
modification of the text. The text displayed on the screen may be
moved up, down, left or right. Also, the cursor can be moved to any
page or to any specified series of letters or words. The cursor
itself can be moved left, right, up, down, to any tab position, or
to the extreme left or right. Any block of text can be moved,
copied or deleted. You may also do a global replace so that all
occurrences of a given string will be replaced with or without a
<quote>prompt</quote> asking you if you wish the item replaced.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>OPERATOR CONVENIENCE</title>
      <para>At the beginning of the text, the operator normally types in a
few simple commands indicating the line length, left margin, and so
forth, and then enters the header and footer as they should appear.
After that point the operator need not worry about the formatting
of the page since it is taken care of automatically. Words that
extend beyond the end of the line are automatically removed and
placed on the next line. Headers and footers are also automatically
inserted so that the operator always knows what portion of the page
is being worked on. Ghost hyphens can also be entered so that if
the word falls at the end of a line, and a ghost hyphen has been
inserted, the hyphen will automatically be added.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>FLEXIBLE DISPLAY</title>
      <para>A command allows you to view the formatting commands or make
them disappear from the screen. Another command allows you to see
which characters will be modified at printout by underlining,
superscripting, boldface and so forth. A page status command allows
of you to see the current format values and other useful
information.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>COMPLETE FORMATTING CONTROL</title>
      <para>The text or individual lines may be centered, left justified, right justified, or right
and left justified. Tabs can be set or cleared at any point.
Spacing of the lines on the text is under complete operator control
with end of page, spacing, and vertical tab commands.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>POWERFUL PRINTING OPTIONS</title>
      <para>Underlining is supported by TTY type printers. For those people
who have specialty
printers there are a variety of additional capabilities
including:</para>
      <para>operator controllable pitch</para>
      <para>1.5 line spacing</para>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="bold">BOLDFACE</emphasis>
      </para>
      <para>superscript<superscript>1</superscript></para>
      <para>subscript<subscript>2</subscript></para>
      <para><phrase role="underline">underline</phrase>, <phrase role="overline">overline</phrase></para>
      <para>Also right and left justification of text is accomplished by
incremental printing and true proportional spacing is supported on
the specialty printers.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>OPERATING SYSTEM COMPATIBILITY</title>
      <para>STYLOGRAPH is fully compatible with the powerful OS-9 operating
system. Text prepared using STYLOGRAPH is directly usable by other software. (This
significantly aids software development since cursor based editing
allows full viewing of the text being worked on thereby reducing
errors and decreasing programming time). The size of the file being
edited is limited only by the capacity of the disk system. Files
may be loaded into the text at any point making it possible to
rapidly create made-up documents using portions of text that have
been previously saved to a text file. Also, to complement this
feature, any portion of a text may be saved to a text file for use
at a later point. The printer output may also be directed to a disk
file for later print spooling. Most disk operating system commands
are directly accessible without leaving the STYLOGRAPH system.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>COMPLETE INSTRUCTIONS</title>
      <para>The manual is written so that people with little or no
experience with computers can easily learn to use STYLOGHAPH in a
few hours. A text file is included which demonstrates most of the
features of STYLOGRAPH and allows the operator to practice most of
the functions. The logical arrangement of the commands and the
immediate display of the results greatly simplifies the learning
process. The manual also contains instructions for limited
modification of STYLOGRAPH for special applications.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
    <section>
      <title>SYSTEM REQUIREMENTS</title>
      <para>STYLOGRAPH, MAIL MERGE,
and SPELLCHECK are designed to operate under the OS-9 operating
system, either Level One or Level Two. With a Level One system,
about 15k of user space remains after STYLOGRAPH is loaded, which
is enough room for about 5 full A4 pages of text to be held in
memory at once, (workfiles can of course be much larger, by making
use of the <quote>NEWS</quote> command). A Level Two system will allow about 35k
of user space, enough for about 11 pages of text.</para>
      <para>The minimum system
configuration you require is your Dragon Data computer, with at
least 64k bytes of RAM, running the OS-9 operating system; a floppy
disk drive; and a television, or preferably a monochrome monitor.
(The monitor will generally give you a better picture than a
television). you can certainly run STYLOGRAPH with only one disk
drive, although two drives are more convenient.</para>
      <para>You can use almost any
printer with STYLOGRAPH, to print out your finished letters and
documents. STYLOGRAPH comes already configured to handle a wide
range of letter quality (daisy-wheel) printers, and allows you full
use of facilities such as proportional spacing, underline, bold,
subscripts and superscript. You can also use STYLOGRAPH equally
well with a simple printer, (such as a matrix printer), with none
of these facilities.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>GETTING STARTED</title>
      <para>PLEASE READ THIS SHORT
SECTION VERY CAREFULLY BEFORE ATTEMPTING TO USE STYLOGRAPH. WE
SUGGEST THAT WHILE YOU ARE LEARNING TO USE STYLOGRAPH YOU SHOULD
MAKE USE OF THE COMMAND AND KEY ASSIGNMENT SUMMARIES AT THE END OF
THIS MANUAL.</para>
      <note>
        <para>In this manual,
when we say that you should hit, for example, CONTROL-D, we mean
that you should hold down the CONTROL key and hit the D key. (For
the assignment of the CONTROL key on your keyboard, see the Key
Assignment Summary at the end of this manual).</para>
      </note>
      <para>The STYLOGRAPH package
from Dragon Data contains two items: this manual, and a single
floppy disk. Because of the risk of inadvertently damaging the disk or deleting the
files on it, you should NEVER use the disk for running STYLOGRAPH.
Use the 'backup' command available on OS-9 to copy the original
disk to a freshly formatted blank disk, and STORE THE ORIGINAL DISK IN A SAFE PLACE.
Refer to the <citetitle pubwork="book">OS-9 User's Manual</citetitle> for instructions
on how to use the 'backup' and 'format' commands.</para>
      <para>Now place the new disk
in drive d0 (drive zero). Change your execution and data
directories to the new disk:</para>
      <screen>
OS9: chx /d0/cmds chd /d0
</screen>
      <para>On the root directory
of the disk, which you can now inspect by</para>
      <screen>
OS9: dir
</screen>
      <para>you will find some
sample STYLOGRAPH workfiles and three directories - CMDS, STY, and SYS.
The CMDS (commands) directory contains the files that you need
to run STYLOGRAPH. You can inspect it by:</para>
      <screen>
os9: dir cmds
</screen>
      <informaltable frame="none" rowsep="0" colsep="0">
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1in"/>
          <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="4in"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>stylo</entry>
              <entry>the word processing program - STYLOGRAPH</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>mm</entry>
              <entry>the mail merge program - MAIL MERGE</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>spell</entry>
              <entry>the spell check program - SPELL CHECK</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>spelladd</entry>
              <entry>the program to add words to the spelling dictionary</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>spellsub</entry>
              <entry>the program to remove words from the spelling dictionary</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>spelldcm</entry>
              <entry>the program to decompile the spelling dictionary to a text file</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>spellcom</entry>
              <entry>the program to compile a text file into a spelling dictionary</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>styfix</entry>
              <entry>the program for customizing STYLOGRAPH</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>mmfix</entry>
              <entry>the program for customizing MAIL MERGE</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
      <para>Plus a few of the
commonly used OS-9 utility programs.</para>
      <para>STYFIX and MMFIX are
used to customize STYLOGRAPH and MAIL MERGE for your printer. The
supplied STYLOGRAPH and MAIL MERGE have been configured for your
Dragon computer with a simple matrix printer, (type 'P40' in the
System Configuration section of this manual), on the parallel
printer port '/p'. If you are using a different type of printer,
such as a daisy-wheel, you can either specify the printer type each
tin: you call STYLOGRAPH or MAIL MERGE, (see below), or you can
permanently change the type that STYLOGRAPH and MAIL MERGE assume
using STYFIX and MMFIX, (see the System Configuration section).</para>
      <para>The STY directory
contains files that are used by STYLOGRAPH, MAIL MERGE, and SPELL
CHECK. These are the STYHLP help files used by STYLOGRAPH, the
STYPS proportional spacing tables used by STYLOGRAPH and MAIL
MERGE, and the DICT spelling dictionary used by SPELLCHECK.</para>
      <para>The DICT dictionary is
very large, and you may want to make a separate SPELLCHECK disk.
The easiest way to do this is to make a backup copy of the
STYLOGRAPH disk, and then delete all the files not associated with
SPELLCHECK.</para>
      <para>The SYS directory
contains the OS-9 error messages file a 'errmsg', used by OS-9 when
reporting an error (such as <quote>Error #216 - Pathname not found</quote>).</para>
      <para>Note that you must have
the STYLOGRAPH disk in drive 0, as STYLOGRAPH expects to find
certain files that it needs in the directory /d0/STY.</para>
      <para>If you are using a
Dragon 64 computer and (you be not already in the 51 characters by
24 lines mode, use the 'go51' command to change the screen
format:</para>
      <screen>
OS9: go51
</screen>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>GETTING INTO AND OUT OF STYLOGRAPH</title>
      <para>You are now ready to
try out STYLOGRAPH. All you need to do is type:</para>
      <screen>
OS9: stylo
</screen>
      <para>To exit STYLOGRAPH at
any time and return to OS-9:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>hit the ESCAPE key to
enter the ESCAPE mode. (For the assignment of the ESCAPE key on
your keyboard, see the Key Assignment Summary at the end of this
manual).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>hit the <quote>/</quote> key to
return to the Supervisor mode, where you will see the main command
menu.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>use the <quote>,</quote> key to move
down the menu. If you have text that you wish to save, move to the
line 'Save and Return', hit RETURN, and answer the questions
STYLOGRAPH gives you. If you just wish to exit STYLOGRAPH, move to
the line 'Return', hit RETURN and answer <quote>Y</quote> to 'Is the text
secure' and 'are you sure?'</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>You can always return
to the ESCAPE mode by hitting the ESCAPE key. You should also use
the ESCAPE key to return to the ESCAPE mode when you want to exit
from a HELP display. Don't be afraid to experiment - it's the
quickest way to learn.</para>
      <para>To try out the sample
workfile, 'intro'
use:</para>
      <screen>
OS9: stylo intro #15k
</screen>
      <para>The '#15k' is a request
to OS-9, asking OS-9 to give STYLOGRAPH 15k bytes, (15360 bytes),
of workspace. This is a reasonable upper limit on OS-9 Level One.
On OS-9 Level Two, 30k would be a reasonable upper limit.</para>
      <section>
        <title>WORKING WITH TWO DISK DRIVES</title>
        <para>If you have two disk
driven, you can use a separate disk for your workfiles. Format a
disk, put it in drive d1, and change your current data directory to
that disk by:</para>
        <screen>
OS9: chd /d1
</screen>
        <para>If there is enough free
space on your OS-9 system disk, you may find it more convenient to
have the STYLOGRAPH programs on your system disk. To do this, copy
the files in the CMDS directory of the STYLOGRAPH disk to the CMDS
directory of your system disk. Refer to the description of the copy
program in the <citetitle pubwork="book">OS-9 User's Manual</citetitle>.
Next make a directory 'STY' on your system disk, e.g.</para>
        <screen>
OS9: makdir /d0/STY
</screen>
        <para>and copy the files in
the STY directory on your STYLOGRAPH disk to the new STY directory
on your system disk.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>WORKING WITH ONE DISK DRIVE</title>
        <para>If you have only one
disk drive, your text files will be on your STYLOGRAPH disk. This
means that whenever your disk becomes full you must make a fresh
STYLOGRAPH disk. The easiest way to do this is to take a second
backup copy of your original STYLOGRAPH disk, and use it as a
master disk for creating new disks using 'backup'. In order to make
more efficient use of the disk spaces you might like to delete all
the SPELLCHECK files, especially the DICT dictionary, which is very
large, and have a separate SPELLCHECK disk. When you want to
SPELLCHECK a text file, copy it onto your SPELLCHECK disk.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>STARTING STYLOGRAPH</title>
      <para>STYLOGRAPH can be
started in three different ways. The first and most common way is
to enter the STYLOGRAPH command followed by the text file that you
wish to edit. The command line would look something like this :</para>
      <screen>
OS9: stylo letter
</screen>
      <para>This would cause
STYLOGRAPH to be called and the text file by the name 'letter' to
be loaded in. If no such file name exists on the disk then no file
will be loaded but STYLOGRAPH will remember the name in case you
want to use it when you save the file at a later time.</para>
      <para>The second method is to
call STYLOGRAPH specifying both an input and output file. A typical
command line from OS-9 might look like this:</para>
      <screen>
OS9: stylo letter1 letter2
</screen>
      <para>This would cause the
file by the name 'letter1' to be loaded by STYLOGRAPH. The file
name 'letter2' would be remembered by STYLOGRAPH so you can save
the file under that name when you are finished editing. If two
files are listed when STYLOGRAPH is called, the first file MUST
exist on the disk or an error will result.</para>
      <para>The third method is to
specify no file name at all such as:</para>
      <screen>
OS9: stylo
</screen>
      <para>In this case STYLOGRAPH
is called but no file will be loaded into memory. This method is
normally not used since you will usually want to save the file when
it is completed. It can be useful when you want to create a short
letter or memo and do not want to save it on the disk.</para>
      <para>You should be aware
that there is no absolute necessity for specifying files at all
when calling STYLOGRAPH since files may be loaded or saved under
any name at any time. You can look at the current input and output
file names by using the PAGE STATUS command which is explained in
the CONTROL COMMANDS section of this manual.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>USING DIFFERENT TERMINALS AND PRINTERS</title>
      <para>STYLOGRAPH must know what kind of terminal<footnote><para>The configuration of terminal type is not available on Dragon 64 or the Color Computer</para></footnote>
and printer you are using before it will work correctly.
You may configure STYLOGRAPH for your particular equipment by using
the <quote>STYFIX</quote> command which is included on your STYLOGRAPH disk.
The operation of this command is explained in the
<quote>Operating System Notes</quote> section of this manual.
You may also specify the terminal and printer on the calling line.
This portion of the command consists of a <quote>+</quote> sign,
a <quote>T</quote> for terminal or a <quote>P</quote> for printer,
and a number specifying the particular equipment.
The terminal and printer numbers are listed in the system
configuration section of this manual. A command line for specifying
a Diablo printer and a SOROC IQ-130 terminal would look like this:</para>
      <screen>
OS9: stylo letter +T3 +P0
</screen>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>EXPANDING THE PAGE LIMIT</title>
      <para>There is one additional
option that may be specified on the calling line from OS-9. The
maximum number of pages that STYLOGRAPH can work with can be
changed. STYLOGRAPH defaults to a maximum of 22. This should be
enough for most applications but in some circumstances where there
are many short lines such as with a mailing list it may be
desirable to increase the maximum number of pages. This maximum can
also be set with the STYFIX command. If you have more pages in
memory than STYLOGRAPH will allow, you will not be able to move the
cursor beyond the last page even though the rest of the text will
be visible on the screen. Also, STYLOGRAPH will prevent you from
inserting text on the last line of the last page. To increase the
number of pages by a calling line option you may use the <quote>+Mx</quote>
option. The <quote>x</quote> refers to the number of pages. For example, the
following line would increase the maximum number of pages to
35:</para>
      <screen>
OS9: stylo letter +M35
</screen>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>HOW STYLOGRAPH WORKS</title>
      <para>STYLOGRAPH is always in
one of three operating modes. These are the ESCAPE, INSERT, and
SUPERVISOR modes. Each mode has its own special characteristics.
After calling STYLOGRAPH from OS-9 you are in the SUPERVISOR mode.
In this mode all of the keys on the terminal have special meanings.
A cluster of 12 keys on the right side of the keyboard is used to
move the cursor around on the screen, move the screen up and down
or change to one of the other operating modes. The letters on the
keys have no special meaning since they are arranged to make their
functions easy to remember and use. For example, to move the cursor
left, right, up or down you will use keys that are arranged in the
corresponding positions in the cluster. There are several keys on
the left side of the keyboard that are used to find, replace,
duplicate, and move portions of the text round. On these keys the
letter signifies its function. So, for example, the <quote>F</quote> key is used
to Find some part of the text.</para>
      <para>In the INSERT mode
STYLOGRAPH ants very much like a typewriter. This is the mode you
will be in when you are typing (also called <quote>entering</quote>) the text.
There are several important differences, however. You do not have
to watch for the end of the line and insert a carriage return since
STYLOGRAPH automatically puts a word on the next line if it is too
large for the previous line. Also, if you make a mistake, you can
simply backspace over your mistake and retype it. The major
difference between typing on a typewriter and using STYLOGRAPH is
that there are also FORMAT COMMANDS that can be entered while using
STYLOGRAPH. These commands are typed in like normal text and cause
the appearance of the text to change in some way. For example,
there are format commands that can change the length of the lines
and the size of the margin. These FORMAT COMMANDS are displayed on
the screen but do not appear on the printed copy.</para>
      <para>The SUPERVISOR mode is
used to start the printing and to interact with OS-9. In this mode
the text is not displayed on the screen. This mode is menu driven
and self-prompting. This means that you will be given a list of
actions that you can take. After making your choice you may be
asked one or more questions. This method of printing and
interacting with OS-9 is very simple and takes almost no practice
to use.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>LEARNING THE SYSTEM</title>
      <para>Most parts of this
manual are designed so that very little knowledge of computer
systems is needed to use it effectively. Some knowledge of OS-9 is
needed, however, so that you can get STYLOGRAPH started and handle
the disk files that are created. Normally it will take a person
with reasonable typing skills only a few hours to start using
STYLOGRAPH competently. The best way to learn to use STYLOGRAPH is
to sit down in front of the terminal and practice all of the
commands as they are explained in the Tutorial at the end of this
manual. After going through the Tutorial you should go through this
manual to learn all of the functions not explained in the tutorial.
A practice text with the name <quote>INTRO</quote> is included on the supplied
disk. This is an ideal text to work with initially to show how
STYLOGRAPH works. To load this text simply enter (type) the
following command line from the disk operating system:</para>
      <screen>
OS9: stylo intro
</screen>
      <para>This file is the
overview section of the manual. By using this file you can see how
a STYLOGRAPH file looks on the screen and also how the printed
output will look. When working with this file you need not worry
about making mistakes or destroying it since you will normally not
be saving it. You should experiment freely so you can become
completely familiar with the system. After you have experimented
with this text and are familiar with the STYLOGRAPH text processing
system you should then try to start creating your own text files
from scratch.</para>
      <para>Another very useful
feature of STYLOGRAPH is that it is virtually impossible to type
too fast. Many times while you are entering text, STYLOGRAPH will
be readjusting lines below the cursor. For example, if you type in
something which causes a word at the end of the line to be bumped
off to the next line, STYLOGRAPH will immediately start rewriting
all of the following lines. You do not have to wait for this to be
completed. You may continue typing and STYLOGRAPH will finish the
rest of the screen without missing any characters that are being
entered. The line that you are typing on will always be displayed
correctly even though the rest of the screen may be in the process
of being updated.</para>
      <para>An important advantage
that STYLOGRAPH has over most other word processing systems is that
formatting is done on the screen. This makes learning the system
especially easy since the effects of most of the commands are
immediately visible. There are some differences between the display
on the screen and the printed outputs however. Spaces between the
lines (for example, if you are double spacing) are not shown on the
screen. This is so you can view as much text as possible on the
screen without scrolling up or down. The left margin is also not
displayed on the screen. Several special printing characteristics
such as underlining, proportional spacing, and so forth cannot be
displayed on the screen because of limitations of the display
device. Also it is possible to insert special printer commands in
the text. These commands will, of course, not actually be printed
out as text. but sent as invisible control sequences.</para>
      <para>You will find that
almost any common text processing task can easily be accomplished
using the STYLOGRAPH word processing system. Often a re-reading of
the manual will help in devising new methods of making the word
processing task easier. Every user of STYLOGRAPH eventually
develops their own <quote>tricks of the trade</quote>. For example, most people
find that it is unnecessary to enter the header and the footer
information at the beginning of each editing session since it is
easier to create a file with this information already on it and
then call it in at the beginning of each new text file.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>ESCAPE MODE</title>
    <para>The escape mode is a
kind of <quote>home base</quote> for all of the various functions of the
STYLOGRAPH word processor. It may be entered at any time simply by
hitting the ESCAPE key on the keyboard. (For the assignment of the
ESCAPE key on your keyboard, see the Key Assignment section at the
end of this manual). This will cause the text to be displayed on
the screen and allow you to do a number of important editing
functions.</para>
    <para>Many of the
characteristics of the display will be explained later but it is
important to understand the meaning of a couple of the
characteristics from the start. The broken vertical lines on the
right of the screen indicate that the line ends with a user-entered
<quote>RETURN</quote>. Lines that end with a hyphen at the far right of the
screen are processor created lines, such as the headers and
footers. and were not typed in at the place that they actually
appear on the screen. The exact way in which the display is
modified and created will become clearer as you become more
familiar with the system. If there is no text in the memory of the
computer, only the line indicating the first page and a single
<quote>RETURN</quote> at the right of the screen will appear on the screen.</para>
    <section>
      <title>CURSOR CONTROL</title>
      <para>There are five keys
which control the position of the cursor on the screen. These keys
are arranged in the shape of a cross to make it easy to remember
their functions:</para>
      <screen>
                           I
                         J K L
                           ,
</screen>
      <para>The centre key in this
cross is the <quote>K</quote> key with the four keys <quote>JIL,</quote> on the outside. The
top key <quote>I</quote> moves the cursor up. The bottom key <quote>,</quote> moves the
cursor down, and the <quote>J</quote> and <quote>L</quote> keys move it left and right
respectively. The <quote>K</quote> key is a special express key which moves the
cursor from one end of the line to the other. Hitting this key once
will move the cursor to the far left and hitting it twice will move
it to the far right. You should practice moving the cursor to
various parts of the screen so you can see how it works.</para>
      <para>You will notice several
important characteristics of the cursor. The cursor will only move
to a portion of the screen in which a character (a character is a
letter, number, punctuation, or space) has previously been entered,
so that the cursor will sometimes unexpectedly jump rapidly from
place to place. If you move the cursor to a portion of the text in
which the lines are right and left justified, you will find there
are some spaces that the cursor cannot move to. This occurs because
these spaces were not actually typed in but were added by
STYLOGRAPH to even out the lines. If you can move the cursor to a
space it means that a <quote>SPACE</quote> from the keyboard was entered there.
If you cannot move the cursor there, then no space character exists
at that place.</para>
      <para>You will notice that it
is impossible to move the cursor off the top or bottom of the text.
If you try to do this you will hear the error bell. (To find out
what error you have made, hold down the <quote>CONTROL</quote> and depress the
<quote>N</quote> key, once to display the error message and again to return to
the ESCAPE mode). The cursor cannot be moved to the <quote>processor
created</quote> lines at the top and the bottom of the page, (the header
and footer), since these have been inserted by STYLOGRAPH and can
only be changed by editing at the point where they were defined
earlier in the text. The text will automatically scroll up or down
if you try to move the cursor off the bottom or top of the
screen.</para>
      <para>The tab key can also be
used to move the cursor. To move to the next defined tab location
hold down the <quote>CONTROL</quote> key and depress the <quote>T</quote> key. This function
is explained more fully in the section on CONTROL commands.
Sometimes the TAB function will not cause the cursor to move. This
means that a character does not exist at the next tab position.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>SCROLLING UP AND DOWN</title>
      <para>The four keys <quote>UO.M</quote>
located in the corners of the cursor control keys are for scrolling
up and down:</para>
      <screen>
                         U I O
                         J K L
                         M , .
</screen>
      <para>The <quote>U</quote> key cause the
whole screen to move up one line and the <quote>M</quote> key cause it to move
down. The <quote>O</quote> and <quote>.</quote> keys cause the screen to move up or down
respectively by the size of the screen. These keys are useful for
rapidly scanning through the text since new text will appear on the
screen as rapidly as the terminal can rewrite the screen. The <quote>O</quote>
key, for example, causes the text to be moved up so that the line
that appeared on the bottom of the screen now appears on the top.
The easiest way to remember the effects of the <quote>O</quote> and of <quote>.</quote> keys
is to keep in mind that moving your finger up to the <quote>O</quote> key causes
the text to move up and moving your finger down causes the text to
move down.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>SCROLLING LEFT AND RIGHT</title>
      <para>Hitting the <quote>7</quote> key
causes the entire screen to shift 25 characters to the left and
hitting the <quote>9</quote> key causes it to move 25 characters to the right.
This is the way text is normally displayed. These commands are
useful when the lines are wider than the screen. If part of the
text extends off the screen you will see arrows at the edge to
indicate this. If there is text extending bar to the left of the
screen there will be left pointing arrows fish on the left side. If
the text extends off to the right side, you will see right pointing
arrows <quote>&gt;</quote> on the right side.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>FINDING A PAGE</title>
      <para>Every page, as it
appears on the screen, has a serial page number. This number
appears on the page boundary which will look like this:</para>
      <screen>
---------- PAGE 5 ----------
</screen>
      <para>This number is to help
you keep track of your place in the text and to provide a
convenient way of getting from one place in the text to another. To
move to a given page hit the pop's key and a message will appear on
the screen like this:</para>
      <screen>
*********** PAGE=
</screen>
      <para>Type in the page number
that you want and hit RETURN. If you enter a number which is larger
than the number of pages available, the cursor will move to the
last line and the error bell will ring. Thin provides a convenient
way of mooing to the bottom of the text. Entering another he'd
instead of a number will move the cursor to the beginning of the
text in memory. As with virtually all other commands, you may hit
the ESCAPE key at any time to return to the ESCAPE mode without
taking any action.</para>
      <para>The number that is used
in the page command and which appears on the page boundary is
called the <quote>serial</quote> page number. It is important to remember that
the serial page number may not be the same as the <quote>printed</quote> page
number. The printed page number is set by a format command that is
explained later. The printed page number can appear in the header
(top margin) or footer (bottom margin) of the page.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>FINDING A STRING</title>
      <para>A string consists of
one or more characters. Words, phrases, numbers, or even single
characters are called strings. You may move the cursor to any given
string by using the <quote>F</quote> command. When you hit the <quote>F</quote> key a space
will open up at the top of the screen and the following message
will appear:</para>
      <screen>
*** FIND {
</screen>
      <para>Enter the string you
want to find and hit RETURN. The cursor will then move to the next
occurrence of that string and the following message will
appear:</para>
      <screen>
*** STOP (RET) OR CONTINUE (SP)?
</screen>
      <para>This means that to stop
and leave the cursor in its present position, hit the RETURN key.
To continue on to the next occurrence of the string, hit the space
bar. This allows you to move rapidly through the text to find a
particular portion of the text. If the string does not exist below
the cursor, the screen will return to normal and the error bell
will ring. Remember that the FIND command will only search for
strings below the cursor so if you want to search the entire text
you must move the cursor to the top first using the <quote>PP</quote>
command.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>REPLACING A STRING</title>
      <para>You may replace one
string with another with the REPLACE, <quote>R</quote>, command. This command is
similar to the FIND command except that it will not only find the
string but it will replace the string with a second string. When
you hit the <quote>R</quote> key the following message will appear:</para>
      <screen>
*** REPLACE {
</screen>
      <para>Enter the string you
want replaced, hit return, and the next message will appear:</para>
      <screen>
*** WITH {
</screen>
      <para>Enter the replacement
string, hit RETURN, and the cursor will move to the next occurrence
of the first string with the following message:</para>
      <screen>
REPLACE (Y-N-A)?
</screen>
      <para>To replace the string
type in a <quote>Y</quote> for yes. If you decide not to replace the string,
enter a <quote>N</quote> for no. If you want to replace all of the strings
without being asked, hit the <quote>A</quote> for all. Unless you know exactly
what you are doing you should not use the <quote>A</quote> option since you will
not be able to see the strings before and after they have been
replaced. After you have responded, unless you took the again
option a message will appear asking you if you want to continue or
not as it did with the FIND command:</para>
      <screen>
*** STOP (RET) OR CONTINUE (SP)?
</screen>
      <para>Hit the RETURN if you
want to stop at this point and hit the space bar if you want to go
on to the next occurrence of the string. As with the FIND command,
this will only search for strings which are below the cursor.
Again, remember that the ESCAPE key may be hit at any time if you
want to go back to the normal display. The REPLACE function has one
additional feature which may be useful if you want to replace or
add CARRIAGE RETURNS. This could be used if you have an old text
file, that was prepared using a line orientated editor: which has a
number of RETURNS that must be removed. While using the FIND or
REPLACE, the <quote>|</quote> character can be entered as a substitute for the
RETURN. For example, to replace the <quote>RETURNS</quote> with a space, you
would enter the <quote>|</quote> and a SPACE so the screen would appear as
follows:</para>
      <screen>
REPLACE {|}
WITH {
</screen>
      <para>You could then go down
through the text and selectively replace only those RETURNS that
need to be removed.</para>
      <para>The FIND and REPLACE
commands can do a search for both upper and lower case characters
by hitting CONTROL-U at the end of the string to find, instead of
the RETURN key, as would normally be the case. At that point, the
search would disregard the ease of the characters in conducting its
search for the desired string.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>MOVING A STRING</title>
      <para>There are many times
during text editing that you will want to move a string from one
place to another. This is easily accomplished with the SAVE, <quote>S</quote>
and WITHDRAW, <quote>W</quote> functions. To do this you must first set of a a
marker at the end of the string. This is done by moving the cursor
to the end of the string and entering two marker characters <quote>}}</quote>.
Do not worry about these unwanted marker characters appearing in the
text since they will automatically disappear when you save the
text. Now move the cursor to the beginning of the string and hit
the <quote>S</quote> key indicating a SAVE. The text between the cursor and the
markers will then disappear from the screen. Then move the cursor
to the place that you want the text to appear and hit the <quote>W</quote> key
to withdraw the text. This is a very useful command but it takes
some thought and planning to use correctly since you must include
the correct number of spaces and/or returns for the text to be
formatted after you are finished. It is not a particularly serious
matter if you have made an error, however, since the errors are
normally easily correctable.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>DUPLICATING A STRING</title>
      <para>Duplicating a string is
very similar to moving a string. This is an especially useful
feature if a particular string occurs many times. By using this
command you will not have to re-enter the string every time it is
needed. To duplicate a string you must set a pair of markers and
SAVE the string as you did when moving a string. The only
difference is that when you want the string to reappear at the
cursor you enter a <quote>D</quote> to duplicate the string. You may do this as
often as you wish. The last place that you want to duplicate the
string you must enter <quote>W</quote> to withdraw the text, thus leaving the
SAVE buffer available for another SAVE command.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>REMOVING TEXT</title>
      <para>The easiest method of
erasing (removing) a large portion of the text is to use the ZAP,
<quote>Z</quote> command. To use this function, set a couple of markers at the
end of the string that you want to delete and move the cursor to
the beginning of the string. Hit the <quote>Z</quote> key and a message will
appear similar to this:</para>
      <screen>
*** DELETE 345 CHARACTERS?
</screen>
      <para>Answer with a <quote>Y</quote> for
yes and a <quote>N</quote> for no. This message is so you can be sure that you
are deleting the correct number of characters and will not
accidentally delete a
large portion of your text. There are a few other ways of deleting
text but these will be explained later.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>SINGLE CHARACTER OVERWRITE</title>
      <para>One of the most common
typographical errors to make is to hit the wrong key. STYLOGRAPH
has a convenient way of correcting this in the ESCAPE mode. You can
hit the <quote>1</quote> (number one) key and the next key you hit will
overwrite the character that the cursor is on. This command is easy
to remember because you are overwriting <quote>1</quote> character.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>SINGLE CHARACTER INSERT</title>
      <para>Another common
typographical error is to simply miss a key. To insert just one
character just move the cursor to the point where you want to
insert the character, hit the up arrow <quote>^</quote> and the next key that
you hit will be inserted in front of the character under the
cursor. All of the characters under and to the right of the cursor
will be bumped to make room.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>SUPERVISOR AND INSERT MODES</title>
      <para>You may enter the
SUPERVISOR mode by hitting the <quote>/</quote> key and the INSERT mode by
hitting the <quote>;</quote> key. There are separate sections in this manual
fully explaining these modes.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>INSERT MODE</title>
    <para>The INSERT mode is the
mode that you will be spending the most time in, since this is the
mode that is actually used to enter text. Before entering text you
must move the cursor to the point that you would like to start
entering text. You then leave the ESCAPE mode and enter the INSERT
MODE by hitting the <quote>;</quote> key once. At this point the cursor line
will have a different appearance to make it easier to enter the
text and to indicate that you are in the INSERT mode. The text to
the left of the cursor will appear normally on the left but the
text to the right will be put on the far right with a string of
hyphens in between. The number of hyphens indicates how much room
there is on the line before a word will be bumped down to the next
line. On some terminals the shape of the cursor will also change or
it may change from flashing to solid to indicate that you are in
the INSERT mode.</para>
    <para>When in the INSERT mode
you can type in the text just as you would on a typewriter. If you
make a mistake you may simply backspace over your error and
continue typing. Use the BACKSPACE key to do this (For the
assignment of the BACKSPACE key on your keyboard, see the Key
assignment section at the end of this manual). You should not hit
the RETURN as you approach the end of the line since STYLOGRAPH
automatically picks up the word at the end of the line and puts it
on the next line if it is too long. All of the text, with the
exception of the line you are typing will, as always, be formatted
as it will appear on the printed copy.</para>
    <para>RETURNS (these are
equivalent to <quote>carriage returns</quote> on a typewriter) are only used
when you want to start the next line at the beginning of the line.
You would start a new paragraph or set up neatly arranged columns
by starting the line with a RETURN. Any time you want some text to
appear in a certain column of the page, such as in charts and
tables, you must start out the line with a RETURN. The presence of
the RETURN is always indicated by a broken vertical line on the far
right of the screen.</para>
    <para>There are a couple of
things to keep in mind when placing the cursor before starting to
enter text. If you are inserting text somewhere inside a line it
makes the most sense to put the cursor on top of a space and then
enter a space as the first character. This assures that the words
that you are entering will always have a space before and after
them as they would normally have when you are done. If you are
starting a complete new tine which starts at the left side of the
screen, it is usually easiest to move the cursor to the previous
RETURN and enter a RETURN as the first character. This will usually
cause the next line to be completely empty and will reduce
distracting cursor movement on some terminals.</para>
    <section>
      <title>CHARACTER MODS</title>
      <para>While you are entering
text you may specify that the characters you are entering will have
some kind of modification when they are printed such as
underlining, superscript, boldface, and so forth. These character
modifications are done with <quote>CONTROL</quote> key combinations. To start
underlining characters hit CONTROL-U and continue entering text.
('CONTROL-U' means 'hold down the CONTROL key and press the U key'.
For the assignment of the CONTROL key on your keyboard, see the Key
Assignment section at the end of this manual). When you want to
stop underlining hit the UNMOD key. BOLDFACE works in the same way
except that CONTROL-B starts the boldface.</para>
      <para>There are five
different kinds of modifications that can be specified: (1)
underlining, (2) overlining, (3) boldface, (4) superscript, and (5)
subscript. Any logical combination of the five can be specified by
hitting the appropriate <quote>CONTROL</quote> keys :</para>
      <informaltable frame="none" rowsep="0" colsep="0">
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1in"/>
          <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="2in"/>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Key</entry>
              <entry>Function</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>U</entry>
              <entry>underline</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>O</entry>
              <entry>overline</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>I</entry>
              <entry>superscript</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>K</entry>
              <entry>subscript</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>B</entry>
              <entry>boldface</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
      <para>As an example, you
might want to have a superscripted character which you want to be
in boldface with an underline. To do this enter CONTROL-U,
CONTROL-I, and CONTROL-B, one after another. Then enter the
character that you want modified. Now hit the UNMOD key to stop
modifying characters in this way and continue entering text.</para>
      <para>On some terminals the
modified characters will appear in low intensity, indicating that
they have been modified. On other terminals the characters will be
indicated by a <quote>reverse</quote> field. You may look at the modification by
using the <quote>view</quote> key (CONTROL-V). Enter CONTROL-V and all of the
character modifications will be displayed. Hit the CONTROL-V key
again and the display will return to normal. On the example just
given in the previous paragraph, the modified character would be
replaced by a <quote>C</quote> when the VIEW key is hit. The meaning of these
characters is listed in the Viewed Character Modifications section
of this manual or you can use the <quote>ASSIST</quote> command which will be
explained later.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>GHOST HYPHENS</title>
      <para>You may enter normal
hyphens as you are entering text and STYLOGRAPH will automatically
break the word at the hyphen if it falls off the end of the line.
The only potential problem with this is that if you modify text at
some later point, the hyphenated word might appear in the centre of
the line with the hyphen still there. You would then have to remove
the hyphen. One way round this problem is to insert ghost hyphens
as you are entering text. When you come to a point, normally in a
long word, where you think a hyphen may be needed, hit CONTROL-G.
The hyphen will not normally appear on the screen at this point.
You then continue entering text. The ghost hyphen will
automatically appear and disappear depending on whether the word
falls at the end of the line or not.</para>
      <para>There are a couple of
things to keep in mind about ghost hyphens. If you are using right
and left justified text the hyphens are often not really needed.
This is especially true if you are using a <quote>speciality</quote> printer
version of STYLOGRAPH since the characters will be evenly spaced
throughout the line. Also, it is often most convenient to go back
through the text and insert ghost hyphens in the ESCAPE mode just
before the final printout so you need not worry about inserting
them while entering text.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>LONG LINES</title>
      <para>When you are working
with lines that are wider than the screen STYLOGRAPH will always
keep the cursor on the screen by shifting the line right or left if
needed so you can see what you are typing. This means that at times
the position of the line may be different from the rest of the
screen. The line will return to normal when you go back to the
ESCAPE made.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>FORMAT COMMANDS</title>
    <para>Format commands are
entered while you are in the INSERT mode. These tell STYLOGRAPH how
the text is to be formatted on the screen and at printout time. The
format commands start in the first column with a comma followed by
the command. The format command must <citetitle>ALWAYS</citetitle> be proceeded by
a RETURN and followed by a RETURN. In many cases the format command
is followed by a number or a character. There must always be a
space between the command and the number or character.</para>
    <para>Since these commands do
not appear on the printout it is often desirable to view the screen
without them. This is done with the FORMAT command (CONTROL-F). To
make the format command disappear from the display press CONTROL-F.
To return the screen to normal, press CONTROL-F again.</para>
    <para>STYLOGRAPH starts out
with format commands and values that are preset. These preset commands are called
default values. For example, if you enter no format commands in
your text, STYLOGRAPH will use the default value of 66 lines for
the page length. To change the page length you must enter a format
command. The normal default values are listed in the Command
Summary section.</para>
    <para>It is possible that
format commands will be entered incorrectly. For example, you could
forget to put a space between the format command and the number,
which would be an error. In this case STYLOGRAPH would simply
ignore the command altogether. The error bell will then sound
whenever the cursor moves from the erroneous line to the next line,
indicating that there has been an error.</para>
    <para>Also, you will notice
that many format commands require no numbers (also called format
parameters). Even for those commands that need a number, you may
omit the number and STYLOGRAPH will automatically use the smallest
sensible number. So. for example, the following two format commands
have the same meaning:</para>
    <screen>
,ce
,ce 1
</screen>
    <para>These are centring
commands and in both cases will cause only one line to be
centred.</para>
    <para>A brief description of
each of the format commands follows. Most of the commands are used
at some point in the INTRO text file so you can see how they work.
The best way to learn their use is to try each of them and then
observe the result. Where a command needs a number, we have used an
X to represent the number. Where a command needs a character as a
parameter, we have used C to represent the character.</para>
    <section>
      <title>,ce X CENTRING</title>
      <para>To centre a line or
lines simply type in the centre command and enter the number of
lines you want centred in place of the X. If you only want to
centre one line you may omit the number. For example, the following
two lines are legitimate centring commands:</para>
      <screen>
,ce 4
,ce
</screen>
      <para>The command on the
first line would centre the next four lines and the command on the
next line would centre only one. It only makes sense to centre a
line which has been proceeded with a RETURN and which is followed
by a RETURN so you will know exactly where the beginning and end of
the line will be. The following lines are not legal format
lines:</para>
      <screen>
,ce4
 ,ce
</screen>
      <para>The first command is
incorrect because there is no space between the command and the
number while the second is incorrect because it does not start in
the first column.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>,rj X RIGHT JUSTIFICATION</title>
      <para>Right justification
works exactly like the centring command except that the following
line or lines are set to the far right of the page. The following
would be legal right justification commands:</para>
      <screen>
,rj 3
,rj
</screen>
      <para>The first command would
right justify three lines and the second would right justify
one.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>,ju JUSTIFY</title>
      <para>The justify command
causes the lines to be right and left justified. The line will not
be justified if it ends with a RETURN. The text on this page was
created with the justify command. If you are using a proportional
spacing printer, the printed output will look slightly different
than on the screen since the line is evened out on the screen by
putting spaces between the words whale on the printed output all of
the letters are evenly spaced apart. For printers without
proportional spacing, (we refer to these as TTY printers). the
lines will have the same spacing on the screen as on the printed
output.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>,nj NO JUSTIFY</title>
      <para>This command will cause
the lines to have a ragged right edge. It is only used if the <command>,ju</command>
command has previously been used.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>,ll X LINE LENGTH</title>
      <para>The line length command
changes the length of the line on the screen. The following two
examples show the use of this command:</para>
      <screen>
,ll 35
,ll 120
</screen>
      <para>The first command sets
the line length to be 35 columns and the second command sets it to
be 120. After the second command the lines will be longer than the
screen so the screen will have to be scrolled left and right to
view some of the text. If the lines extend off the side of the
screen there will be right facing arrows <quote>&gt;</quote> on the right
side.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>,in X INDENT</title>
      <para>The indent command
causes all of the following lines to be spaced to the right by <quote>X</quote>
spaces. This effectively causes the line length to be reduced also.
Here are two examples of correct indent commands:</para>
      <screen>
,in 7
,in
</screen>
      <para>The first example
causes 7 spaces to be added to the left hand side of all of the
following lines. If the current line length in this example is 65,
then the actual line length is now really 58. The second example
causes the indent to go back to zero and is the same as entering
<quote>,in 0</quote>. The line length must never be reduced to less than 10 by
this command.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>,si X SINGLE INDENT</title>
      <para>The single indent
command is useful when you want to indent for only one line. You
could, for example, use this command to create an indent at the
beginning of every paragraph (although it would be easier to simply
type in the spaces or use a TAB, or better still to use the
paragraph formatting commands). This and the <command>,ppsi</command> command are the
only commands that will accept a minus number. A minus number will
cause the next line to be spaced back to the left by <quote>X</quote> columns.
Before using a minus single indent you must be sure that there is
enough room on the left side by using the <quote><command>,in</command></quote> indent command. The
following two examples will show how this might work:</para>
      <screen>
,si 6
,si -4
</screen>
      <para>The first example
causes the next line to be indented by 6 spaces and the effective
line length to be reduced by 6. The second example causes the next
line to stick out four columns to the left of the normal line and
the line length to be increased by 4. For the second example to
work, an indent of 4 or greater must have been set. This command
with a negative parameter is very useful in conjunction with a tab
for entering indented blocks of text in which the first line has a
title in the margin, for example:</para>
      <screen>
,in 10
,si -10
TITLE     This is an indented block of text with a title on the
          first  line. A 'tab'  was used  to move to the first
          word, 'This'.
</screen>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>,lm X LEFT MARGIN</title>
      <para>The left margin on the
printed page can be set to any value as long as the line length and
the left margin do not exceed the width of the printed page. This
command differs from the indent command in that it affects headers
and footers as well as the text. Also, the margin does not appear
on the screen but only appears on the printout. Use it to position
the printed text on the paper to suit your printer.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>,cs X CHARACTER SPACING</title>
      <para>The character spacing
can be set for those people who have versions for 'speciality'
printers. The value X is the number of characters per inch. This
value would normally only be set at 10 or 12 for <quote>elite</quote> and <quote>pica</quote>
spacing respectively. Other values may be set for special
applications but the error bell will sound as a warning that a
non-normal value has been entered.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>,ps PROPORTIONAL SPACING</title>
      <para>Speciality printers and
Centronics 737 and 739 printers support a special printing method
called proportional spacing. What this means is that the characters
are set in the line so that their widths are adjusted for. This
causes the printout to look <quote>typeset</quote>. To do this kind of printing
you must first have established a <quote>STYPS</quote> file in the <quote>STY</quote>
directory of your disk, and a special printer wheel must be
installed in your printer. The following section on the
proportional spacing command presents some details not needed for
elementary text processing; you may want to go on to other format
commands until you need to know more about the <command>,ps</command> command.</para>
      <para>Some printers. such as
Diablo, Qume, NEC, and Centronics 737 are capable of true
proportional spacing. This means that each character has a
different width so that the placement of a character on the line is
different for each character. When a text is proportionally spaced,
an <quote>i</quote> will take less space than an <quote>m</quote>.</para>
      <para>Before STYLOGRAPH can
operate with proportional spacing, it must know two characteristics
of the type face. First of all, it must know the width of the
character, and second. it must know the actual character to be
output. The width of the character will vary from printer to
printer and from one type face to another. Also, some printers
require that the character that is output to the printer be
different from the character seen on the screen. This is because
the proportionally spaced characters are actually arranged
differently on the print wheel than standard characters. For
example, to print a proportionally spaced <quote>x</quote> on a Diablo printer,
you must actually send it a <quote>v</quote>. The correspondence between the
standard character set and the proportional set is referred to as a
<quote>translation</quote>.</para>
      <para>STYLOGRAPH obtains the
character width and the translation from a proportional spacing
file on the disk. This file should be named <quote>STYPS</quote>. You will
normally create this file by copying one of the STYPS files that
are supplied on the disk. A table showing which supplied file is
suitable for each printer is given in the System Configuration
section. For example, to set up proportional spacing for the Diablo
printers you would use:</para>
      <screen>
OS9: copy /d0/sty/styps.d /d0/sty/styps
</screen>
      <para>The STYPS file provided
on the STYLOGRAPH disk is a copy of STYPS.D for the Diablo
printers. Delete it with the 'del' command if you want to use a
different file. Before STYLOGRAPH can correctly handle
proportionally spaced text, it must first read in one of these
proportional spacing files. The original STYLOGRAPH disk contains
proportional spacing tables for different printers and the most
common print wheels. For print wheels that are not supported you
may create a new proportional spacing table by editing one of the
existing tables. These tables are standard text files which can be
edited by STYLOGRAPH. Each of these tables contains three rows of
constants. Here is a partial list of one of the tables:</para>
      <informaltable frame="none" rowsep="0" colsep="0">
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="0.6in"/>
          <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="0.6in"/>
          <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" colwidth="1.6in"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>'r</entry>
              <entry>8</entry>
              <entry>'&lt;</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>'s</entry>
              <entry>8</entry>
              <entry>$7C</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>'t</entry>
              <entry>8</entry>
              <entry>'{</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>'u</entry>
              <entry>10</entry>
              <entry>'?</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>'v</entry>
              <entry>10</entry>
              <entry>'0</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>'w</entry>
              <entry>14</entry>
              <entry>$7E</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>'x</entry>
              <entry>10</entry>
              <entry>'v</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>'y</entry>
              <entry>10</entry>
              <entry>'!</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>'z</entry>
              <entry>10</entry>
              <entry>'g</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>'{</entry>
              <entry>10</entry>
              <entry>-'u NEC ONLY</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>'|</entry>
              <entry>10</entry>
              <entry>'.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>'}</entry>
              <entry>10</entry>
              <entry>'k</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>'~</entry>
              <entry>10</entry>
              <entry>'w</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>$7F</entry>
              <entry>10</entry>
              <entry>'p</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
      <para>The first column
contains a list of the standard ASCII character set. The third
column contains the character that must be output to get these
characters. The middle column contains the number increments
required for the width of the character. Notice that there are two
ways of specifying the characters. If the actual characters are
used, the character is preceded by an apostrophe. The character may
also be specified by it's ASCII code. This is indicated by
preceding the hexadecimal number with a <quote>$</quote>. Some of the third
column characters are preceded by a minus sign. This is used only
with the NEC printers, to indicate that the character is one of the
32 shifted characters on the print thimble, since the thimble
actually has 128 positions.</para>
      <para>When producing a
proportional spacing table, several things should be kept in mind.
First, the width of the character should be an even number for the
Diablo, Qume, and NEC printers. This number should be double the
width that is listed for these characters in the printer
documentation. Second, characters which are printable but are not
available from the keyboard must be entered with the ASCII code.
Finally, it is possible, although very tedious, to create one of
these tables without any documentation on the print wheel, by
printing all of the characters from a text which is not set to
proportional spacing. You can then figure out what the translation
table must look like, and you may estimate the character widths.
After a few trials of adjusting the translations and the widths it
should be possible to get a satisfactory printout.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>,nps NO PROPORTIONAL SPACING</title>
      <para>This causes STYLOGRAPH
to go back to the normal printing mode if proportional spacing has
been set.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>,pl X PAGE LENGTH</title>
      <para>This command sets the
length of the page in lines. It must be set to a number between 10
and 100. It is important to realize, when using this command, that
the header (top margin) and footer (bottom margin) count as lines
on the page so the page length must be set large enough to allow
some text lines on each page. So, for example if you leave the page
length at the default value of 66 and have 6 lines in the header
and 6 lines in the footer, there will be a total of 54 lines or
text on each page.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>,pg NEW PAGE</title>
      <para>You may start on a new
page by the use of this command. This will cause the footer to be
put at the bottom of the page and the next line to appear after the
header on the top of the next page. Remember that pagination is
automatic in STYLOGRAPH. You need only use this command if you want
to force a 'new page', for instance when starting a chapter.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>,pn X PAGE NUMBER</title>
      <para>This command sets the
page number which can appear in the header or the footer of the
page as explained in the header and footer description. This
command only affects the page number printed in the header or
footer - it does not affect the serial page number which appears on
the page boundary on the screen and which is used in the find page
numbers escape command. Page numbering is automatic in STYLOGRAPH.
You will normally only need to use this command if the text you are
editing is part of a large: document, and is to be printed out
separately. Note that MAIL MERGE will automatically continue the
page numbering over a number or files if they are printed out
together, so that the <command>,pn</command> command is not needed at the start of
each file.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>,tf TOP OF FORM</title>
      <para>This is a command which
has no effect on the display on the screen but causes a TOP OF FORM
command to be sent to the printer. It is normally used with
printers that are using special forms paper or are using a single
sheet feeder. If used, it should be inserted at the start of the
header so that a new sheet will be fed at the top of the page.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>HEADERS AND FOOTERS</title>
      <para>,hd DEFINE HEADER</para>
      <para>,ft DEFINE FOOTER</para>
      <para>,, END DEFINITION</para>
      <para>These three commands
are used to page. For example, the following set up the header and
footer of the 5 lines will cause a simple three line header to
appear at the top of all of the following pages:</para>
      <screen>
,hd
INTRO
,,
</screen>
      <para>This would cause the
first line at the top of the page to be a space, the word <quote>INTRO</quote>
to appear on the second line and another space to appear' on the
third line. You may also cause the page number to appear in the
header or footer by entering the characters ### at any point. When
STYLOGRAPH sees these characters it will replace them with the page
number. You may enter one or more of these characters at any place.
STYLOGRAPH always replaces these characters with a left justified
number and replaces the remaining <quote>#</quote> characters with spaces. You
may also use any of the following formatting commands in a header
or footer:</para>
      <para>,ll line length</para>
      <para>,ce centre</para>
      <para>,rj right justify</para>
      <para>These commands when
used within a header or footer affect only the headers and footers
and do not affect the rest of the text. This means that if you set
the line length for the text you may also have to set the line
length for the headers and footers to the same length. This also
means that you may allow the headers and footers to extend beyond
the normal right margin since the header and footer line lengths
are specified separately from the rest of the text.</para>
      <para>The following would be
an example of how the headers and footers were set up for this
portion of the manual:</para>
      <screen>
,hd

,rj
FORMAT COMMANDS

,,
,ft
,ll 70

,ce
PAGE ###

,,
</screen>
      <para>The line length for the
headers and footers must be set separately rest of the text and can
be different from the line length and the rest of the text. This
allows the lines in the header and footer to extend out from the
text on the rest of the screen. The header does not appear on the
first page so the footer contains the line length since it will be
the first one to be used by STYLOGRAPH.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>,sp X SPACE LINES</title>
      <para>Extra spaces between
lines can be inserted by this command. The parameter <quote>X</quote> specifies
how many lines are to be inserted. Spaces are not carried over from
one page to the next so that all of the spaces may not actually
appear on the printout if you are too close to the bottom. The
following are legal spacing commands:</para>
      <screen>
,sp 22
,sp
</screen>
      <para>The first command will
cause 22 lines to be spaced on the page. If, for example, there are
only 13 lines remaining on the page before the footer, then only 13
lines will be spaced. The second command spaces only one line.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>,ss X SET SPACING</title>
      <para>This particular command
is for setting the spacing between the lines. It has the same
function as single, double or triple spacing on a typewriter.
Although the spaces between the lines do not appear on the screen,
STYLOGRAPH does keep track of the line number on the page so that
the headers and footers will be inserted in the proper places.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>,vt X VERTICAL TAB</title>
      <para>This command will cause
the next line to be printed on the specified line number on the
page. The following command would cause the next line to be printed
on the 20th line:</para>
      <screen>
,vt 20
</screen>
      <para>If the present line
number on the page is greater than 20, the error bell will sound
and the command will be ignored.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>,vs X VERTICAL SPACING</title>
      <para>The vertical spacing
between the lines can also be set using this command. As with the
character spacing command it is only usable on those versions of
STYLOGRAPH that support a <quote>speciality</quote> printer. The use of any
value other than 4, 6 or 8 will result in a warning that a
non-normal line spacing is in use. Remember that when using this
command you must also change the number of lines on the page. For
example, if you set the vertical spacing to 4 (this is equivalent
to <quote>space and a half</quote> spacing on some typewriters) you must also
set the number of lines on the page to 44 for a normal 11 inch
page. This is because there will be 4 lines per inch and there are
11 inches on the page, making a total of 44 lines per page.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>,nl X NEED LINES</title>
      <para>There are some cases
where you will need to be sure that a portion of text, such as
table or illustration, appears on one page. The <command>,nl</command> command checks
to see if there are enough lines on the page. If there is not, a
new page will be started. Since STYLOGRAPH actually formats
correctly on the screen, there is often no need to use this command
since you can always readily see where you are on a page. Its
primary purpose is to be used with the MAIL MERGE program when you
may not have a chance to preview the text, and to protect your
carefully arranged formats against future changes to the text or
page size. See also the <command>,ppnl</command> command.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>PARAGRAPH COMMANDS</title>
      <section>
        <title>,pp PARAGRAPH</title>
        <para>This causes a new
paragraph to be started. This will have no effect unless one or
more of the next three commands have been set. It causes three
things to happen. (1) The <command>,ppnl</command> value is checked to see that there
are enough lines left on the page to start a new paragraph. If
there are not, a new page is started. (2) The number of lines,
indicated by the <command>,ppsp</command> command, are spaced. (3) The first line is
indented according to the <command>,ppsi</command> command.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>,ppnl X PARAGRAPH NEED LINES</title>
        <para>This has exactly the
same effect as the <command>,nl</command> command except that it has its effect
whenever the <command>,pp</command> command is entered. It is useful in ensuring that
you don't get just one line of a new paragraph at the bottom of a
page.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>,ppsp X PARAGRAPH SPACE</title>
        <para>This has the same
effect as the <command>,sp</command> command except that it has its effect whenever
the <command>,pp</command> command is entered. Remember that these spaces between the
lines will not appear on the screen but will appear on the
printout.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>,ppsi X PARAGRAPH SINGLE INDENT</title>
        <para>This causes a single
indent of X spaces to appear whenever the <command>,pp</command> paragraph command is
encountered. As with the <command>,si</command> command, the indent must have
previously been set if the <command>,ppsi</command> is set to a negative value.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>,bfs X BOLDFACE STRIKE</title>
      <para>This controls the
number of times that characters in boldfaced are printed.
STYLOGRAPH initially starts out with the value set to 4. If you
wish the boldface to be darker you may increase this value.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>,padc C PAD SPACE CHARACTER</title>
      <para>STYLOGRAPH uses the
space character as a separator. That is, when the end of a line is
reached STYLOGRAPH will break the line at a space. Also, STYLOGRAPH
will add spaces between words, if justification is on, to make the
text right and left justified. You may cause a space to be treated
as a normal character rather than as a separator by using the <command>,padc</command>
command. This command causes the character <quote>C</quote> when you enter it in
your text to be printed on the printer as a space although it will
be displayed normally on the screen. For example, let's assume that
you have entered the following command:</para>
      <screen>
,padc &amp;
</screen>
      <para>After this point the
character <quote>&amp;</quote> on the screen will be printed out as space on the
printer. One common use for this is to prevent abbreviations and
other strings from being broken at the end or a line. For example,
you would not want someone's name and initials broken between the
initials, with one initial at the end of one line and the other at
the start of the next line. If you have J.&amp;M.&amp; Johnson, the
line will not be broken up. On the printed output the <quote>&amp;</quote> will
be replaced by a space.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>,mmc C MAIL MERGE CHARACTER</title>
      <para>This command sets the
character for the mail merge program. Its use is explained in the
MAIL MERGE manual.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>,pc C PRINTER CONTROL CHARACTER</title>
      <para>This command sets the
printer control character which allows special commands to be sent
to the printer. If <quote>C</quote> is omitted, the printer control character
facility is disabled. This should only be used by people who are
thoroughly familiar with the ASCII protocol of their particular
printer. Some printers allow special characteristics such as double
height, double width, or other enhanced printing. This command
allows those special commands to be embedded in the text. For
example. the printer control character could be set as follows:</para>
      <screen>
,pc \
</screen>
      <para>This means that all
sequences between two <quote>\</quote> characters will be sent to the printer.
The sequences may be specified in three different ways; ASCII
character, decimal number, or hexadecimal number. Each of these
printer command characters must be separated by a space or a comma.
ASCII characters are indicated by an apostrophe ' preceding the
character. Decimal numbers are entered without any preceding
character and hexadecimal numbers are preceded by a dollar sign $.
A typical printer control sequence in a text might look like this
:</para>
      <para>This sequence \$1B,14\
will produce elongated characters on the Centronics 737 printer.
The sequence \$1B,$14\ will select the condensed character set and
the sequence \'a,'b,'c\ will cause the sequence <quote>abc</quote> to be printed
on the printer.</para>
      <para>There are three other
commands that may be specified between the <quote>PC</quote> characters for
special printer operations:</para>
      <para>S stops the printer
for changing printwheels, etc.</para>
      <para>B backspaces one space
for overprinting</para>
      <para>Tx tabs printer to the
<quote>x</quote> column</para>
      <para>Presuming the command <command>,pc</command> a has been previously executed,
      the following would be legal commands:</para>
      <para>The \b\x e and x would
be overprinted, the printer would stop here\s\ and could be
restarted from the keyboard, and the numbers <quote>12345</quote> would appear
in column 70 \t70\12345.</para>
      <para>Notice that these
printer sequences are not taken into account when the line length
is calculated for the screen, so the line with these sequences
embedded will look longer than a normal line on the screen, but
will be the correct length on the printer.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>,* COMMENTS</title>
      <para>There may be situations
in which you will want to enter comments in the text which should
not appear on the printed copy. For example, you may want to leave
a reminder for the next person that will be working on the text.
This could indicate the type of print wheel you want to be used or
it could be a simple note about the purpose of the text. It is
often a good idea to use these comment commands to document the
history of the text and its various revisions. To enter these
comments you need to enter the <quote><command>,*</command></quote> on the left edge of the screen
and follow of it with a comment. The comment must end with a return
and cannot extend beyond the end of the line. This is not really a
formatting command like the previous commands since it does not
change the appearance of the printed copy. Typical comments might
appear like this:</para>
      <screen>
,* use a pica print wheel for this text
,* written 4/5/1775. Ben Franklin
,* revised 5/22/1975 Thomas Jefferson
</screen>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>CONTROL COMMANDS</title>
    <para>CONTROL commands can be
executed from either the ESCAPE mode or the INSERT mode. To execute
a CONTROL command you must hold down the CONTROL key and press the
designated key at the same time. Some of the CONTROL commands have
already been briefly described.</para>
    <section>
      <title>CONTROL-P PAGE STATUS</title>
      <para>The page status command
causes the screen to be replaced with information about the current
status of the text. The input and output file names, their status,
a number of format parameters, and the room left in memory are all
listed. To redisplay the text hit CONTROL-P again. Notice that many
of the formatting commands themselves are displayed here. This is a
quick way of recalling these commands if you have forgotten
them.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>CONTROL-N NAME THE ERROR</title>
      <para>Whenever the error bell
sounds it means that STYLOGRAPH has encountered an error. If you
want to see a description of the error just press CONTROL-N and the
cursor line will be replaced with a description of the error. To
return to the normal text do the command again or hit the ESCAPE key.</para>
      <para>Most of the time the
cause of the error will be obvious since the error usually is the
result of something you have just entered. The error bell will also
sound whenever the cursor passes a line in which there is a format
command error. This can be particularly puzzling when using the
FIND, REPLACE, or FIND PAGE commands since the error bell can sound
whenever you are moving from one portion of the text to another. In
this circumstance the only way to find the line that caused the
error is to move the cursor back up through the text and then move
the cursor down through the text until the bell sounds again.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>CONTROL-F FORMAT DISPLAY/CONCEAL</title>
      <para>The format lines can be
displayed or removed from the screen by this command. This is
useful when you want to look at the text without the format lines.
There are some commands such as the FIND command that cause
STYLOGRAPH to display the format commands.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>CONTROL-V VIEW</title>
      <para>This command will cause
the character mods to be displayed rather than the characters
themselves. You can find the meaning of these character mods by
looking them up in the View Character Modifications section of this
manual or by using the <quote>assistance</quote> command. To return the display
to normal, press the CONTROL-V keys again.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>CONTROL-A ASSISTANCE</title>
      <para>If you forget a
particular command you may get some <quote>assistance</quote> by hitting
CONTROL-A. This will cause the screen to be cleared and a <quote>menu</quote> to
appear. This is like a table of contents since it indicates your
choice of other things to look at. There is a pointer on the left
side of the menu. To choose an item on the menu you simply move the
cursor up and down on the menu using the <quote>I</quote> and <quote>,</quote> keys as you
would when moving the cursor up and down on the screen. When the
cursor is at the correct line, hit the <quote>RETURN</quote> key and the screen
will be replaced with a list of the appropriate commands. The best
way to learn the use of this function is to try the various items
on the menu. You will notice that the disk will be accessed when
you choose an item on the menu. This is because the various help
tables are being read off the disk. For the command to work, the
<quote>STYHLP</quote> files must exist on your execution disk. If the table does
not appear, it means that the tables cannot be found on the
disk.</para>
      <para>The assistance command
is especially useful while you are first learning the system. This
command will cause a <quote>menu</quote> to be displayed on the screen. This
menu is a list of different kinds of assistance you can get. Notice
that there are three different lists of format commands. The
horizontal commands affect the horizontal positioning of the text.
The indent, line length, centering, and justification commands
would be examples of this. The vertical commands affect the
placement of the lines on the page. The page length, header,
footer, and set spacing commands would be examples of vertical
formatting commands.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>DELETES</title>
      <section>
        <title>CONTROL-D SINGLE CHARACTER DELETE</title>
        <para>This command deletes
the character on which the cursor is superimposed. The cursor then
moves to the next character. Remember that in the INSERT mode the
cursor may not be directly on top of the character since the gap in
the line has been filled with hyphens. In the INSERT mode the
deleted character will always be at the end of the line or
hyphens.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>CONTROL-S WORD DELETE</title>
        <para>The word that the
cursor is sitting on and the following spaces, if there are any,
will be deleted by this command. The cursor will then move to the
first character of the next word. The RETURN is considered to be a
word so that if the cursor is sitting on a RETURN it will be
deleted by this command.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>CONTROL-X LINE DELETE</title>
        <para>This command will
delete a line if it is bracketed by RETURNS. This means that if the
cursor line was started by hitting the RETURN and ends with a
RETURN, that line will be deleted. The RETURN at the end will
remain in case you want to enter a new line. To delete the RETURN,
do a single character delete. A series of lines can be deleted by
alternately depressing the <quote>X</quote> and <quote>D</quote> keys while holding down the
CONTROL key.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>TABS</title>
      <section>
        <title>CONTROL-T MOVE CURSOR TO A TAB POSITION</title>
        <para>The tab functions in
STYLOGRAPH operate very much like those on a typewriter. The
CONTROL-T command has a slightly different function in the ESCAPE
mode than in the INSERT mode. In the insert mode the line must be
started with a RETURN for it to work at all. If there is a RETURN
at the end of the previous line, STYLOGRAPH will add the proper
number of spaces to the line to move the cursor to the next valid
tab position. In the ESCAPE mode the cursor will move to the next
tab position only if there is already a character there. When
STYLOGRAPH starts out, tabs are automatically set to every 8th
character position. These may be removed or changed at will.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>CONTROL-R SET A TAB</title>
        <para>A tab will be set at
the cursor position when the CONTROL-R keys are pressed.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>CONTROL-Y CLEAR A TAB</title>
        <para>If a tab has been set
at the present cursor position it will be cleared by this
command.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>CONTROL-G GHOST HYPHEN</title>
      <para>A ghost hyphen can be
inserted anywhere in a word by moving the cursor to the appropriate
position and hitting the CONTROL-G. The most logical use of this
command is to scan the text. just before it is to be printed out,
for lines that are short and are also followed by a large word. To
cause the large word to be hyphenated simply move the cursor to the
place that you would like to place the hyphen and press the
CONTROL-G. STYLOGRAPH will automatically move the first part of the
word to the previous line if it will fit. Ghost hyphens can also be
entered when inserting text.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>CHARACTER MODS</title>
      <para>CONTROL-U UNDERLINE</para>
      <para>CONTROL-O OVERLINE</para>
      <para>CONTROL-I SUPERSCRIPT</para>
      <para>CONTROL-K SUBSCRIPT</para>
      <para>CONTROL-B BOLDFACE</para>
      <para>These CONTROL commands
are referred to as MOD (modifier) commands.. Characters MODS can be
specified in either the INSERT or ESCAPE modes, although the method
is slightly different for each mode. All of the modifications are
specified with CONTROL keys. For example, underlining is done by
holding down the CONTROL key and hitting the <quote>U</quote> key.</para>
      <para>In the ESCAPE mode
CONTROL-U causes the character at the cursor to be underlined and
the cursor to move one character to the right. Note that the space
bar can also move the cursor to the right in the ESCAPE mode.
Therefore, to underline a series of words, but not the spaces
between them, you can hold down the CONTROL key and hit the <quote>U</quote> key
to underline the words and the space bar to skip between the words.
All of the character mods work in this manner. If the character is
already modified, the new modification will be added to it.
Also, the UNMOD key can be used in the same manner to remove
modifications of the character.</para>
      <para>In the INSERT mode
CONTROL-U causes all characters entered after this point to be
underlined. This will continue until the UNMOD key is hit. After
this point none of the entered characters will be modified. It is
possible for a character to have more than one modification. If,
for example. you wanted a word to be boldfaced and underlined, you
would hold down the CONTROL key and hit the <quote>U</quote> key and then the
<quote>B</quote> key. You would then type in word and then hit the UNMOD
key.</para>
      <para>Many printers can print
these modifications but they cannot be displayed on the screen. The
presence of these modified characters is indicated on the screen by
some changes in the display. Normally these characters will be
displayed in low intensity or in reverse field. You can examine
these modifications by use of the VIEW control command. To do this
you must hit CONTROL-V. This will cause all the modified characters
to be changed to <quote>symbolic</quote> characters. The meaning of these
characters is listed in the View Character Modifications section.
The display will return to normal by hitting CONTROL-V again. The
meaning of these symbolic characters can also be shown with the
<quote>Assistance</quote> command.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>SUPERVISOR MODE</title>
    <para>The SUPERVISOR mode is
entered from the ESCAPE mode by hitting the <quote>/</quote> key. This will
cause the text to disappear from the screen and a <quote>menu</quote> to appear.
This menu is a list of actions that you can take. The cursor and
<quote>&gt;</quote> symbol can be moved up and down with the <quote>I</quote> and <quote>,</quote> keys
the same as in the ESCAPE mode. You execute a command by moving the
cursor to that line and then hitting the RETURN. You will then be
prompted for any further information if it is needed. In many cases
you will be asked for a yes or no response to a question. There may
be an asterisk * beside one of the responses such as (Y/N*). The
asterisk indicates that you may give that response by hitting the
RETURN. This will be the most common answer to the question, so you
can hit the RETURN in response to most of the questions.</para>
    <section>
      <title>EDIT</title>
      <para>This command has the
same effect as hitting the ESCAPE key. It causes STYLOGRAPH to go
back to the escape mode so that the text is displayed on the
screen, and you are ready to edit the text.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>PRINT</title>
      <para>This command will cause
the current text in memory to be printed out on the printer. When
this command is executed you will first be asked if you want to
change the printer. STYLOGRAPH normally uses the parallel printer
port called <quote>/p</quote>. If you want to use a different printer port, such
as <quote>/p1</quote> the serial port, you should answer <quote>Y</quote> to the first
question. STYLOGRAPH will prompt you for the name of the printer
port. If you want to use the serial port, you would respond with
<quote>/p1</quote> (If OS-9 does not recognize the name you have entered.
(because a device descriptor of that name has not been loaded into
memory), OS-9 will display <quote>Error #221 - Module not found</quote>. Note
that if you forget the <quote>/</quote> at the start of the printer name, your
text will go to a disk file with that name.)</para>
      <para>Next STYLOGRAPH will
ask you if you want to stop for new pages. This is in case you are
not using continuous feed paper in your printer and need to hand
load each sheet. When the printer has stopped to allow you to load
a new sheet you will see another prompt on the screen. You may
resume printing by hitting any key except the <quote>ESCAPE</quote> key. The
<quote>ESCAPE</quote> key will cause the printing to stop.</para>
      <para>STYLOGRAPH will then
ask if you want to print all the pages. If you answer <quote>N</quote> you will
then be asked for the numbers of the first and last pages that you
want printed. Remember that these numbers refer to the serial page
numbers, as displayed on the screen, and not to the numbers that
appear on the printout.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>SAVE AND RETURN</title>
      <para>This command is a time
saver that allows you to save the text file and then return to
OS-9. It operates exactly like the SAVE command except that after
it is done, STYLOGRAPH is exited and you will be back in OS-9. If
all of the text has not been read in from the disk, STYLOGRAPH will
automatically read in the remaining text and send it to the output
file. This is the ONLY way you will be able to permanently save
text files which are larger than memory, or if you have dumped any
of the text to an output file; if you attempt to execute a simple
SAVE command (see below) when the file is still open, STYLOGRAPH
will give you an error.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>SAVE</title>
      <para>The save command causes
the text in memory to be saved to a disk file. You will first be
asked if you want to save the file under the present file name. The
present file name will be the same file name that was used when
STYLOGRAPH was first called. If you do not want to save it under
this name, or you did not give a name when you called STYLOGRAPH,
you will be prompted for the file name. If you also specified an
output file name when you initially called STYLOGRAPH, the output
file name will be used by the SAVE command. This command will be
prohibited if there are any files still open. This is to prevent
you from erroneously saving part of a file when you intended to
save the whole file. If files are open and you only want to save
part of the text, you must use the SAVE TO MARK command.</para>
      <para>If there is already a
file by that name when the SAVE command is executed, STYLOGRAPH
will rename the old file by adding <quote>.BAK</quote>, (for backup), to the
name. If there is already a backup file by that name, STYLOGRAPH
will ask you if you want the old file deleted. You may answer with
a <quote>Y</quote> or <quote>N</quote>. If you answer <quote>N</quote> no action is taken.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>SAVE TO MARK</title>
      <para>This command may be
used to save a smaller portion of the text. For example, you may
have a certain paragraph or part of one text that you will also be
needing in another text. To save the portion simple enter two
marker characters <quote>}}</quote> at the end of the block of the text and then
move the cursor to the front of the text. Then execute the SAVE TO
MARK command. After using this command you will normally want to go
back and delete the <quote>}}</quote> characters.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>RETURN</title>
      <para>This command allows you
to return to OS-9 without saving the file. To be sure you are not
making a mistake, STYLOGRAPH will first ask you if the text is
secure (that is, is there a copy on the disk?) before returning you
to OS-9.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>LOAD</title>
      <para>This command causes a
text file to be loaded into memory at the position of the cursor.
The command will prompt you for the name of the file you want to
load. Remember that when STYLOGRAPH is first called from OS-9, the
file name on the command line will be loaded automatically, so
normally it will not be necessary to use the LOAD command.</para>
      <para>The LOAD command
provides a convenient way of producing made-up documents. Separate
parts of a manuscript can be created and saved to disk files. At a
later point any assortment of files that exist in disk files can be
loaded to create a finished manuscript. This could be used for
legal documents and form letters in which identical parts of a text
are used in many different documents.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>ERASE</title>
      <para>All of the text an
memory is erased with this command. To be sure you are not
destroying a valuable text, STYLOGRAPH first asks you twice if you
are sure. You must answer <quote>Y</quote> to each question before the text is
erased. This command should, obviously, be used with caution. This
command will be prohibited if any files are open.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>SPECIAL</title>
      <para>This command has the
opposite function of the TTY command. It allows you to go back to
printing on a speciality printer after having printed on a TTY type
printer.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>TTY</title>
      <para>You can set STYLOGRAPH
to act as if it were outputting to a TTY type printer (such as a
simple matrix printer) by the use of this command. The printed
output will then appear without many of the special effects such as
boldface and proportional spacing. This command is useful if you
also have a high speed line printer and would like to get a rapid
printout of the text. This command is equivalent to selecting
printer type 30 when you call STYLOGRAPH from OS-9.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>PASS</title>
      <para>This command allows you
to pass a command to OS-9. You will be prompted for the command
line. You can execute any OS-9 command, provided there is
sufficient memory available. When the command is finished, hit
ESCAPE to return to STYLOGRAPH. Note that the 'chd' and 'chx'
commands will have no effect on STYLOGRAPH's own data and execution
directories.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>SPOOL</title>
      <para>This command is similar
to the PRINT command except that the output is directed to a disk
file. This allows the text to be printed out at another time using
the 'copy' command under OS-9, (e.g. 'copy file /p'). You will be
prompted for the name of the output file.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>WHEEL</title>
      <para>This command loads in a
proportional spacing table. STYLOGRAPH will load in a proportional
spacing table at startup so this command is normally only used if
the print wheel is being changed. The proportional spacing table
that is usually loaded in is named <quote>STYPS</quote> You will first be asked
if you want to load a table by this name. You will be prompted for
a different name if you wish.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>NEW</title>
      <para>This command is for
working with files that are too large to fit in memory in one go.
STYLOGRAPH can only work on text that is in the memory of the
computer. If the text will not fit in the memory, then part of it
will be kept on the disk. There are two files that this excess text
is kept on, the input file and the output file. When STYLOGRAPH is
called, it first loads in text from the input file until memory is
nearly full. You may then edit and work on this portion of the file
until you are ready to go on to the next portion of text. You will
then use the NEW command to dump your present text to the output
file and bring in some more text from the input file. Notice that
once you are finished with a portion or text and have dumped it to
the output file, you cannot then go back and work on it during this
editing session. This means that you may only use the NEW command
to go forward through the text.</para>
      <para>The NEW command
actually consists of two different steps, <quote>dumping</quote> and <quote>filling</quote>.
<quote>Dumping</quote> consists of sending the present text in memory to the
output file and <quote>filling</quote> consists of bringing text into memory
from the input file. You will be given a choice of doing either or
both of these operations. You may use the <quote>PAGE STATUS</quote> command to
see if either or both of the files are open. The input file is open
if there is still text in it which has not been read in to the
memory. The output file is open whenever a portion of text has been
dumped to the output file.</para>
      <para>When dumping text, all
of the text above the cursor page is dumped to the output file.
Therefore, if you are finished working with pages 1-5 you may put
the cursor somewhere on page 6 before executing the NEW command. If
you put the cursor on the first page, no text will be dumped and
you will see a message indicating that the cursor is on the first
page. If you are dumping text for the first time, you will be asked
if you wish to use the present file name. If you do not, you will
be asked for a new file name. Also, if there is an old backup file
of that name, you will be asked if you want to delete the old
backup file. There are occasions where you will want to dump text
to the output file but will not want to do any filling. You might
do this to create more free space in memory to do additional
editing. For example, you might want to make room for additions to
the text at some point. Also, you might want to make room to load
in another file or make a large block move. Remember that you can
only print out text that is in memory, so you might want to print
the text before dumping it.</para>
      <para>Text will be filled
from the input file if there is any remaining. The new text will be
added to the bottom of the present text in memory. STYLOGRAPH will
leave a little room in memory so you can do some additional
editing. Working with text files larger than memory is a great
convenience but it should be done with caution. Having a large text
in one file greatly increases the chance of losing the text, either
through a power failure or a disk error. If you are working with a
large text file it makes sense to always keep a recent copy of the
text on a backup disk so that you can always easily recover from
such an error. In many cases it makes more sense to break a large
text into several smaller sections, such as chapters, and then
print out all the files together using the MAIL MERGE program. This
simplifies editing and decreases the chances of losing a large text
file.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>SYSTEM CONFIGURATION</title>
    <section>
      <title>CONFIGURING STYLOGRAPH FOR YOUR PRINTER</title>
      <para>STYLOGRAPH is supplied
configured to work with the parallel printer port (<quote>/p</quote>), and a
simple matrix printer, type P40 in the table below. If you are
using a different port or a different type of printer, there are
two ways of informing STYLOGRAPH. You can specify the printer type
when you call STYLOGRAPH, for example:</para>
      <screen>
OS9: stylo letter +P0
</screen>
      <para>and specify the printer
port name by answering <quote>Y</quote> when STYLOGRAPH asks <quote>Different printer?
(Y/N*)</quote>. Alternatively, you can permanently reconfigure STYLOGRAPH
using the STYFIX command.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>STYFIX COMMAND</title>
      <para>The <quote>STYFIX</quote> command is
normally used to set up three different characteristics of
STYLOGRAPH; the printer port name, the printer type, and whether it
loads up a proportional spacing table when it is first called. It
can also set the maximum number of pages that STYLOGRAPH can work
on. The normal method of operation is to first establish STYLOGRAPH
in your execution directory, by placing your STYLOGRAPH disk in
drive 0, and entering:</para>
      <screen>
OS9: chx /d0/cmds
</screen>
      <para>Next, change your data
directory to be your execution directory: e.g.</para>
      <screen>
OS9: chd /d0/cmds
</screen>
      <para>You should then execute
the following command:</para>
      <screen>
OS9: styfix stylo
</screen>
      <para>The STYFIX command is
menu driven and self prompting. Simply enter the number of your
choice and answer the questions. You must consult the table below
for the particular number of your printer. When entering the name
of the printer port, remember that it must start with a <quote>/</quote>. After
you have specified the printer type you may return to OS9 and your
copy of STYLOGRAPH will be correctly configured for your particular
printer and terminal. Don't forget to change your data directory
back again, e.g.</para>
      <screen>
OS9: chd /d0
</screen>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>TERMINAL NUMBERS<footnote><para>Not available on Dragon 64 or the Color Computer</para></footnote></title>
      <para>
This table lists the various terminal types handled by STYLOGRAPH,
and gives the associated numbers for use when calling STYLOGRAPH, or when using STYFIX.</para>
      <informaltable frame="none" rowsep="0" colsep="0">
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colwidth="0.5in"/>
          <colspec colwidth="5in"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>T1</entry>
              <entry>SOROC IQ-120</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>T2</entry>
              <entry>SOROC IQ-140</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>T3</entry>
              <entry>SOROC IQ-130/135</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>T4</entry>
              <entry>Televideo TVI 912/920 and Lear-Siegler ADM-31</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>T5</entry>
              <entry>Hazeltine 1500/1420</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>T6</entry>
              <entry>Hazeltine 1400</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>T7</entry>
              <entry>Lear Siegler ADM-3A</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>T8</entry>
              <entry>Lear Siegler ADM-42</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>T9</entry>
              <entry>Microterm MIME-2A</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>T10</entry>
              <entry>Microterm ACT-5A</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>T11</entry>
              <entry>Intertec INTERTUBE II</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>T12</entry>
              <entry>SWTPC CT-82</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>T13</entry>
              <entry>SWTPC CT-8209/12</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>T14</entry>
              <entry>DEC VT-52</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>T15</entry>
              <entry>ADDS REGENT 25</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>T16</entry>
              <entry>Heath H-19, Zenith Z-10</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>T17</entry>
              <entry>TEC 510, 610</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>T18</entry>
              <entry>Beehive MICRO B2</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>T19</entry>
              <entry>Beehive B100</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>T20</entry>
              <entry>Volker-Craig VC-404</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>T21</entry>
              <entry>Hewlett Packard 2621 A/P</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>T22</entry>
              <entry>ADDS Viewpoint</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>T23</entry>
              <entry>Motorola Exorterm</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>T24</entry>
              <entry>Visual Technology Inc. VISUAL 300</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>T25</entry>
              <entry>TEC70</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>T26</entry>
              <entry>ANSI/DEC VT-100</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>T27</entry>
              <entry>GIMIX 24x80 Video</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>T28</entry>
              <entry>Volker-Craig VC4404</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>T29</entry>
              <entry>CYBERNEX XL 87</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>T30</entry>
              <entry>Perkin-Elmer 550 CRT</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>T31</entry>
              <entry>Lear-Siegler ADM-5</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>T32</entry>
              <entry>Hazeltine ESPRIT</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>PRINTER TYPES AND CHARACTERISTICS</title>
      <para>
This table lists the various printer types handled by STYLOGRAPH,
and gives the associated numbers for use when calling STYLOGRAPH, or when using STYFIX.</para>
      <informaltable frame="none" rowsep="0" colsep="0">
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="0.6in"/>
          <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="1.4in"/>
          <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" colwidth="3.0in"/>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Type</entry>
              <entry>Proportional Spacing file</entry>
              <entry>Printers of this type</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>P0</entry>
              <entry>STYPS.D</entry>
              <entry>All DIABLO, all C.ITOH, NEC 3515, 3525, 5515, 5525, 7715, 7725, QUME SPRINT, 5/xx or 9/xx</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>P10</entry>
              <entry>STYPS.N</entry>
              <entry>NEC 3510, 3520, 5510, 5520, 7710, 7720</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>P20</entry>
              <entry>STYPS.7</entry>
              <entry>CENTRONICS 737/739</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>P30</entry>
              <entry>none</entry>
              <entry>TTY (matrix) printer with backspace capability</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>P40</entry>
              <entry>none</entry>
              <entry>TTY (matrix) printer without backspace capability</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
      <para>NOTES</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>P0, P10, and P20 type
printers will support: Underline. Overline, Boldface, Superscript,
Subscript, and proportional spacing.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>P30 type printers will support: Underline, Overline, and Boldface, but no proportional
spacing.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>P40 type printers support no character modifications and no proportional spacing.
Most matrix printers are of this type.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>SUMMARY OF STYLEGRAPH COMMANDS</title>
    <section>
      <title>ESCAPE COMMANDS (USED IN ESCAPE MODE)</title>
      <informaltable frame="none" rowsep="0" colsep="0">
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="0.4in"/>
          <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="4.0in"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>J</entry>
              <entry>cursor left</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>L</entry>
              <entry>cursor right</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>I</entry>
              <entry>cursor up</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>K</entry>
              <entry>cursor left and right to end of line</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>U</entry>
              <entry>scroll up one line</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>M</entry>
              <entry>scroll down one line</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>O</entry>
              <entry>scroll up one screen</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>.</entry>
              <entry>scroll down one screen</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>1</entry>
              <entry>overlay one character with next key hit</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>^</entry>
              <entry>insert next key hit</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>7</entry>
              <entry>scroll left by 25 columns</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>9</entry>
              <entry>scroll right by 25 columns</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>;</entry>
              <entry>enter INSERT mode</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>/</entry>
              <entry>go to SUPERVISOR mode</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>S</entry>
              <entry>save text from cursor to marker</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>W</entry>
              <entry>withdraw saved text</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>D</entry>
              <entry>duplicate (without withdrawing) saved text</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Z</entry>
              <entry>zap (delete) text from cursor to marker</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>}}</entry>
              <entry>set marker (two required)</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>P</entry>
              <entry>move to page N</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>F</entry>
              <entry>
                <literallayout>find character string
responses: space  - go to next;
           return - stop</literallayout>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>R</entry>
              <entry>
                <literallayout>replace first character string with second
responses: Y       - replace string;
           N       - don't replace string;
           A       - replace all occurrences (no prompt);
           space   - go on to next;
           return  - stop</literallayout>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>CONTROL COMMANDS (USED IN ESCAPE AND INSERT MODES)</title>
      <informaltable frame="none" rowsep="0" colsep="0">
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1.0in"/>
          <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="4.0in"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>CONTROL-A</entry>
              <entry>help</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>CONTROL-P</entry>
              <entry>page status</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>CONTROL-N</entry>
              <entry>name the last error</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>CONTROL-W</entry>
              <entry>delete word</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>CONTROL-D</entry>
              <entry>delete single character</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>CONTROL-X</entry>
              <entry>delete line (bracketed by returns)</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>CONTROL-F</entry>
              <entry>display/non-display format commands</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>CONTROL-R</entry>
              <entry>set a tab</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>CONTROL-T</entry>
              <entry>move to tab</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>CONTROL-Y</entry>
              <entry>clear a tab</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>CONTROL-G</entry>
              <entry>insert a ghost hyphen</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>CONTROL-V</entry>
              <entry>view/hide character modifiers</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>CONTROL-U</entry>
              <entry>underline - in escape
mode, underline a character. In INSERT mode, underline following
characters until UNMOD hit.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>CONTROL-O</entry>
              <entry>overline - same as underline</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>CONTROL-I</entry>
              <entry>superscript - same as underline</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>CONTROL-K</entry>
              <entry>subscript - same as underline</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>CONTROL-B</entry>
              <entry>boldface - same as underline</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>UNMOD</entry>
              <entry>end/remove mods - in
ESCAPE mode, removes all mods from a character. In INSERT mode,
returns to unmodified character entry.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>FORMATTING COMMANDS</title>
      <para>Default values are
shown in square brackets [ ].</para>
      <table frame="none" rowsep="0" colsep="0">
        <title>Vertical formatting commands</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="0.8in"/>
          <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="4.2in"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>,PL N</entry>
              <entry>Set page length to N lines per page [66]</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>,PG</entry>
              <entry>Force a new page</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>,PN N</entry>
              <entry>Set the printed page number to N</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>,TF</entry>
              <entry>Send TOP OF FORM to printer</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>,HD</entry>
              <entry>Start header definition</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>,FT</entry>
              <entry>Start footer definition</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>,,</entry>
              <entry>End header or footer definition</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>,SP N</entry>
              <entry>Space N lines (print parameter)</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>,SS N</entry>
              <entry>Set line spacing to N (print parameter) [1]</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>,VT N</entry>
              <entry>Vertical tab to Nth line (print parameter)</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>,VS N</entry>
              <entry>Vertical spacing, lines/inch (print parameter)</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>,NL N</entry>
              <entry>Need N lines on same page, (to keep a block of text on one page).</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <table frame="none" rowsep="0" colsep="0">
        <title>Horizontal formatting commands</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="0.8in"/>
          <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="4.2in"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>,CE N</entry>
              <entry>Centre N lines</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>,RJ N</entry>
              <entry>Right justify N lines</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>,JU</entry>
              <entry>Justify</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>,NJ</entry>
              <entry>No justify</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>,LL N</entry>
              <entry>Line length of N characters [screen width -1]</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>,IN N</entry>
              <entry>Indent N spaces from the margin until next ,IN command</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>,SI N</entry>
              <entry>Indent one line N spaces (N can be negative)</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>,LM N</entry>
              <entry>Set left margin on printer to N spaces [0]</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>,CS N</entry>
              <entry>Character spacing, N characters/inch (print parameter)[12]</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>,PS</entry>
              <entry>Start proportional spacing</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>,NPS</entry>
              <entry>Return to non-proportional spacing, normal spacing</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <table frame="none" rowsep="0" colsep="0">
        <title>Paragraph formatting commands</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="0.8in"/>
          <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="4.2in"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>,PP</entry>
              <entry>Start a new paragraph</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>,PPNL N</entry>
              <entry>Paragraphs need N lines on same page</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>,PPSP N</entry>
              <entry>Space N lines on new paragraphs</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>,PPSI N</entry>
              <entry>Indent N spaces on first line of paragraph</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <table frame="none" rowsep="0" colsep="0">
        <title>Misc. Formatting commands</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="0.8in"/>
          <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="4.2in"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>,BFS N</entry>
              <entry>Boldface strike N times at printout</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>,PADC C</entry>
              <entry>Pad character C for non-paddable spaces on printout</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>,MMC C</entry>
              <entry>Mail Merge character C</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>,PC C</entry>
              <entry>Print character C for delimiting printer control strings</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>,*</entry>
              <entry>Comment line</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>VIEWED CHARACTER MODIFICATIONS</title>
      <informaltable frame="none" rowsep="0" colsep="0">
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1.1in"/>
          <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="1.0in"/>
          <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="2.5in"/>
          <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry/>
              <entry>Command</entry>
              <entry>As seen on screen in viewing mode</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Underline</entry>
              <entry>CONTROL-U</entry>
              <entry>
                <literallayout class="monospaced">_________________________________</literallayout>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Overline</entry>
              <entry>CONTROL-O</entry>
              <entry>
                <literallayout class="monospaced">555555555555555555555555555555555</literallayout>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Boldface</entry>
              <entry>CONTROL-B</entry>
              <entry>
                <literallayout class="monospaced">333333333333333333333333333333333</literallayout>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Superscript</entry>
              <entry>CONTROL-I</entry>
              <entry>
                <literallayout class="monospaced">AAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA</literallayout>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Subscript</entry>
              <entry>CONTROL-K</entry>
              <entry>
                <literallayout class="monospaced">aaaaaaaaaaaaaaaaaaaaaaaaaaaaaaaaa</literallayout>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
      <section>
        <title>Displayed mod characters</title>
        <programlisting>
_ Underline
3 Boldface
4 Underline, Boldface
5 Overline
6 Underline, Overline
7 Boldface, Overline 
8 Underline, Boldface, Overline
A Superscript
B Superscript, Underline
C Superscript, Boldface
D Superscript, Underline, Boldface
E Superscript, Overline
F Superscript: Underlined Overline
G Superscript, Boldface, Overline
H Superscript, Underline, Boldface, Overline
a Subscript
b Subscript, Underline
c Subscript, Boldface
d Subscript. Underline, Boldface
e Subscript, Overline
f Subscript: Underline, Overline
g Subscript, Boldface. Overline
h Subscript, Underline, Boldface, Overline
</programlisting>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
</article>
