<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <articleinfo>
    <title>SPELLING CHECKER USER'S MANUAL</title>
    <titleabbrev>SPELL CHECK</titleabbrev>
  </articleinfo>
  <section>
    <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
    <para>The STYLOGRAPH Spelling
Checker is a fast, reliable, and easy-to-use software tool that
greatly enhances the usefulness of the STYLOGRAPH Word Processing
System. The Spelling Checker allows even an inexperienced user to
eliminate spelling errors from a text file. Although it is
recommended that this manual be studied thoroughly before using the
Spelling Checker, many people will be able to use it with little
instruction. The Spelling Checker operates in a totally
self-prompting fashion which simply means that whenever any action
is of required on your part, a message will appear on your screen
stating what action is required and what your options may be. You
merely call the program and indicate the name of the text file to
be checked. Spelling Checker then scans through the entire file and
compares each word to a Standard Dictionary. Next, it refers to a
Supplementary Dictionary (created by the user) that contains any
additional words (such as peoples' names, names of cities, or
technical terms) that might not exist in the Standard Dictionary.
It then displays on the user's screen (or printer) a count of the
total number of words in the file, the number of different words it
contains, and the number of words that may have been misspelled. It
also lists in a convenient, tabular form all the words that it
considers to be possible misspellings. Some of these words are
likely to be actual misspellings that should be corrected. Others,
however, may be rare words that are spelled correctly but are not
in the dictionary; you may wish to add these colds to the
Supplementary Dictionary (as explained below) if they are words
that occur frequently in the text files you will be checking in the
future.</para>
    <para>At this point, the
Spelling Checker enters an interactive Review process, where the
user decides which of several options to select. If no spelling
errors have been detected, the program simply ends and returns the
user to OS-9.</para>
    <para>If possible errors have
been detected, the user has the option of either exiting the
program or of continuing with a word-by-word review of the possibly
misspelled words. If the Exit option is selected, the user is
returned to OS-9. If the user decides to proceed with the Review,
he may choose to exit the program at any point in the Review.</para>
    <para>During the Review
process, each possibly misspelled word is displayed along with a
set of options that may be selected for each word. The options may
be selected by a single keystroke from the terminal. These options
include:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Ignoring the word
(leaving the word intact in the text file)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Adding the word to the
Supplementary Dictionary</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Flagging the word
(placing a special character, normally a "&lt;" next to the word in
the disk text file so that it may be located easily with the
STYLOGRAPH Word Processor)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Displaying the word
surrounded by its original context in the text file (to help
determine what word was intended)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Changing the spelling
of the word, so that all occurrences of this word will be corrected
automatically in the text file</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Exiting the Spelling
Checker to return to OS-9</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>As each word is
displayed, the user has the option or ignoring it, adding it to the
dictionary, flagging it or selecting it for Display-in-context. The
Display-in-context option allows the user to see the questionable
word in its context before deciding what to do with it. When all
the words have been presented, the Spell Checker goes through the
words that have been selected for Display-in context, showing each
on the screen with some of the surrounding text. After the word is
displayed, the user has the choice of ignoring it, adding it to the
dictionary, or flagging it. In addition, the user has the option of
changing the word to a new spelling. If the change option is
selected, the user is asked to type in the new, correct spelling
for the word, which is then substituted in the text file for the
old, incorrect spelling. If you select the change option, be sure
that the new spelling you enter is the correct one!</para>
    <para>After the Review is
complete, the Spelling Checker automatically creates a new text
file that incorporates all the spelling changes and flags that the
user has requested. (If no changes or flags have been selected,
then no new text file will be created). It also adds any new words
to the Supplementary Dictionary that the user has indicated. At
this point, the program is finished, and control returns to OS-9.
If flags have been added to the text file, the user may wish to
edit the file immediately with the STYLOGRAPH Word Processor.
STYLOGRAPH's Find feature provides a convenient way to locate all
the flags that have been added, so that appropriate action may be
taken on them. If no flags have been added, then no further editing
is necessary; the text file should now be free of any spelling
errors.</para>
    <para>It is important to note
that each word in the original text file need be dealt with only
once in the Review process. For example, once a word has been
Flagged, all occurrences of the word will be Flagged in the text
file; the user will not be bothered with that word again.
Furthermore, all of the user options may be selected with a single
keystroke, so the Review process proceeds quickly and
efficiently.</para>
    <para>The Standard Dictionary
supplied with the STYLOGRAPH spelling checker is among the most
complete and accurate computerised dictionaries available. The
large vocabulary of 42,000 words includes all of the common words
normally encountered in English text. It includes the names of the
days of the week, months of the year, countries, states and most
large cities, common first and last names, and other entries not
found in all dictionaries. It also includes all of STYLOGRAPH'S
formatting commands, so these do not appear as typographical errors
to the Spelling Checker. The dictionary has been prepared with
great care to ensure that it is complete and error-free. They have
been cheeked against a dictionary of common misspellings to ensure
that all the most likely misspellings are doubly certain to be
detected.</para>
    <para>The Standard Dictionary
is supplied to you in compacted form to reduce the amount of disk
space it occupies and to reduce the time required for the program
to read it from disk. A combination of sophisticated compression
techniques have reduced the dictionary to less than one quarter of
the size it would take up if it were supplied as an ordinary text
file. As a result, the Standard Dictionary cannot be listed on your
terminal, nor can it be edited using STYLOGRAPH. However, for those
users who might wish to convert the compacted form of the
dictionary to a normal text file, a special decompression utility
program (called SPELLDCM) has been furnished for this purpose and
is described later in the manual.</para>
    <para>Most users will wish to
add words to the dictionary to customize it for their own purposes.
For example, technical terms, special abbreviations or codes, and
names are popular candidates for inclusion. These words may be
conveniently entered into the Supplementary Dictionary, usually
called "supp" in the STY directory of the disk in drive 0. The
supplied Supplementary Dictionary is empty; it is there to receive
words the user may wish to add to it. The user may add an unlimited
number of words to the Supplementary Dictionary. This may be done
easily in either of two ways. The first is simply to use the
Add-to-dictionary option during the Review process of the Spelling
Checker. The second is to edit the Supplementary Dictionary using
STYLOGRAPH. The Supplementary Dictionary is simply a text file that
can be listed or edited like any other file. As this dictionary
grows, however, it will occupy more disk space and will take longer
to read. To anticipate this possibility, a utility program called
"SPELLADD" has been furnished with the Spelling Checker to merge
your Supplementary Dictionary with the Standard Dictionary. In this
way, all the speed and space advantages of the compacted dictionary
format will apply to the words you have added to the dictionary. Of
course, additional words may be added to the Supplementary
Dictionary at any time.</para>
    <para>Some users may even
want to delete certain words from the Standard Dictionary. While
most users will not need to do this, a utility program called
"SPELLSUB" is included to serve this function. This might be useful
to the person who, for example, does not want certain spelling
alternatives (e.g. British or American spellings) to be allowed or
who does not wish particular "slang" words to exist in the
dictionary.</para>
    <para>One final precautionary
note must be made. Although the Spelling Checker will detect all
genuinely misspelled words, it cannot detect a correctly spelled
word that is used improperly. For example, if the word "principle"
is used when "principal" is meant, the Spelling Checker will not
detect the misspelling. Both "principle" and "principal" are
legitimate words, and although their meanings are different, there
is no way that the Spelling Checker can determine which of the two
you intend.</para>
    <para>This concludes the
introduction to the STYLOGRAPH Spelling Checker. The following
sections contain more detailed operation on the use of the Spelling
Checker. We recommend that you read through this Operation section
of the manual at least once to become familiar with the
requirements and various options of the program. Since the program
is simple and self-prompting, a single, careful reading may be all
that is necessary.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>OPERATION</title>
    <section>
      <title>1. Using the Spelling Checker</title>
      <para>To use the Spelling
Checker command the user will normally type in the name "spell"
followed by the name of the file that is to be checked. For
example, if you want to cheek a file called "INTRO" you would type
in the following lines from OS-9:</para>
      <screen>
OS9: spell intro
</screen>
      <para>A filename must be
supplied; if none is given, an error message will appear and the
program's execution will' be terminated. If the user wishes the
output of Spelling Checker to be routed to a printer rather than to
the terminal, he may redirect the output using OS's redirection
facility. For example:</para>
      <screen>
OS9: spell intro &gt;/p
</screen>
      <para>Most of the user
prompts and messages will still be directed to the terminal, but
the list or possibly misspelled words will appear on the printer,
along with the summary information about the number or words in the
text file.</para>
      <para>At this time, Spelling
Checker will scan the text file. Following this, it will compare
the words in the text file against the Standard Dictionary, whose
filename is DICT. The dictionary must be in directory STY on the
disk in drive 0. The time required for scanning will of course
depend on the size of the file being checked. Messages will appear
on the user's terminal indicating what the program is doing at each
stage of its operation. The Spelling Checker can abort its
operation during this phase if any of the following conditions
arise:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The text file cannot be
found</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The Standard Dictionary
cannot be found</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The file contains too
many different words. so that Spelling Checker's storage capacity
has been exceeded.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>The first two
conditions are self-explanatory and may easily be corrected by
ensuring that the required files exist with their correct
filenames. The third condition, which most users will never
encounter, indicates an "overflow" problem has been encountered in
processing the text file. In this case, the text file must be
divided into smaller sections using the STYLOGRAPH word processor.
Normally, any file that STYLOGRAPH can manage will be processed
without overflow by the Spelling Checker. With unusual files in
which each word is different from all others, an overflow can
arise. This is most likely to happen if Spelling Checker is used to
check long lists of names, technical terms, or even to check a
dictionary. Using smaller text files or expanding the amount of
memory available will solve this problem quickly. For example:</para>
      <screen>
os9: spell intro #15k
</screen>
      <para>After scanning the text
file and processing the Standard Dictionary, the Spelling Checker
will look for the user's Supplementary Dictionary, whose name is
"supp" in the STY directory of the disk in drive 0. If it is not
found, the user will be prompted (asked) for an alternative
filename for this dictionary. If you have no Supplementary
Dictionary, just hit RETURN.</para>
      <para>If the file exists
under a different name or drive, supplying the correct file
specification will allow the Spelling Checker to process the user's
Supplementary Dictionary. If a carriage return is entered in reply
to the prompt, the Spelling Checker will assume that no user
Supplementary Dictionary exists, and so it will check the text file
against the Standard Dictionary only.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>2. Text File Information Display</title>
      <para>After the text file has
been scanned and the dictionaries have been processed, some useful
information will be displayed on the user's terminal, including the
total number of words in the text file and the number of different
(or unique) words it contains. The program considers a word to be
any contiguous (unbroken) string of letters (upper case, lower
case, or mixed) that is at least two letters long. (A single letter
is not treated as a word, since a single letter cannot be
misspelled!) Any space, hard-hyphen, numeral, punctuation mark, or
other printable character is treated as a delimiter (or breaking
point) between words. Apostrophes are not considered as delimiters;
instead, they are ignored, as though they were not present.
Similarly, special "control characters" that may have been placed
in the STYLOGRAPH Word Processor (to indicate Character mods like
underlining, boldface, soft-hyphen, etc.) are ignored, so the user
need not worry about them or even be aware of their existence.</para>
      <para>The Spelling Checker
will then display on the user's terminal a listing of all the words
it considers to have questionable spelling. If no possible
misspellings have been detected, the program will automatically
terminate and control will return to OS-9. If possible errors have
been found, they will be listed in a convenient, tabular form or
five columns, followed by a count of their number. At this point,
some users day decide to exit the program rather than to proceed
with the Review process which follows. If the user has routed the
Spelling Checker's output to a printer, this list of possibly
misspelled words will be available as hard copy to be scanned at a
later time (for checking in a conventional dictionary, for
instance).</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>3. The Review process.</title>
      <para>At this point in the
program, the Spelling Checker will sort through its list of
possibly misspelled words and print them on the user's terminal one
at a time, along with a list of five options from which the user
may choose. For example, given the misspelling "occassion", the
user will see displayed:</para>
      <screen>
OCCASSION (I*/D/A/F/X)?
</screen>
      <para>At this time, the user
simply enters one of the five indicated letters (no RETURN is
necessary), and the appropriate action will be taken, as described
next. (Note that the questionable word will be displayed in upper
case only, with no hyphens or apostrophes, regardless of the word's
appearance in the actual text file. At this point, the Spelling
Checker is concerned only with spelling, and this is what it is
asking about.)</para>
      <section>
        <title>The Ignore Option</title>
        <para>The first choice "I",
is the ignore option. Entering the letter "I" will cause the
Spelling Checker to ignore this and all following occurrences of
the word "occassion". The asterisk following the "I" simply
indicates that this is the "default" option; merely entering a
RETURN instead of the letter "I" will cause this option to be
entered. In selecting the Ignore option, the user is indicating
that the spelling of the word is acceptable but that the word
should not be added to the Supplementary Dictionary. This option
will be useful for rare words or abbreviations that are correct but
unlikely to occur in any future files.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>The Display-in-Context Option</title>
        <para>The second choice, "D"
is the Display-in-Context option. This indicates that the user
wishes to see the word displayed in the context in which it
occurred in the original text file before acting on it. When this
option is selected, no immediate action will be taken by the
program. It will delay its display of the word in context until the
entire list of possibly misspelled words has been reviewed. At that
time, all the words selected for display will be presented in
context, one at a time, with a full list or options provided for
each, including the Change option.</para>
        <para>It is important to note
that the Display option provides the only way for the Change option
to be specified. In other words, the user is not permitted to
change the spelling of the word without first viewing it in its
actual context. This is a deliberate restriction in the program
that is intended to prevent the user from changing the spelling of
a word without an appropriate measure of caution.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>The Add-to-Dictionary Option</title>
        <para>The third option, "A"
allows the user to Add the displayed word to of the Supplementary
Dictionary. The actual addition takes place at a later phase of
Spelling Checker's operation, but this is of no concern to the
user. In addition, the user will not be bothered with this word
again during the Review process; the Spelling Checker assumes that
this word is spelled correctly, and it will accept all further
occurrences of this word in the current text file, as well as in
later text files.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>The Flag Option</title>
        <para>The fourth option, "F"
causes all occurrences of the displayed word of to be flagged in
the text file, after it is written to disk following completion of
the remainder of the program. The normal (or default) flag
character is the left arrow (&lt;) appended to the end of all
occurrences of the word in question. Thus, if the word RYTHM is
selected for flagging, it will appear as RHYTHM&lt; (or as
rhythm&lt; if it appears in lower case) in the text file when the
program is finished.</para>
        <para>After the suspect word
his been checked in a conventional dictionary, it is a simple
matter to edit the text file with the STYLOGRAPH word processor and
find all occurrences of the Flag character (&lt;) with the Find
function. If some character other than the left arrow is preferred,
the program asks for an alternative Flag Character, which the user
simply enters in response to a prompt. This option will be most
useful in situations where the user cannot determine the correct
spelling of a word or name at the time of the Review and so must
wait until some later occasion to verify its spelling.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>The Exit Option</title>
        <para>The fifth and last
option, "X" allows the user to exit the Spelling Checker and return
to OS-9. This is a useful feature for the user who is interrupted
and so cannot complete the entire Review. Selecting this option
voids any actions that were taken by the user on the preceding
words; the text file will be left intact, in its original state.
The user may then use the Spelling Checker on the current file at
some later time.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>4. The Display Process</title>
      <para>When the Review is
completed, the Spelling Checker displays all words that have been
selected for Display-in-context. Each selected word is displayed
surrounded by its context in the original text file. This display
will show the text exactly as it occurs in the original file,
preserving upper and lower case, hyphens and apostrophes. For
example, if the selected word is "jumpes" the Display-in-context
might look like this:</para>
      <programlisting>
The quick brown fox jumpes over the lazy dog
</programlisting>
      <para>The Display-in-context contains about 64 characters,
with the selected word appearing near the center of the display. An
upward arrow points to the last letter of the selected word,
allowing it to be located quickly. If any RETURNS occur within this
range of 64 characters, they will be replaced by the STYLOGRAPH
RETURN marker (a broken vertical line). If the selected word occurs
at the very beginning or end of the text file, or if its
immediately preceding or following context contains a long series
of spaces or RETURNS, obviously this will affect the appearance of
the context display.</para>
      <para>After the selected word
is displayed in its context, a prompt will appear that looks like
this:</para>
      <screen>
(I*/A/F/C)?
</screen>
      <para>These symbols indicate
the four options available to the user for acting upon the selected
word. As explained before, "I" indicates Ignore (the default
option), "A" indicates Add to the Supplementary Dictionary, and "F"
indicates Flag the word in the text file. These options operate
exactly as specified in the previous section of the Review
Process.</para>
      <para>The "C" option allows
the user to Change the spelling of the word in the text file. If
this option is selected, the user will be asked to enter the new
spelling for the word. The user should then enter the correct
spelling, being careful to enter it accurately in upper or lower
case as appropriate.</para>
      <para>It should be noted that
if a word contains STYLOGRAPH Character Mods (such as underlining
or boldface), it cannot be Changed, since the Spelling Checker is
not able to handle these modifications. Instead, following a
warning message, the Flag option will be imposed automatically. In
this case, the user will have to correct these modified words with
the STYLOGRAPH word processor. By the same token, no character mods
may be introduced when the correct spelling is entered. Following
entry of the new, changed spelling, the user will be prompted by
the message, "ARE YOU SURE (Y/N)?", at which time entering Y (for
Yes) or N (for No) is expected. If N (No) is entered, the user will
have another opportunity to enter the correct spelling. Once a
change is entered, all further occurrences of the changed word will
be corrected automatically.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>5. Updating the Text File and the Supplementary
Dictionary</title>
      <para>After the preceding
four phases of the Spelling Checker have been completed, the
altered text file (containing flags and changed spellings) will be
written to disk (if any alterations have been made), and the user's
Supplementary Dictionary will be expanded (if required) to include
any words added to the dictionary. Note that these actions will be
taken only as necessary. In other words, if no flags or changes
have been specified, no new text file will be created; if no words
have been selected for addition to the dictionary, no additions to
the Supplementary Dictionary will be made. If a new text file is to
be created, the user will first be warned of any current backup
file that might be deleted in the process. If no backup file
exists. or if the user indicates that a backup file may be deleted,
the original text file will be renamed as a backup file and the
corrected file will be written to disk as a text file.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>6. Using the Utility Programs</title>
      <para>The following utility programs are for manipulating
the Standard dictionary file. In most cases they will not be used
at all. However, there are some users who may wish to make changes
to the dictionary or are curious about the makeup of the
dictionary. The following utilities will allow you to compress and
decompress the dictionary and to add and subtract words from it.
Notice that once the dictionary has been decompressed it is simply
a list of ASCII characters separated by RETURNS. This decompressed
file can then be worked on by other software packages such as
BASIC09, data base management, or sort/merge programs.</para>
      <section>
        <title>SPELLDCM - Dictionary decompression</title>
        <para>This program will take
the compressed dictionary file and output the normal ASCII
character strings to the user's terminal. To look at the words in
the dictionary you could enter the following line from OS9:</para>
        <screen>
OS9: spelldcm /d0/sty/dict
</screen>
        <para>This will cause all of
the words in the dictionary to be listed out to your screen. If you
do this you will notice that all of the words are in alphabetical
order. You will also notice that all of the letters are in upper
case and that there are no spaces or punctuations in the file. By
redirecting the output of this program to a disk file you can
create an text file of the dictionary. For example:</para>
        <screen>
OS9: spelldcm /d0/sty/dict &gt;dictionary
</screen>
        <para>This could take several
minutes to do and there must be plenty of disk space available
since the decompressed file will be four times the size of the
compressed file. You could even rename the resulting file to the
name "DICT" so that the Spelling Checker would use the new file as
the normal dictionary file. This is not recommended since the
decompressed file would take up unnecessary disk space and cause
the Spelling Checker to run much more slowly.</para>
        <note><para>The
decompressed version of the dictionary supplied is over 400k bytes
in size, and will not fit on a mini-floppy disk, (unless
double-sided, 80 track).</para></note>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>SPELLCOM - Dictionary compression</title>
        <para>This program will take
a normal ASCII text file and create a compressed file. For maximum
compression the text file should be in alphabetical order. This
program could compress a file that has been decompressed by the
above program. Also, the supplementary dictionary could be
compressed to speed up the operation of the Spelling Checker. This
will mean that new words cannot be added to this dictionary,
however. There may be some situations in which this may be
desirable since you may want to prevent people from making
unauthorized entries to the supplementary dictionary. This is
particularly true of multi-user systems in which many different
people will be using the dictionary, and not all of them will be
good spellers. This precaution would reduce the chance of
misspellings being added to the dictionary.</para>
        <para>The normal syntax of
the command is as follows:</para>
        <screen>
OS9: spellcom dict4 dict5
</screen>
        <para>This would cause the
text file "DICT4" to be compressed and output to the file "DICT5".
The size of the resulting file will be less than 50% of the
original.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>SPELLADD - Add words to the dictionary</title>
        <para>This is the program
that is normally used to add words to the Standard Dictionary. If
the Supplementary Dictionary gets to be very large you may want to
add it to the Standard Dictionary using this program. With the
original dictionary file "DICT" renamed to "DICTOLD" the command
line would look something like the following:</para>
        <screen>
OS9: chd /d0/sty
OS9: spelladd dictold supp dict
</screen>
        <para>The "DICTOLD" file must
be a compressed file, which should be in alphabetical order. The
"SUPP" file must be an uncompressed (ASCII text) file which may be
in any order. All of the characters should be in upper case and
should not contain any characters other than letters "A" through
"Z". Any other characters that are encountered will simply be
regarded as separators so that the string "ALPHA=BETA" will appear
as separate words "ALPHA" and "BETA" in the dictionary. The new
words will be added in the correct alphabetical sequence. Before
you add any words to the Standard Dictionary you should check them
all carefully to ensure that they are correct. Once incorrect words
are added to the Standard Dictionary, it is very unlikely that
their existence will ever be discovered. You should also remember
that everyone has a few words that they consistently misspell, so
that they will look correct to them when they are checked.
Consequently, all of the words should be checked by someone else or
be looked up in a dictionary before they are added to the Standard
Dictionary. The list of words to be added must be no longer than
about 3,000 words. If the list is too long, the program will
terminate with an error. In that case, the list must be split into
shorter sections and added one at a time.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>SPELLSUB - Remove words from the
dictionary</title>
        <para>This utility will
remove words from the Standard dictionary. This need will rarely
arise, but the utility is included for completeness. It could be
used to shorten the dictionary or to remove misspellings that have
inadvertently been added to the dictionary. Assuming that the
dictionary to be shortened is called "DICTOLD" the command will
look like the following:</para>
        <screen>
OS9: chd /d0/sty
OS9: spellsub dictold /d1/mydir/wrong dict
</screen>
        <para>This will cause all of
the words in the file "WRONG" to be taken out of the file
"DICTOLD". The dictionary file must be a compressed file that is in
alphabetical order. The third name (WRONG in this example) must be
a list of uncompressed (ASCII) words separated by RETURNs. The last
name on the line ("DICT" in this example) will be the name of the
new file, which will have the words omitted.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
</article>
