<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <articleinfo>
    <title>A STYLOGRAPH TUTORIAL</title>
    <titleabbrev>TUTORIAL</titleabbrev>
  </articleinfo>
  <para>This short set of
exercises is designed for the person who is inexperienced with
computers and who will be using STYLOGRAPH. The commands that are
introduced here are only a few of the many commands that are
available through the STYLOGRAPH word processing system. They are,
however, the commands that are most often used, and those that you
will need immediately for practical everyday uses like letter or
report typing. As you go through the tutorial, sit down at the
computer terminal and follow the directions. This will let you
become accustomed to typing on the video terminal and also give you
some idea of the way STYLOGRAPH operates. When you are done with
the tutorial, it is a good idea to go back and read the manual
through to get an idea of the other capabilities of the STYLOGRAPH
system.</para>
  <section>
    <title>A. THE TERMINAL</title>
    <para>There are a few
differences between the typewriter that you have used in the past
and the screen and keyboard that you will be using with STYLOGRAPH.
This section is designed to make you aware of those
differences.</para>
    <important>
      <para>In this manual and
tutorial, we make frequent references to certain special keys, such
as RETURN, ESCAPE, and CONTROL. On your keyboard these may be named
differently. Refer to the Key Assignments Summary At the back of
this manual for a guide to these special keys on your keyboard.</para>
    </important>
    <para>First of all, you will
notice that the letters on the terminal are set up exactly the way
they are on the typewriter. However, there are some extra keys with
special functions that you should notice, because those functions
are important to the working of STYLOGRAPH:</para>
    <para>1. The CAPS LOCK key:
This key is somewhat like an upper-shift lock on a typewriter,
except that it only locks the upper-case for letters; the numbers
and punctuation on the keyboard are unaffected by it. You usually
turn the upper-case on and off by hitting the key. This is a very
useful key when you want to type in capital letters, as it leaves
everything else on the lower case level.</para>
    <para>2. Auto-Repeat
function: Many video terminals will repeat the letter, number, or
punctuation that you are typing if you hold the key down. Some
terminals do not have this feature, but rather, have a REPEAT key
which will produce this function if held down at the same time as
the key that you want repeated.</para>
    <para>3. CONTROL key: The
control key is something like a shift key on the typewriter, except
that it normally produces no real effect on the letters typed on
the video terminal. The CONTROL key. however, is used extensively
in STYLOGRAPH and you should try and locate it on the video
terminal you're using. It's usually somewhere on the left side of
the keyboard. To enter, for example, CONTROL-D, hold down the
CONTROL key and hit the D key.</para>
    <para>4. ESCAPE key: The
ESCAPE key does not appear on a typewriter, but is important to the
workings of STYLOGRAPH. It will be used in STYLOGRAPH
extensively.</para>
    <para>5. RETURN key: The
carriage return is located in the same place as on a typewriter.
You will find, however, that you will use it much less than you
have when you typed in the past. This is because STYLOGRAPH will
automatically move words to the next line for you if they are too
long to fit on the current line you're working on.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>B. TERMINOLOGY</title>
    <para>Before you begin
working through the STYLOGRAPH tutorial, there are a few words that
will be thrown around quite a bit with which you will have to be
familiar.</para>
    <para>1. Character: a
<quote>character</quote> is any of the letters, numbers, or symbols available on
the keyboard. Since the computer codes all characters in numerical
form, it has no real idea that letters are a different kind of
symbol from punctuation marks, so it's easier to refer to all of
them as <quote>characters</quote>.</para>
    <para>2. String: a <quote>string</quote>
refers to one or more characters together. The computer does not
know English (or any other human language, for that matter), and so
the string or characters <quote>v7iu3e:d,q</quote> makes as such sense to the
computer as the string <quote>elephant</quote>. Naturally, only the second
string of characters is intelligible to us, but the computer
doesn't know that. So, it is easier to think of a paragraph
sentence, word, or any part thereof, as a string. Usually, the term
will be used when you are trying to perform some operation on it,
such as <quote>moving a string</quote> or <quote>duplicating a string</quote>.</para>
    <para>3. Edit: <quote>editing</quote>
something on a computer is no different from editing a typewritten
piece of material, except that it's much easier. When you type
something, and it gets edited, you usually have to retype it. Not
so with your computer word-systems, like STYLOGRAPH. Here, you see
the information as it will be printed out so that you can catch any
typing errors, misspellings, etc. Your first print-out is usually
error-free. but even if it isn't, it's no problem to go back and
re-edit it, and get another printout in a matter of minutes.</para>
    <para>4. Text: the word
<quote>text</quote> as used in word processing, isn't much different from the
word's normal English usage in sentences like <quote>The text of the
letter was long</quote>. It simply refers to written information that you
can work on, or edit. If you are thinking like a computer, you can
envisage <quote>text</quote> as a lot of <quote>strings</quote> put together.</para>
    <para>5. Mode: a <quote>mode</quote> is a
certain way of doing things, a kind of <quote>system</quote>. STYLOGRAPH has
three separate <quote>modes</quote> or systems, each of which is used to perform
different types of tasks on the text you wish to edit. These are
the <quote>SUPERVISOR, ESCAPE, and INSERT</quote> modes, and they will be
discussed in more detail below.</para>
    <para>6. Disk: a <quote>disk</quote> is a
piece of flattened magnetic tape: much like cassette tape, on which
the computer can permanently store information and retrieve it at a
later time. Disks are needed because the information that is stored
directly in the computer will disappear when you turn the computer
off. Therefore, you must <quote>save</quote> your text to the disk before
turning the computer off.</para>
    <para>7. File: a <quote>file</quote> is
how information is stored on a disk. It is much like a file in a
filing cabinet, in that it is stored in an organized way for later
retrieval. But the disk system of the computer can do many things
with a file: it can be listed, printed out, processed, copied to
other disks, etc., in only a fraction of the time it would take for
a secretary to do it. The only real difference is that a disk file
tends to contain less information than a <quote>file</quote> in the real
office-life sense. For example, one disk file may contain only one
letter, or only one report.</para>
    <para>8. Cursor: A <quote>cursor</quote>
is a little marker which tells you where you are in the text. On
typewriters, the platen moves from right to left to tell you where
you are on a line. On a computer: the cursor moves from left to
right to tell you <quote>where you are</quote> on the screen. On some video
terminals, the cursor is a solid block, while on others it can be a
blinking block or a simple line underneath the letters. You will
need to identify the cursor on your terminal and move it around to
use STYLOGRAPH.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>C. STARTING THE SYSTEM</title>
    <para>Now that you're
somewhat familiar with the terminology and equipment that will be
used with STYLOGRAPH, we'll get you started on your first
lesson.</para>
    <para>First of all, you must
get your computer running. Refer to your computer manual for this.
When you have the OS-9 prompt</para>
    <screen>OS9:
</screen>
    <para>remove the system disk
from drive 0 and put in your STYLOGRAPH disk. Change your execution
and data directories to this disk by typing:</para>
    <screen>OS9: chx /d0/cmds; chd /d0
</screen>
    <para>If you are using a
Dragon 64 and you are not already in the 51 characters by 24 lines
screen mode, go into that mode with:</para>
    <screen>OS9: go51
</screen>
    <para>To start the STYLOGRAPH
system, all you have to do is to type in the STYLOGRAPH program
name <quote>STYLO</quote> and the name of the file that you will be working on.
To get you going, enter</para>
    <screen>OS9: stylo lesson1
</screen>
    <para>What this will do is
first. load in the STYLOGRAPH word processor, and second, tell
STYLOGRAPH that the name of the text file you will be working on is
<quote>LESSON1</quote> At this point, you will be in one of the three <quote>modes</quote> of
STYLOGRAPH, the SUPERVISOR mode.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>D. THE SUPERVISOR MODE</title>
    <para>If everything is
working correctly, you should now see a list of tasks, or <quote>options</quote>
in front of you on the screen. The tasks should have names like
<quote>EDIT</quote>, <quote>PRINT</quote>, <quote>SAVE AND RETURN</quote> and so forth. Don't be worried
about how long the list is; you'll only be using these three
commands in this short tutorial. This list is called a <quote>menu</quote>. It
is like a restaurant menu because it shows you what is available,
and allows you to make your selection. Now, all you have to do is
to tell it what you want to do. Notice that to the left of the list
is a pointer-like symbol; you need to move the pointer to the task
you want STYLOGRAPH to do, and then hit the RETURN key. You can
move the pointer down by hitting the comma (<quote>,</quote>) key, and you can
move it up by hitting the <quote>I</quote> key. (We know that this makes no
sense at all right now, but bear with us. It soon will). Move the
pointer around a little to get used to it. What you want to do now
is to EDIT some text, so move the pointer to EDIT, and hit
RETURN.</para>
    <para>At this point, you
should see something like this on your screen:</para>
    <screen>--------------------- PAGE 1 --------------------
                                                |
</screen>
    <para>You are now in another
<quote>mode</quote> of STYLOGRAPH, the ESCAPE mode. The ESCAPE mode is designed
to display the text that you're working on and to allow you to do
some things to the text. However, because there is no text to work
on yet, the screen will be pretty empty. In order to enter some
text, you have to go to the third mode of STYLOGRAPH, the INSERT
mode. We will return to the ESCAPE mode a little later. To get into
the INSERT model you only have to hit the semicolon key (<quote>;</quote>).</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>E. THE INSERT MODE</title>
    <para>Now the screen should
look like this:</para>
    <screen>--------------------- PAGE 1 --------------------
------------------------------------------------|
</screen>
    <para>All you need to do now
in order to enter text is to type it in, as if you were typing
normally. Before you start typing, however, you should know two
things about entering text into STYLOGRAPH:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>You don't have to hit
the RETURN key to move to the next line. In fact, STYLOGRAPH keeps
track of how many spaces are left on the line. and will
automatically put the word you are typing on the next line if it
doesn't fit. The number or dashes on the line you are typing let
you know how many spaces are left on the line.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If you make any mistake
as you are typing, you can simply backspace over the error and
retype it. All computer terminals have a backspace key, like
typewriters.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>Now, to show you some
of the features of STYLOGRAPH, type in this sample bit of text:</para>
    <screen>--------------------- PAGE 1 ------------------------
Type in this sample text to demonstrate what kinds of
things STYLOGRAPH can do. Typing is made much easier
because STYLOGRAPH allows you to type in material as
you go along and automatically puts words on the next
line if they are too long.--------------------------|
</screen>
    <para>You may be wondering what you do use the RETURN key for. You use
it if you want to start typing in text on a new line. This is for
new paragraphs, skipping lines, or any other time that you don't
need to finish a line. For example, of you now hit a RETURN and
type another line in the sample text, it will look like this:</para>
    <screen>------------------------ PAGE 1 ------------------------
Type in this sample text to demonstrate what kinds of
things STYLOGRAPH can do. Typing is made much easier
because STYLOGRAPH allows you to type in material as
you go along and automatically puts words on the next
line if they are too long.                             |
   This text should start on the next line because you
have hit a carriage RETURN-----------------------------|
</screen>
    <para>You will notice that
when you hit a carriage RETURN, STYLOGRAPH signifies it with a
vertical mark on the right hand margin.</para>
    <para>Now that you can enter
text into STYLOGRAPH using the INSERT mode, there are some other
things that you can do in the INSERT mode which will make your
typed work come out formatted perfectly. When you type on a
typewriter, you can set margins. The same thing is true of
STYLOGRAPH; you can set margins using a set of format commands that
are entered in the INSERT mode like regular text, but do not appear
on the final printed copy.</para>
    <para>Each of the format
commands requires a line all for itself. You will have to hit
another RETURN to enter the commands. Right and left margins are
set separately. You can set the left margins by entering a:</para>
    <screen>,lm 12
</screen>
    <para>on the line. Note that
the comma MUST be the first character on the line. (there must be
no preceding spaces), there MUST be no gap between the comma and
the command <quote>lm</quote>, and there MUST be a space between the command and
the numeric parameter, <quote>12</quote>. What this will do is set the start of
the left margin at 12 spaces in from the left boundary of the
paper. Of course you don't have to use 12, the left margin can be
set at 10, 8, or any other number you please. Usually 10 or 12 are
the standards, however. The command will not appear on the
print-out of the text.</para>
    <para>Right margins are set a
little differently, but use the same restrictions as for the left
margin command. The right margins are set by allowing a certain
line length for each line. If you only allow a certain number of
spaces per line, this will naturally set the right margin. To set
the right margin, hit another RETURN and enter:</para>
    <screen>,ll 48
</screen>
    <para>Your text should now
look like this:</para>
    <screen>------------------------ PAGE 1 ------------------------
Type in this sample text to demonstrate what kinds of
things STYLOGRAPH can do. Typing is made much easier
because STYLOGRAPH allows you to type in material as
you go along and automatically puts words on the next
line if they are too long.                             |
  This text should start on the next line because you
have hit a carriage RETURN
,lm 12
,ll 48
--------------------------------------                 |
</screen>
    <para>Notice that the line of
dashes does not extend all the way to the end of the screen. This
is because you have set the right margin with the <command>,ll</command> command.
Naturally, your line length need not be 48; it can be anything,
although 65 and 75 are the usual standards.</para>
    <para>One of the most
frustrating jobs in typing is centring titles on a page. This is
easily done with another STYLOGRAPH format command, however. The
centring command looks like this:</para>
    <screen>,ce
</screen>
    <para>Enter the command, hit
a RETURN, and type in the following lane:</para>
    <screen>       Presto! This line is centred.---------------|
</screen>
    <para>Now hit the RETURN, and
presto! the line is centred. The <command>,ce</command> command may be followed by any
number, and STYLOGRAPH will automatically centre that next number
of lines. For example, the command</para>
    <screen>.ce 5
</screen>
    <para>will centre the next
five lines of text. Again, remember that you need to follow the
restrictions of the margin commands that the command start in the
first space of the line, and that the command be preceded by a
comma.</para>
    <para>Along with centring,
you often have to put things on the right margin. Examples of this
(it's called <quote>right justification</quote>) are the return addresses and
dates of business letters, and the page numbers of reports. A
STYLOGRAPH format command will also do this for you automatically.
In your sample text, type in:</para>
    <screen>,rj
</screen>
    <para>followed by RETURN, and then:</para>
    <screen>December 19, 1943-------------------   |
</screen>
    <para>followed by another
RETURN. This should result in the date being placed against the far
right margin:</para>
    <screen>                                              December 19, 1943  |
</screen>
    <para>As with the <command>,ce</command>
command, you can follow the <command>,rj</command> command with any number, and
STYLOGRAPH will automatically right-justify that many lines of
following text. Your entire text should look like this now:</para>
    <screen>Type in this sample text to demonstrate what kinds of
things STYLOGRAPH can do. Typing is made much easier
because STYLOGRAPH allows you to type in material as
you go along and automatically puts words on the next
line if they are too long.                             |
   This text should start on the next line because you
have hit a carriage RETURN
,lm 12                                                 |
,ll 48                                                 |
,ce                                                    |
            Presto! This line is centred
,rj                                                    |
                                      December 19, 1943|
</screen>
    <para>There is one last
INSERT mode feature of STYLOGRAPH that will be described in this
tutorial. The <quote>header</quote> and <quote>footer</quote> features let you set the top
and bottom margins for the pages. They are also very useful if your
letter or report extends beyond one page long, and if certain
things will have to be printed on the top or the bottom of each
page.</para>
    <para>STYLOGRAPH lets you
specify what you want printed, or how many lines to skip, on the
top or bottom of every page <citetitle>once</citetitle>, and then will
automatically do it for you as each page is printed out. Things
that are printed at the top of the page are called <quote>headers</quote> and
things that are printed at the bottom of the page are called
<quote>footers</quote>. In combination with the <command>,rj</command> and <command>,ce</command> commands, you can do
some very fancy formatting. You can define a <quote>header</quote> with the
following commands:</para>
    <screen>,hd
,,
</screen>
    <para>Anything placed between
the <command>,hd</command> and <command>,,</command> will be repeated at the top of every page of text.
So, for example, if you entered the following chain of commands
(remember to follow each of the with a carriage RETURN):</para>
    <screen>,hd                                                    |
                                                       |
,rj                                                    |
19/12/43                                               |
,,                                                     |
</screen>
    <para>It would cause the date
<quote>19/12/43</quote> to be printed out on the edge of the right margin at
every page of the text printout. Too see this work, enter the chain
of commands, and then enter the following command which will skip
to another page:</para>
    <screen>,pg
</screen>
    <para>After a RETURN, your
entire screen should look something like this:</para>
    <screen>------------------------ PAGE 1 ------------------------
Type in this sample text to demonstrate what kinds of
things STYLOGRAPH can do. Typing is made much easier
because STYLOGRAPH allows you to type in material as
you go along and automatically puts words on the next
line if they are too long.                             |
   This text should start on the next line because you
have hit a carriage RETURN
,lm 12                                                 |
,ll 48                                                 |
,ce                                                    |
            Presto! This line is centred
,rj                                                    |
                                      December 19, 1943|
,hd                                                    |
                                                       |
,rj                                                    |
19/12/43                                               |
,,                                                     |
,pg                                                    |
------------------------ PAGE 2 -----------------------|
                                                       -
                                              19/12/43 -
                                                       -
-------------------------------------------------------|
</screen>
    <para>The three dashes which
appear on the right margin edge of the top of page 2 signify that
these three lines are indeed, a header. You could now add
additional text if you wanted. The <quote>footer</quote> command is essentially
the same, except that the command looks like this:</para>
    <screen>,ft
,,
</screen>
    <para>and that any material
entered between the <command>,ft</command> and the <command>,,</command> would be printed out
automatically at the bottom of the page. In practicing a footer, we will introduce one
more nice feature of STYLOGRAPH: the automatic page numbering. By
using the symbol <quote>#</quote> in any header or footer of a STYLOGRAPH text
file, the page number will replace the symbol in the final
printout. For example, enter the next set of commands (again,
following each with a RETURN):</para>
    <screen>,ft                                                    |
                                                       |
,ce                                                    |
PAGE #                                                 |
                                                       |
,,                                                     |
</screen>
    <para>and following these
commands with another <command>,pg</command> command, Page 2 of your text will look
like this:</para>
    <screen>------------------------ PAGE 2 -----------------------|
                                                       -
                                              19/12/43 -
                                                       -
,ft                                                    |
                                                       |
,ce                                                    |
PAGE #                                                 |
                                                       |
,,                                                     |
,pg                                                    |
                                                       -
                         Page 2                        -
                                                       -
------------------------ PAGE 3 -----------------------|
</screen>
    <para>STYLOGRAPH will
automatically increase the page numbers by one every time you go
onto a new page. Note again the dashes in the right margin of the
footer, signifying that it is put there by the footer command, and
not by you.</para>
    <important>
      <para>
You don't need to use the <command>,pg</command> command when you get to the bottom of
the page. STYLOGRAPH also keeps track of the number of lines on the
page and will automatically skip to a new page when you run out of
lines. You can see the usefulness of this if you've ever ended up
typing on the very bottom of a sheet of paper because you forgot to
keep track of yourself.</para>
    </important>
    <para>Now that you have practiced a little with the INSERT
mode, let's move back to the ESCAPE mode, and see what kinds of
tricks can be done there. All you need to do to get back into the
ESCAPE mode is to hit the ESCAPE key. This will remove the dashes
that you see in the INSERT mode.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>F . THE ESCAPE MODE</title>
    <para>The escape mode is
designed to display the text you have entered so that you may
easily work on it. To <quote>work</quote> on any particular part of the text you
will need to move the cursor to it (remember <quote>cursor</quote>'?). The
cursor is moved by using four keys on the right side of the
keyboard:</para>
    <screen>                             I
                           J   L
                             ,
</screen>
    <para>Each of these keys will
move the cursor in a different direction. You can remember the
direction of each key if you just remember the position of the
keys: Left and Right movement is controlled by the <quote>J</quote> (left) and
<quote>L</quote> (right) keys, while up and down movement is controlled by the
<quote>I</quote> (up) and <quote>,</quote> (down) keys. While this might seem awkward at
present it will become very easy to move in and around your text
after only a few hours experience with STYLOGRAPH.</para>
    <para>Now while you are in
the ESCAPE mode, use the cursor movement keys to move back to the
top of the text you have just entered. You probably need only to
use the <quote>I</quote> and <quote>J</quote> keys at this point. You may hear a beep or bell
if you have been moving the cursor around and it has run out of
room in the direction you were going. You can either come to the
<quote>top</quote> (beginning) or <quote>bottom</quote> (ending) of the text, but you haven't
done any damage. Practice moving the cursor around to different
places in the text you have entered. It's very important that you
know how to direct the cursor around to various parts of the text,
because cursor position is a crucial feature in executing many
commands in the ESCAPE mode.</para>
    <para>Once you have mastered
this, it's time to show you some of the more useful features of the
STYLOGRAPH system. One of the most powerful commands in the ESCAPE
mode is the <quote>Find</quote> command. Place the cursor at the start of the
text, and hit the <quote>F</quote> key. This will cause the following to be
printed on the terminal:</para>
    <screen>*** FIND {
</screen>
    <para>At this point, if you
enter any string (remember string?) that is located anywhere in the
text you have entered. STYLOGRAPH will search for it, find it, and
move the cursor to it. For example, enter the string <quote>typ</quote> and hit
the RETURN. The cursor should now be placed in front of the word
<quote>type</quote> in the second sentence of the text you have entered, and
another message should have appeared:</para>
    <screen>*** STOP (RET) OR CONTINUE (SP)?
</screen>
    <para>What STYLOGRAPH wants
to know now is whether you want to keep looking for the string
<quote>typ</quote>, or stop at this string. If you want it to stop here, you can
hit the RETURN. If you want it to keep looking for the string you
have specified, hit the space bar. If you do hit the space bar, you
will find that the cursor has been moved to the next occurrence of
the string <quote>typ</quote>, the word <quote>typing</quote> in the next sentence, and the
stop-or-continue message has reappeared. If you hit the space bar
again, it will go to the third occurrence of the <quote>typ</quote> string in
the text; namely, the word <quote>typed</quote> in the next sentence. If you hit
the space bar again, the error bell/beep will ring, telling you
that the string does not occur again anywhere in the text after the
word <quote>typed</quote> in the third sentence. Note that STYLOGRAPH searches
for strings from the position of the cursor at the time of the
command down to the bottom of the text. Any occurrence of the
string above the cursor when you give the <quote>FIND</quote> command will not
be found.</para>
    <para>A powerful variant of
the <quote>FIND</quote> command is the <quote>REPLACE</quote> command, which will find any
string, and replace it with any other specified string. Place the
cursor at the top of the text again. Now, hit the <quote>R</quote> key. A
message will appear:</para>
    <screen>*** REPLACE {
</screen>
    <para>Now enter a string; for
example, let's replace the word <quote>allows</quote> in the text with the word
<quote>lets</quote>. Simply enter the word <quote>allows</quote> and hit the RETURN. At this
point the screen should look like this:</para>
    <screen>*** REPLACE {allows}
*** WITH {
</screen>
    <para>Now enter the word
<quote>lets</quote> and again hit the RETURN. At this point, STYLOGRAPH will
search for the string <quote>allows</quote> and place the cursor at it. You will
also be asked whether or not you want to change it:</para>
    <screen>*** REPLACE (Y-N-A)?
</screen>
    <para><quote>Y-N-A</quote> is an
abbreviation of <quote>Yes-No-All</quote> If you answer <quote>Y</quote> then it will replace
<quote>allows</quote> with <quote>lets</quote>. If you answer <quote>N</quote> then it will go to the next
occurrence of <quote>allows</quote> in the text (since there is no next
occurrence here, it will ring the bell) and ask you the same
question. If you answer <quote>A</quote> it will replace all of the occurrences
of <quote>allows</quote> that it finds in the text with the string <quote>lets</quote>. You
usually should not use the <quote>A</quote> option, because STYLOGRAPH will not
show you all of the changes it makes. Nevertheless, you can see
what a nice feature this is if you have ever misspelled a word or
name consistently throughout a letter or report; now all you have
to do is tell STYLOGRAPH to REPLACE it with the correct
spelling.</para>
    <para>You often have to
underline words when you type letters or reports. One more command
that you can use from the ESCAPE mode will do this for you
automatically when you have a printout made of your text. For
example, if you wanted to underline the word <quote>Stylograph</quote> in the
text passage you have entered, simply move the cursor to the first
letter of the word, either by moving it manually with the <quote>I</quote>, <quote>J</quote>,
<quote>,</quote> and <quote>L</quote> keys, or with the <quote>FIND</quote> function. Now all you need to
do is to hold down the CONTROL key and hit the U (for Underline)
key for each letter you want underlined. You will notice that this
operation changes the display of the letters you have <quote>underlined</quote>
to tell you that something has been done to the letters when you
look through the text again. Now when you have the text printed
out, the work <quote>Stylograph</quote> will be underlined.</para>
    <para>There are two other
ESCAPE mode commands which come in handy when you are working on a
letter or report and you want to make some simple changes. Both of
these commands are used to remove unwanted letters or words from
the text. To erase single letters or spaces from a text, all you
have to do is position the cursor at the letter, and then hit
CONTROL-D (for delete). This will cause the letter to disappear,
and the rest of the text will <quote>move up</quote> to fill in the gap left by
the erased letter. Try this on any letter of the text that you have
entered. A similar command is used to delete entire words from the
text; to do this, simply place the cursor at the word you want
erased, and hit CONTROL-W (for word). Again, the word will
disappear, and the rest of the text will move up to fill the gap
left by its disappearance. Note that any punctuation symbols not
separated from the word by a space will also be deleted. When you
use these commands, be careful, because if you hold the keys down
for any length of time longer than needed for one letter or word,
you may delete more than one.</para>
    <para>Now you know all the
commands you need to enter text to format it perfectly and to edit
any typing errors you have made and missed earlier. It's time to
take a look at the printed copy, and to go back to the SUPERVISOR
mode. To do this: just hit the slash <quote>/</quote> key.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>G. THE SUPERVISOR MODE (Again)</title>
    <para>The <quote>menu</quote> should have
reappeared now. As before, to request any of the tasks on the menu,
position the pointer next to it. Let's print out the text you've
entered by using the <quote>I</quote> and <quote>,</quote> keys to move to the PRINT command.
Make sure that your printer is correctly connected up to your
computer. We are assuming that you are using a parallel printer ion
the parallel printer port <quote>/p1</quote>. Once you've done that, hit the
RETURN. This will cause STYLOGRAPH to ask you some questions that
you needn't worry about right now:</para>
    <screen>Different Printer (Y/N*)?
Stop for New Pages (Y/N*)?
Print all Pages (Y*/N)?
</screen>
    <para>For the present time,
just hit the RETURN key for each of them, and the text should be
printed out on the printer. Once this is done, you should notice
that on the printout, the format commands should not be visible,
the headers and footers are properly executed, and that the text
appears as it did in the ESCAPE and INSERT modes. If any of these
is wrong, go back to the portion of the tutorial where instructions
were given for it, and see what went wrong, correct it using either
the ESCAPE commands or INSERT mode, and print it out again. Once
the text is printed out, the pointer on the SUPERVISOR menu will
again be positioned at the EDIT option. You can return to edit the
text further by simply hitting the RETURN as before. If the
printout is satisfactory. you can save the text permanently on a
disk by positioning the pointer to the SAVE AND RETURN option. At
this position, hit the RETURN again, and you will hear the disk run
for a short time and then the screen will clear showing the OS-9
prompt:</para>
    <screen>OS9:
</screen>
    <para>If you look at the
contents of the disk, using the 'dir' command, you should find that
a file named <quote>LESSON1</quote> exists on it. This is the text file you have
created with STYLOGRAPH and this tutorial. In order to work on it
further, simply repeat the command you used to create the file in
the first place:</para>
    <screen>OS9: stylo lesson1
</screen>
    <para>This will again
activate the STYLOGRAPH system, load in your text file, and put you
in the SUPERVISOR mode. where you may EDIT, PRINT, and SAVE the
file again.</para>
    <para>We hope that this
course has been useful. You should read the entire manual in order
to get a good idea of the many other features of STYLOGRAPH. You
will eventually find word processing a very easy and efficient way
to edit and print documents; in fact, after you have mastered it
you will undoubtedly wonder how you ever got along without it.</para>
  </section>
</article>
