<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
<title>Basic System Organization</title>
<para>
OS-9 is a modular operating system that has been designed so that each
module provides specific functions. The modularity of OS-9 allows
modules to be included in the system or deleted when OS-9 is configured
on a specific computer depending on the functions that the operating
system is to perform. For example, a small, ROM based control computer
does not need the disk related OS-9 modules.
</para>
<figure>
<title>OS-9 Component Module Organization</title>
<screen>
                     +-----------------------+
    +----------+     !                       !     +----------+
    !          !     !                       !     !          !
    !   INIT   ! - - !     OS-9 KERNEL       ! - - !  Clock   !
    !          !     !   (OS9P1, OS9P2)      !     !          !
    +----------+     !                       !     +----------+
                     +-----------------------+
                                 !
                                 !
                     +-----------------------+
                     !                       !
                     ! Input/Output Manager  !
                     !       (IOMAN)         !
                     !                       !
                     +-----------------------+
                        |        |        |
             |----------|        |        |---------|
       .-----------.       .-----------.      .------------.
       |           |       |           |      |            |
       | Disk File |       | Pipe File |      | Char. File |
       |  Manager  |       |  Manager  |      |  Manager   |
       |   (RBF)   |       | (Pipeman) |      |   (SBF)    |
       |           |       |           |      |            |
       '-----------'       '-----------'      '------------'
       |          |              |             |           |
       |          |              |             |           |
  .--------.  .--------.    .--------.    .--------.  .--------.
  |        |  |        |    |        |    |        |  |        |
  |  Disk  |  |  Disk  |    |  Pipe  |    |  ACIA  |  |  PIA   |
  | Driver |  | Driver |    | Driver |    | Driver |  | Driver |
  |        |  |        |    | (Piper)|    |        |  |        |
  '--------'  '--------'    '--------'    '--------'  '--------'
   |     |     |     |           |         |     |     |     |
   |     |     |     |           |         |     |     |     |
 .---. .---. .---. .---.    .--------.   .---. .---. .---. .---.
 |D0 | |D1 | |D2 | |D3 |    |  Pipe  |   |T1 | |T2 | |P1 | |P2 |
 '---' '---' '---' '---'    '--------'   '---' '---' '---' '---'
RBF Device Descriptors     Pipe Descr.    SCF Device Descriptors
</screen>
</figure>
<para>
Notice that the diagram on the previous page clearly shows OS-9's
multilevel organization.
</para>


<bridgehead renderas="sect5">
Level 1 - Kernal and Clock Module
</bridgehead>
<para>

The first level contains the KERNEL, CLOCK MODULE, and INIT. The
kernel provide basic system services such as multitasking, memory
management, and links all other system modules. The CLOCK module is a
software handler for the specific real-time-clock hardware. INIT is an
initialization table used by the kernel during system startup. It
specifies initial table sizes, initial system device names, etc.
</para>


<bridgehead renderas="sect5">
Level 2 - Input/Output Manager (IOMAN)
</bridgehead>
<para>
The second level is the Input/Output Manager (IOMAN). It provides
common processing to all I/O operations. The I/0 Manager is required if
any OS-supported I/0 is to be performed.
</para>


<bridgehead renderas="sect5">
Level 3 - File Manager Level (RBF, SCF, and Pipeman)
</bridgehead>
<para>
The third level is the File Manager level. File managers perform I/O
request processing for similar classes of I/O devices. The Random Block
File Manager (RBF) processes all disk-type device functions, and the
Sequential Character File Manager (SCF) handles all non-mass storage
devices that basically operate a character at a time, such as terminals
and printers. The user can add additional File Managers to handle
classes of devices not covered by SCF or RBF. Another file manager
called PIPEMAN supports the <quote>pipe</quote> interprocess communication method that
uses memory buffers for data transfer instead of mass storage files.
</para>


<bridgehead renderas="sect5">
Level 4 - Device Drivers
</bridgehead>
<para>
The fourth level is the Device Driver Level. Device drivers handle
basic physical I/O functions for specific I/O controller hardware.
Standard OS-9 systems are typically supplied with a disk driver, an ACIA
driver for terminals and serial printers, and a PIA driver for parallel
printers. Many users add. customized drivers of their own design or
purchase drivers from a hardware vendor.
</para>


<bridgehead renderas="sect5">
Level 5 - Device Descriptors
</bridgehead>
<para>
The fifth level is the Device Descriptor Level. These modules are
small tables that associate specific I/O ports with their logical names,
and the port's device driver and file manager. They also contain the
physical address of the port and initialization data. By use of device
descriptors, only one copy of each driver is required for each specific
type of I/O controller regardless of how many controllers the system
uses.
</para>
<para>
One important component not shown is the <application>Shell</application>, which is the command
interpreter. It is technically a program and not part of the operating
system itself and is described fully in the <citetitle pubwork="book">OS-9 User's Manual</citetitle>.
</para>
<para>
Even though all modules can be resident in ROM, generally only the
KERNEL and INIT modules are ROMed in disk-based systems. All other
modules are loaded into RAM during system startup by a disk bootstrap
module called BOOT (not shown on diagram) which is also resident in ROM.
</para>

</chapter>
