<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
<title>Memory Modules</title>

<para>Any object to be loaded into the memory of an OS-9 system must use
the memory module format and conventions. The memory module concept
allows OS-9 to manage the logical contents as well as the physical
contents of memory. The basic idea is that all programs are
individual, named objects.</para>

<para>
The operating system keeps track of modules which are in memory at all
times by the use of a "module directory". The module directory contains
the address of each module and a count of how many processes are using
each particular module. When modules are loaded into memory, they are
added to the module directory. When a process links to a module in
memory, its link count is incremented by one. When modules are no
longer needed (a link count of 0), their memory is deallocated and the
module name removed from the directory (except ROMS, which are discussed
later). In many respects, modules and memory in general, are managed
like a disk. In fact, the disk and memory management sections of OS-9
share many subroutines.
</para>
<para>Each module has three parts; a module header, module body and a
cyclic-redundancy-check (CRC) value. The header contains information
that describes the module and its use. This information includes: the
modules size, its type (machine language. BASIC09 compiled code,
etc); attributes (executable, reentrant, etc), data storage memory
requirements, execution starting address, etc. The CRC value is used
to verify the integrity of a module.</para>

<para>There are several different kinds of modules, each type having a
different usage and function. Modules do not have to be complete
programs, or even 6809 machine language. They may contain BASIC09
<quote>I-code</quote>, constants, single subroutines, subroutine packages, etc. The
main requirements are that modules do not modify themselves and that
they be position-independent so OS-9 can load or relocate them
wherever memory space is available. In this respect, the module
format is the OS-9 equivalent of <quote>load records</quote> used in
older operating systems.</para>

<sect1>
<title>Memory Module Structure</title>

<para>At the beginning (lowest address) of the module is the module
header, which can have several forms depending on the module's
usage. OS-9 family software such as BASIC09, Pascal, C, the
assembler, and many utility programs automatically generate modules
and headers. Following the header is the program/constant section
which is usually pure code. The module name string is included
somewhere in this area. The last three bytes of the module are a
three-byte Cyclic Redundancy Check (CRC) value used to verify the
integrity of the module.</para>

<table>
<title>Module Format</title>
<tgroup cols="1">
<colspec colwidth="1.5in"/>
    <tbody>
    <row rowsep="1">
	<entry align="center">MODULE HEADER</entry>
    </row>
    <row rowsep="1">
	<entry align="center">PROGRAM OR CONSTANTS</entry>
    </row>
    <row rowsep="1">
	<entry align="center">CRC</entry>
    </row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>

<para>The 24-bit CRC is performed over the entire module from the first
byte of the module header to the byte just before the CRC itself. The
CRC polynomial used is $800FE3.</para>

<para>Because most OS-9 family software (such as the assembler)
automatically generate the module header and CRC values, the
programmer usually does not have to be concerned with writing
routines to generate them.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1>
<title>Module Header Definitions</title>

<para>The first nine bytes of all module headers are identical:
</para>

<informaltable frame="none" rowsep="0" colsep="0">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colwidth="0.9in" align="right"/>
<colspec colwidth="4in"/>
<thead>
<row>
	<entry>MODULE OFFSET</entry>
	<entry>DESCRIPTION</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
	<entry>$0,$1 =</entry>
	<entry>Sync Bytes ($87,$CD). These two constant bytes are used to
	locate modules.</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry>$2,$3 =</entry>
<entry>Module Size. The overall size of the module in bytes (includes
CRC).</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry>$4,$5 =</entry>
<entry>Offset to Module Name. The address of the module name string
relative to the start (first sync byte) of the module. The name
string can be located anywhere in the module and consists of a string
of ASCII characters having the sign bit set on the last character.
</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry>$6 =</entry>
	<entry>Module Type/Language Type. See text.</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry>$7 =</entry>
	<entry>Attributes/Revision Level. See text.</entry>
</row>

<row>
	<entry>$8 =</entry>
	<entry>Header Check. The one's compliment of (the vertical parity
	(exclusive OR) of) the previous eight bytes</entry>
</row>

</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>

<sect2>
<title>Type/Language Byte</title>

<para>The module type is coded into the four most significant bits of
byte 6 of the module header. Eight types are pre-defined by
convention, some of which are for OS-9's internal use only. The type
codes are:</para>
<informaltable frame="none" rowsep="0" colsep="0">
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colwidth="0.9in" colname="c1"/>
<colspec colwidth="1in" colname="c2"/>
<colspec colwidth="3in" colname="c3"/>
<spanspec spanname="two" namest="c2" nameend="c3"/>

    <thead>
        <row><entry>Code</entry><entry>Name</entry><entry>Meaning</entry></row>
    </thead>
	<tbody>
		<row>
				<entry>$10</entry>
				<entry>Prgrm</entry>
				<entry>Program module</entry>
		</row>
		<row>
				<entry>$20</entry>
				<entry>Sbrtn</entry>
				<entry>Subroutine module</entry>
		</row>
		<row>
				<entry>$30</entry>
				<entry>Multi</entry>
				<entry>Multi-module (for future use)</entry>
		</row>
		<row>
				<entry>$40</entry>
				<entry>Data</entry>
				<entry>Data module</entry>
		</row>
		<row>
				<entry>$50-$B0</entry>
				<entry spanname="two">User-definable</entry>
		</row>
		<row>
				<entry>$C0</entry>
				<entry>Systm</entry>
				<entry>OS-9 System module</entry>
		</row>
		<row>
				<entry>$D0</entry>
				<entry>FlMgr</entry>
				<entry>OS-9 File Manager module</entry>
		</row>
		<row>
				<entry>$E0</entry>
				<entry>Drivr</entry>
				<entry>OS-9 Device Driver module</entry>
		</row>
		<row>
				<entry>$F0</entry>
				<entry>Devic</entry>
				<entry>OS-9 Device Descriptor module</entry>
		</row>
	</tbody>
    </tgroup>
</informaltable>

<note><para>0 is not a legal type code.</para></note>

<para>
The four least significant bits of byte 6 describe the language type as
listed below:
</para>

<informaltable frame="none" rowsep="0" colsep="0">
<tgroup cols="3">
<colspec colwidth="0.9in" colname="c1"/>
<colspec colwidth="1in" colname="c2"/>
<colspec colwidth="4in" colname="c3"/>
<spanspec spanname="two" namest="c2" nameend="c3"/>
    <tbody>
        <row>
            <entry>0</entry>
            <entry>Data</entry>
            <entry>Data (non-executable)</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>1</entry>
            <entry>Objct</entry>
            <entry>6809 object code</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>2</entry>
            <entry>ICode</entry>
            <entry>BASIC09 I-code</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>3</entry>
            <entry>PCode</entry>
            <entry>PASCAL P-code</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry></entry>
            <entry spanname="two">The following are currently not implemented:</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>4</entry>
            <entry>CCode</entry>
            <entry>C I-code</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>5</entry>
            <entry>CblCode</entry>
            <entry>COBOL I-code</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>6</entry>
            <entry>FrtnCode</entry>
            <entry>FORTRAN I-code</entry>
        </row>
	</tbody>
    </tgroup>
</informaltable>

<para>
The purpose of the language type is so high-level language run-time
systems can verify that a module is of the correct type before execution
is attempted. BASIC09, for example, may run either I-code or 6809
machine language procedures arbitrarily by checking the language type
code.
</para>
</sect2>
<sect2>
<title>Attribute/Revision Byte</title>

<para>
The upper four bits of this byte are reserved for module attributes. Currently,
only bit 7 is defined, and when set indicates the module is reentrant and
therefore <quote>sharable</quote>.
</para>
<para>
The lower four bits are a revision level from zero (lowest) to
fifteen. If more than one module has the same name, type, language,
etc., OS-9 only keeps in the module directory the module having the
highest revision level. This is how ROMed modules can be replaced or
patched: you load a new equivalent module having a higher revision
level. Because all modules locate each other by using the LINK system
call which searches the module directory by name, it always returns the
latest revision of the module, wherever it may be.
</para>
<para>
NOTE: A previously linked module can not be replaced until all processes
which linked to it have unlinked it (after its link count goes to zero).
When a new module is loaded, it will go into the module directory. Both
copies will be in memory, but previous users will use the old copy until
they unlink from the old and link to the new module.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Other Level II Memory Management Characteristics</title>
<para>
The following features apply only to Level II systems.
</para>

<bridgehead renderas="sect5">Preloading Modules</bridgehead>
<para>
Memory modules loaded by the LOAD command or F$LOAD system call are
loaded into memory and added to the module directory but are not mapped
into any process' address space until executed or LINKed. Thus, a large
number of modules can be preloaded into memory for fast access when
needed. By judicious use of LOAD, LINK and UNLINK more than 64K of
modularized code can be accessed by one task.
</para>
<bridgehead renderas="sect5">Shared Data Modules</bridgehead>
<para>
Because one or more memory modules (hence, memory blocks) can be
mapped simultaneously into several logical maps (and frequently are for
programs such as Basic09), RAM data modules can be used to allow two or
more tasks to share a common data area. The assembler is used to create
a memory module with the proper header, CRC, etc., and PCB, FDB, FCC,
FCS, directives only to initialize all required data space.
</para>
<bridgehead renderas="sect5">Write Protect</bridgehead>
<para>
If the system MMU has this feature and the OS-9 option is enabled,
OS-9 will write-protect any blocks containing Sharable memory modules.
Sharable modules have the "reentrant" bit set in the module header. This
increases system security by protecting all tasks sharing a copy of a
memory module from another process accidentally (or deliberately)
altering the shared module. Note that in order to "patch" modules in
systems with write protect the "reentrant'I atribute bit must be cleared
(on disk) prior to loading into memory.
</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Typed Module Headers</title>
<para>
As mentioned before, the first nine bytes of the module header are
defined identically for all module types. There is usually more header
information immediately following, the layout and meaning varies
depending on the specific module type. Module types $C - $F are used
exclusively by OS-9. Their format is given elsewhere in this manual.
</para>

<para>
The module type illustrated below is the general purpose <quote>user</quote> format
that is commonly user for OS-9 programs that are called using the FORK or
CHAIN system calls. These modules are the
<quote>user-defined</quote> types having type codes of 5 through E. They
have four more bytes in their headers defined as follows:
</para>

<informaltable frame="none" rowsep="0" colsep="0">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colwidth="0.9in" align="right"/>
<colspec colwidth="4in"/>
	<thead>
		<row>
			<entry>MODULE OFFSET</entry>
			<entry>DESCRIPTION</entry>
		</row>
	</thead>
	<tbody>
		<row>
	<entry>$9,$A =</entry>
	<entry>Execution Offset. The program or subroutine's starting
	address, relative to the first byte of the sync code. Modules
	having multiple entry points (cold start, warm start, etc.) may
	have a branch table starting at this address.</entry>
		</row>
		<row>
    <entry>$B,$C =</entry>
    <entry><para>Permanent Storage Requirement. This is the minimum number of
    bytes of data storage required to run. This is the number used by
    <xref linkend="f.fork"/> and <xref linkend="f.chain"/>
    to allocate a process' data area.</para><para>
    If the module will not be directly executed by a <xref linkend="f.chain"/>
    or <xref linkend="f.fork"/>
    service request (for instance a subroutine package), this entry
    is not used by OS-9. It is commonly used to specify the maximum
    stack size required by reentrant subroutine modules. The calling
    program can check this value to determine if the subroutine has
    enough stack space.</para></entry>
		</row>
	</tbody>
    </tgroup>
</informaltable>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Executable Memory Module Format</title>
<informalfigure>
<screen>
Relative            Usage                    Check Range
Address

        +------------------------------+  ---+--------+---
 $00    |                              |     |        |
        +--    Sync Bytes ($87CD)    --+     |        |
 $01    |                              |     |        |
        +------------------------------+     |        |
 $02    |                              |     |        |
        +--   Module Size (bytes)    --+     |        |
 $03    |                              |     |        |
        +------------------------------+     |        |
 $04    |                              |     |        |
        +--   Module Name Offset     --+   header     |
 $05    |                              |   parity     |
        +------------------------------+     |        |
 $06    |     Type     |   Language    |     |        |
        +------------------------------+     |        |
 $07    |  Attributes  |   Revision    |     |        |
        +------------------------------+  ---+--    module
 $08    |     Header Parity Check      |             CRC
        +------------------------------+              |
 $09    |                              |              |
        +--     Execution Offset     --+              |
 $0A    |                              |              |
        +------------------------------+              |
 $0B    |                              |              |
        +--  Permanent Storage Size  --+              |
 $0C    |                              |              |
        +------------------------------+              |
 $0D    |                              |              |
        |  (Add'l optional header      |              |
        |   extensions located here    |              |
        |                              |              |
        |  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .  .   |              |
        |                              |              |
        |                              |              |
        |       Module Body            |              |
        | object code, constants, etc. |              |
        |                              |              |
        |                              |              |
        +------------------------------+              |
        |                              |              |
        +--                          --+              |
        |       CRC Check Value        |              |
        +--                          --+              |
        |                              |              |
        +------------------------------+  ------------+---
</screen>
</informalfigure>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>ROMed Memory Modules</title>

<para>When OS-9 starts after a system reset, it searches the entire
memory space for ROMed modules. It detects them by looking for the
module header sync code ($87,$CD) which are unused 6809 opcodes. When
this byte pattern is detected, the header check is performed to
verify a correct header. If this test succeeds, the module size is
obtained from the header and a 24-bit CRC is performed over the
entire module. If the CRC matches correctly, the module is considered
valid, and it is entered into the module directory. The chances of
detecting a <quote>false module</quote> are virtually nil.</para>

<para>In this manner all ROMed modules present in the system at startup
are automatically included in the system module directory. Some of
the modules found initially are various parts of OS-9: file managers,
device driver, the configuration module, etc.</para>

<para>After the module search OS-9 links to whichever of its component
modules that it found. This is the secret of OS-9's extraordinary
adaptability to almost any 6809 computer; it automatically locates
its required and optional component modules, wherever they are, and
rebuilds the system each time that it is started.</para>

<para>ROMs containing non-system modules are also searched so any
user-supplied software is located during the start-up process and
entered into the module directory.</para>
</sect1>

<sect1>

<title>Memory Module Examples</title>
<para>
The following examples show the structure of two OS-9 memory modules.
The first is a typical terminal descriptor, and the second is a data
module that is used to share data between processes.
</para>
<example>
<title>Terminal Device Descriptor</title>
<programlisting>
 nam TERM
 ttl Device Descriptor for terminal

 use defsfile

**************************
*  TERMINAL device module

 mod TrmEnd,TrmNam,DEVIC+OBJCT,REENT+1,TrmMgr,TrmDrv
 fcb UPDAT. mode
 fcb $F port bank
 fdb A.TERM port address
 fcb TrmNam-*-1 option byte count
 fcb DT.SCF Device Type: SCF

* DEFAULT PARAMETERS

 fcb 0 case=UPPER and lower
 fcb 1 backspace=BS,SP,BS
 fcb O delete=backspace over line
 fcb 1 auto echo on
 fcb 1 auto line feed on
 fcb 0 null count
 fcb 1 end of page pause on
 fcb 24 lines per page
 fcb C$BSP backspace char
 fcb C$DEL delete line char
 fcb C$CR end of record char
 fcb C$EOF end of file char
 fcb C$RPRT reprint line char
 fcb C$RPET dup last line char
 fcb C$PAUS pause char
 fcb C$INTR Keyboard Interrupt char
 fcb $11 Keyboard Quit char
 fcb C$BSP backspace echo char
 fcb C$BELL line overflow char
 fcb A.T.init ACIA initialization
 fcb 0 reserved
 fdb TrmNam offset of echo device   (continued)
 fcb 0 Transmit Enable char
 fcb 0 Transmit Disable char
TrmNam fcs "TERM" device name
TrmMgr fcs "SCF" file manager
TrmDrv fcs "ACIA" device driver

 emod Module CRC

TrmEnd EQU *
</programlisting>
</example>

<example>
<title>Data Module</title>
<programlisting>
          nam  DataMod
          use  defsfile
LEVEL     equ  1 select level 1
          ifp1
          endc
TYPE      set  DATA      load value of $40
REVS      set  REENT+1   load value of $81
          mod  DataMEnd,DataMNam,TYPE,REVS,DataMEnt,0
DataMNam  fcs  "DataMod"
          fcb  0
DataMEnt  fcs  /12345678901234567890/
          fcs  /23456789012345678901/
          fcs  /34567890123456789012/
          fcs  /45678901234567890123/
          emod
DataMEnd  equ  *
</programlisting>
</example>

</sect1>
</chapter>
