<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
<title>Basic System Organization</title>

<para>OS-9 is composed of a group of modules, each of which provides
specific functions. When OS-9 is configured for a specific system
various modules are selected to provide a given level of
functionality. For example, a small control computer without a disk
does not need the disk-related OS-9 modules. Most examples in this
manual describe a fully-configured OS-9 system.</para>

<figure>
<title>OS-9 Component Module Organization</title>
<screen>
                 +-----------------------+
+----------+     !                       !     +----------+
!          !     !                       !     !          !
!   INIT   ! - - !     OS-9 KERNEL       ! - - !  Clock   !
!          !     !        (ROM)          !     !          !
+----------+     !                       !     +----------+
                 +-----------------------+
                             !
                             !
                 +-----------------------+
                 !                       !
                 ! Input/Output Manager  !
                 !       (IOMAN)         !
                 !                       !
                 +-----------------------+
                    !                 !
                    !                 !
   +--------------------+       +--------------------+
   !                    !       !                    !
   ! Disk File Manager  !       ! Char. File Manager !    More
   !      (RBFMAN)      !       !      (SCFMAN)      ! -&gt; opt.
   !                    !       !                    !
   +--------------------+       +--------------------+
        !          !                !           !
        !          !                !           !
   +--------+  +--------+       +--------+  +--------+
   !        !  !        !       !        !  !        !
   !  Disk  !  !  Disk  !       !  ACIA  !  !  PIA   !    More
   ! Driver !  ! Driver !       ! Driver !  ! Driver ! -&gt; opt.
   !        !  !        !       !        !  !        !
   +--------+  +--------+       +--------+  +--------+
     !     !     !     !          !     !     !     !
     !     !     !     !          !     !     !     !
   +---+ +---+  +---+ +---+     +---+ +---+  +---+ +---+
   !D0 ! !D1 !  !D2 ! !D3 !     !T1 ! !T2 !  !P1 ! !P2 !-&gt; More
   +---+ +---+  +---+ +---+     +---+ +---+  +---+ +---+   opt.
    RBF Device Descriptors        SCF Device Descriptors
</screen>
</figure>


<para>Notice that the diagram on the previous page indicates a
multilevel organization.</para>

<para>The first level is the KERNEL and the CLOCK MODULE. The kernel
provide basic system services such as multitasking, memory
management, and links all other system modules. The CLOCK module is a
software handler for the specific real-time-clock hardware. INIT is
an initialization table used by the kernel during system startup. It
specifies initial table sizes, initial system device names, etc.</para>

<para>The second level is the Input/Output Manager. It provides common
processing all I/O operations. It is required if any OS-supported I/O
is to be performed.</para>

<para>The third level is the File Manager level. File managers perform
I/O request processing for similar classes of I/O devices. The Random
Block File Manager (RBFMAN) processes all disk-type device
functions, and the Sequential Character File Manager (SCFMAN) handles
all non-mass storage devices that basically operate a character at a
time, such as terminals and printers. The user can add additional
File Managers to handle classes of devices not covered by SCFMAN or
RBFMAN.</para>

<para>The fourth level is the Device Driver Level. Device drivers handle
basic physical I/O functions for specific I/O controller hardware.
Standard OS-9 systems are typically supplied with a disk driver, a
ACIA driver for terminals and serial printers, and a PIA driver for
parallel printers. Many users add customized drivers of their own
design or purchased from a hardware vendor.</para>

<para>The fifth level is the Device Descriptor Level. These modules are
small tables that are associate specific I/O ports with their logical
names, and the port's device driver and file manager. They also
contain the physical address of the port and initialization data. By
use of device descriptors, only one copy of each driver is required
for each specific type of I/O controller regardless of how many
controllers the system uses.</para>

<para>One important component not shown is the <application>shell</application>, which is the
command interpreter. It is technically a program and not part of the
operating system itself, and is described fully in the
<citetitle pubwork="book">OS-9 Users Manual</citetitle>.</para>

<para>Even though all modules can be resident in ROM, generally only the
KERNEL and INIT modules are ROMed in disk-based systems. All other
modules are loaded into RAM during system startup by a disk bootstrap
module (not shown on diagram) which is also resident in ROM.</para>
</chapter>
