<?xml version="1.0"?>
<appendix xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>GLOSSARY</title>
  <section>
    <title>INTRODUCTION</title>
    <para>
The terms in this Chapter are defined in accordance with their meaning as
used in this document describing CIS COBOL and may not have the same meaning
for other languages.
</para>
    <para>
These definitions are also intended to be either reference material or
introductory material to be reviewed prior to reading the detailed language
specifications that are contained in this manual. For this reason, these
definitions are, in most instances, brief and do not include detailed
syntactical rules.
</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>DEFINITIONS</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Access Mode.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The manner in which records are to be operated upon within a file
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Actual Decimal Point.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The physical representation, using either of the
           decimal point characters . (period) or , (comma) of the decimal
           point position in a data item.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Alphabet-Name.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A user-defined word in the SPECIAL-NAMES paragraph of the
           Environment Division that assigns a name to a specific character
           set and/or collating sequence.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Alphabetic Character.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A character that belongs to the following set. of
           letters: A,B,C,D,E,F,G,H,I,J,K,L,M,N,O,P,Q,R,S,T,U,V,W,X,Y,Z and
           the space. <phrase role="extension">Also a,b,c,d,e,f,g,h,i,j,k,l,m,n,o,p,q,r,s,t,u,v,x,y and z
           which are converted to their upper case equivalents.</phrase>
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Alphanumeric Character.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Any character in the computer's character set.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Arithmetic Expression.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>An arithmetic expression can be an identifier or a
           numeric elementary item, a numeric literal, such identifiers and
           literals separated by arithmetic operators, two arithmetic
           expressions separated by an arithmetic operator, or an arithmetic
           expression enclosed in parentheses.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Arithmetic Operator.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A single character, or a fixed two-character combination, that belongs to the following set:
          </para>
          <informaltable frame="none" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
            <tgroup cols="2">
              <thead>
                <row>
                  <entry>Character</entry>
                  <entry>Meaning</entry>
                </row>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>+</entry>
                  <entry>Addition</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>-</entry>
                  <entry>Subtraction</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>*</entry>
                  <entry>Multiplication</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>/</entry>
                  <entry>Division</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </informaltable>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Ascending Key.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A key upon the values of which data is ordered starting with
           the lowest value of key up to the highest value of key in
           accordance with the rules for comparison of the data items.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Assumed Decimal Point.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A decimal point position which does not involve the
           existence of an actual character in a data item. The assumed
           decimal point has logical meaning but no physical representation.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>At End Condition.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A condition caused in one of two circumstances:
          </para>
          <orderedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem>
              <para>
During the execution of a READ statement for a sequentially accessed file.
          </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
During the execution of a RETURN statement when no next logical record exists for the associated sort or merge file.
          </para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Called Program.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A program which is the object of a CALL statement combined
           at run time with the calling program to produce a run unit.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Calling Program.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A program which executes a CALL to another program.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Character.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The basic indivisible unit of the language.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Character Set (CIS COBOL).</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The complete CIS COBOL character set consists
           of all characters listed below:
          </para>
          <informaltable frame="none" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
            <tgroup cols="2">
              <thead>
                <row>
                  <entry>Character</entry>
                  <entry>Meaning</entry>
                </row>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>0,1, ... ,9</entry>
                  <entry>Numeric digit</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>A,B ... ,Z</entry>
                  <entry>Uppercase alphabetic</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>
                    <phrase role="extension">a,b ... ,z</phrase>
                  </entry>
                  <entry>
                    <phrase role="extension">Lowercase alphabetic</phrase>
                  </entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry/>
                  <entry>Space (Blank)</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>+</entry>
                  <entry>Plus Sign</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>-</entry>
                  <entry>Minus Sign</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>*</entry>
                  <entry>Asterisk</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>/</entry>
                  <entry>Stroke (Virgule or Slash)</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>=</entry>
                  <entry>Equal Sign</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>$</entry>
                  <entry>Currency Sign</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>,</entry>
                  <entry>Comma</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>;</entry>
                  <entry>Semicolon</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>.</entry>
                  <entry>Period (Decimal Point, Fullstop)</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>'</entry>
                  <entry>Quotation Mark</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>(</entry>
                  <entry>Left Parenthesis</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>)</entry>
                  <entry>Right Parenthesis</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>&gt;</entry>
                  <entry>Greater Than Symbol</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>&lt;</entry>
                  <entry>Less Than Symbol</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </informaltable>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Character Position.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A character position is the amount of physical storage
           required to store a single standard data format character
           described as usage in DISPLAY. Further characteristics of the
           physical storage are defined by the implementor.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Character-String.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A sequence of contiguous characters which form a
           CIS COBOL word, a literal, a PICTURE character-string or a
           comment-entry.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Class Condition.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The proposition, for which a truth value can be determined,
           that the content of an item is wholly alphabetic or is wholly numeric.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Clause.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
A clause is an ordered set of consecutive CIS COBOL character-strings
whose purpose is to specify an attribute of an entry.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Collating Sequence.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The sequence in which the characters that are
          acceptable in a computer are ordered for purposes of sorting,
          merging and or comparing.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Column.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
          A character position within a print line. The columns are
          numbered from one, by one, starting at the left-most character
           position of the print line and extending to the right-most
          character position of the print line.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Comment Entry.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>An entry in the Identification Division that may be any
          combination of characters from the computer character set.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Comment Line.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A source program line represented by an asterisk in the
           indicator area of the line and any characters from the computer's
           character set in area A and area B of that line. The comment line
           serves only for documentation in a program. A special form of
           comment line represented by a stroke (/) in the indicator area of
           the line and any characters from the computer's character set in
           area A and area B of that line causes page ejection before
           printing the comment.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Compile Time.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The time at which an CIS COBOL source program is translated
           by the compiler to an CIS COBOL intermediate code program.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Compiler-Directing Statement.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A statement, beginning with a
           compiler-directing verb, that causes the compiler to take a
           specific action during compilation.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Computer-Name.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A system-name that identifies the computer upon which the
           program is to be compiled or run.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Condition.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A status of a program at execution time for which a truth value
can be determined. Where the term <quote>condition</quote> (condition-1,
condition-2,) appears in these language specifications in or in
reference to <quote>condition</quote> (condition-1, condition-2, ...) of a
general format, it is a conditional expression consisting of
either a simple condition optionally parenthesised, or a negated
simple condition.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Condition-Name.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The user-defined word assigned to a   status of an
           implementor-defined switch or device.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Conditional Expression.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A simple condition specified in an IF, or PERFORM.
           (See Simple Condition and Complex Condition.)
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Conditional Statement.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A conditional statement specifies that the truth
           value of a condition is to be determined, and that the subsequent
           action of the run-time program is dependent on this truth value.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Configuration Section.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A section of the Environment Division that describes
           overall specifications of source and run computers.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Connective.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A reserved word that is used to:
          </para>
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
Associate a data-name, paragraph-name, condition-name, or text-name with its qualifier.
          </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
Link two or more operands written in a series.
          </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
Form conditions (logical connectives). (See Logical Operator.)
</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Contiguous Items.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
Items that are described by consecutive entries in
the Data Division, and that bear a definite hierarchic
relationship to one another.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Counter.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>    A data item used for storing numbers or number representations in
              a manner that permits these numbers to be increased or decreased
              by the value of another number, or to be changed or reset to zero
              or to an arbitrary positive or negative value.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>CRT.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <phrase role="extension">An interactive input/output device comprising a cathode ray tube
              and a keyboard by which an Operator can enter and receive visual
              data.</phrase>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Currency Sign.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The character <quote>$</quote> (dollar sign) in the CIS COBOL character set.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Currency Symbol.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The character defined by the CURRENCY SIGN clause in the
              SPECIAL- NAMES paragraph. If no CURRENCY SIGN clause is present in
              a CIS COBOL source program, the currency symbol is identical to
              the currency sign.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Current Record.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The record which is available in the record area associated with the file.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Current Record Pointer.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A conceptual entity that is used in the selection of the next record.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Cursor.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <phrase role="extension">The indicator on a CRT screen that marks the line and character
position which the input/output control is currently referencing.</phrase>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Data Clause.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A clause that appears in a data description entry in the Data
              Division and provides information describing a particular
              attribute of a data item.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Data Description Entry .</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>An entry in the Data Division that is composed of a
              level-number followed by a data-name, if required, and then
              followed by a set of data clauses as required.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Data Dictionary.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A dictionary file of user def in ed names constructed by the
              Compiler containing the number of bytes for each entry.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Data Item.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A character or set of contiguous characters (excluding in either
              case literals) defined as a unit of data by the CIS COBOL program.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Data-name.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A user-defined word that names a data item described in a data
              description entry in the Data Division. When used in the general
              formats , <quote>data-name</quote> represents a word which can neither be
              subscripted, nor indexed unless specifically permitted by the
              rules for that format.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Debugging Line.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A debugging line is any line with <quote>D</quote> in the indicator area of the line.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Declaratives.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A set of one or more special purpose sections written at the
           beginning of the Procedure Division, the first of which is
           preceded by the key word DECLARATIVES and the last of which is
           followed by the key words END DECLARATIVES. A declarative is
           composed of a section header, followed by a USE compiler directing
           sequence, followed by a set of associated paragraphs (0 or more).
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Declarative-Sentence.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A compiler-directing sentence consisting of a single
           USE statement terminated by the separator period (.).
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Default Disk.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <phrase role="extension">The disk from which the compiler or run-time system is loaded
          and from which, in the absence of a specific drive identifier, any
          copy file or called code will be loaded if required.</phrase>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Delimiter.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>    A character (or sequence of contiguous characters) that
           identifies the end of a string of characters, and separates that
           string of characters from the following string of characters. A
           delimiter is not part of the string of characters that it 
           delimits.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Descending Key.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A key upon the values of which data is ordered starting
           with the highest value of key down to the lowest value of key, in
           accordance with the rules for comparing data items.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Digit Position.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A digit position is the amount of physical storage
           required to store a single digit. This amount varies depending on
           the usage of the data item describing the digit position. Further
           characteristics of the physical storage are defined by the
           implementor.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Division.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>   A set of sections or paragraphs (0 or more) that are formed and
           combined in accordance with a specific set of rules is called a
           division body. There are four divisions in a CIS COBOL program:
           Identification, Environment, Data and Procedure.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Division Header.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A combination of words followed by a period and a space
           that indicate the beginning of a division. The division headers are:
           </para>
          <programlisting>
    IDENTIFICATION DIVISION.
    ENVIRONMENT DIVISION.
    DATA DIVISION.
    PROCEDURE DIVISION    USING data-name-1  data-name-2 ... .
</programlisting>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Dynamic Access.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>An access mode in which specific logical records can be
           obtained from or placed into a disk file in a non-sequential
           manner (see Random Access) and obtained from a file in a
           sequential manner (see Sequential Access) during the scope of the
           same OPEN statement.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Editing Character.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A single character or a fixed two character combination
           belonging to the same set:
           </para>
          <informaltable frame="none" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
            <tgroup cols="2">
              <thead>
                <row>
                  <entry>Character</entry>
                  <entry>Meaning</entry>
                </row>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>B</entry>
                  <entry>Space</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>0</entry>
                  <entry>Zero</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>+</entry>
                  <entry>Plus</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>-</entry>
                  <entry>Minus</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>CR</entry>
                  <entry>Credit</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>DB</entry>
                  <entry>Debit</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>Z</entry>
                  <entry>Zero Suppress</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>*</entry>
                  <entry>Check Protect</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>$</entry>
                  <entry>Currency Sign</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>,</entry>
                  <entry>Comma</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>.</entry>
                  <entry>Period (Decimal Point)</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>/</entry>
                  <entry>Stroke (Virgule, Slash)</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </informaltable>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Elementary Item.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A data item         that is described as not being further
                   logically subdivided.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>End of Procedure Division.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The physical position in a CIS COBOL source
program after which no further procedures appear.
Any descriptive set of consecutive clauses terminated by a
period (.) and written in the Identification Division, Environment
Division or Data Division of an CIS COBOL source program.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Environment Clause.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A clause that appears as part of an Environment Division entry.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Extend Mode.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>    With the EXTEND phrase specified, the state of a file after
                   execution of an OPEN statement, and before the execution of a
                   CLOSE statement for the file.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Figurative Constant.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A compiler-generated value referenced through the use
                   of certain reserved words.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>File.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A collection of records.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>File Clause.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A clause that appears as part of any of the following Data
                   Division entries:
                          File Description (FD)
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>FILE-CONTROL.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The name of an Environment Division paragraph in which the
                   data files for a given source program are declared.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>File Description Entry.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>An entry in the File Section of the Data Division
                   that is composed of the level indicator FD, followed by a
                   file-name, and then followed by a set of file clauses as required.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>File-Name.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A user-defined word that names a file described in a file
                   description entry or a sort-merge file description entry within
                   the File Section of the Data Division.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>File Organization.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The permanent logical file structure established at the
          time that a file is created.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>File Section.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>   The section of the Data Division that contains file
          description entries together with their associated record
          descriptions.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Format.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A specific arrangement of a set of data.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>FORMS Program.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <phrase role="extension">A screen formatting program that automatically generates CIS COBOL
          CRT input/output coding from actual screen layout.</phrase>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Group Item.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>  A named contiguous set of elementary or group items.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>High Order End.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>  The leftmost character of a string of characters.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>I-O-CONTROL.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>   The name of an Environment Division paragraph in which object
          program requirements for specific input/output techniques, rerun
          points, sharing of same areas by several data files, and multiple
          file storage on a single input/output device are specified.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>I-O Mode.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The state of a file after execution of an OPEN statement, with the
          I-O phrase specified for that file, and before the execution of a
          CLOSE statement for that file.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Identifier.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>   A data-name, followed as required by the syntactically
          correct combination of subscripts and indices necessary to make
          unique reference to a data item.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Imperative Statement.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A statement that begins with an imperative verb and
          specifies an unconditional action to be taken. An imperative
          statement may consist of a sequence of imperative statements.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Implementor-Name.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A system-name that refers to a particular feature avail-
          able on the implementors computing system.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Index.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>   A computer storage position or register, the contents of which
          represent the identification of a particular element in a table.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Index Data Item.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A data item in which the value associated with an
          index-name can be stored in a form specified by the implementor.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Indexed File.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>  A file with indexed organization.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Indexed Organization.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The permanent logical file structure in which each
          record is identified by the value of one or more keys within that
          record.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Indicator Area.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>   The leftmost parameter position of a CIS COBOL source
          record that indicates the use of the record.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Input File.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>     A file that is opened in the input mode.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Input Mode.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The state of a file after execution of an OPEN statement, with
              the INPUT phrase specified, for that file and before the execution
              of a CLOSE statement for that file.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Input-Output File.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A file that is opened in the I-O mode.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Input-Output Section.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>     The section of the Environment Division that names
              the files and the external media used by a program and which
              provides information required for transmission and handling of
              data during execution of the run-time program.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Integer.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>     A   numeric literal or a numeric data item that does not
              include any character positions to the right of the assumed
              decimal point. Where the term 'integer' appears in general
              formats, integer must not be a numeric data item, and must not be
              signed, nor zero unless explicitly allowed by the rules of that format.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Intermediate Code</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <phrase role="extension">The code produced by the CIS COBOL compiler from the source code entered,
        and which the Run Time System 'fast loads' for execution.</phrase>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Invalid Key Condition.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A condition, at object time, caused when a specified
              value of the key associated with an indexed or relative file is
              determined to be invalid.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Issue Disk.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
The flexible diskette or which the CIS COBOL software is supplied to users.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Key.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A data item which identifies the location of a record, or a set of
              data items which serve to identify the ordering of data.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Key of Reference.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>        The key currently being used to access records within an indexed file.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Key Word.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A reserved word whose presence is required when the format in
              which the word appears is used in a source program.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Level-Number.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A user-defined word which indicates the position of a data
              item in the hierarchical structure of a logical record or which
              indicates special properties of a data description entry. A
              level-number is expressed as a  one or two digit number.
              Level-numbers in the range 1 through 49 indicate the position of a
              data item in the hierarchical structure of a logical record.
              Level-numbers in the range 1 through 9 may be written either as a
              single digit or as a zero followed by a significant digit.
              Level-number 77 identifies special properties of a data
              description entry.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Library-Name.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A user-defined word that names a CIS COBOL library
  source file that is to be used by the compiler for a given source program compilation.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Library-Text.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>        A sequence of character-strings and/or separators in a COBOL library.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Line Sequential File Organization</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <phrase role="extension">A sequential file containing variable length records separated
by the C/R (carriage return) and L/F (line feed) characters.</phrase>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Linkage Section.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The section in the Data Division of the called program
            that describes data items available from the calling program.
            These data items may be referred to by both the calling and called program.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Literal.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>   A character-string whose value is implied by the ordered set of
            characters comprising the string.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Logical Operator.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The reserved word 'NOT'. It can be used for logical negation.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Logical Record.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The most inclusive data item. The level-number for a record is 01.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Low Order End.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The rightmost character of a string of characters.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Mnemonic-Name.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A User-defined word that is associated in the Environment
            Division with a specified implementor-name.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Native Character Set.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The implementor-defined character set associated with
            the computer specified in the OBJECT-COMPUTER paragraph.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Native Collating Sequence.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The implementor-defined collating sequence
            associated with the computer specified in the OBJECT-COMPUTER paragraph.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Negated Simple Condition.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The 'NOT' logical operator immediately followed
            by a simple condition.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Next Executable Sentence.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The next sentence to which control will be
            transferred after execution of the current statement is complete.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Next Executable Statement.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The next statement to which control will be
             transferred after execution of the current statement is complete.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Next  Record.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The record which logically follows the current record of a file.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Non contiguous Items.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>          Elementary data items, in the Working-Storage and
            Linkage Sections, which bear no hierarchic relationship to other data items.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Nonnumeric Item.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A data item whose description permits its contents to be
             composed of any combination of characters taken from the
             computer's character set. Certain categories of nonnumeric items
             may be formed from more restricted character sets.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Nonnumeric Literal.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>   A character-string bounded by quotation marks. The
string of characters may include any character in the
computer's character set. To represent a single quotation mark
character within a nonnumeric literal, two contiguous quotation
marks must be used.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Numeric Character.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A character that belongs to the following set of digits:
           0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Numeric Item.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>   A data item whose description restricts its contents to a
value represented by characters chosen from the digits '0' through
'9'; if signed, the item may also contain a '+', '-' or other
representation of an operational sign.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Numeric Literal.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A literal composed of one or more numeric characters that
also may contain either a decimal point, or an algebraic sign, or
both. The decimal point must not be the rightmost character. The
algebraic sign, if present, Must be the leftmost character.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>OBJECT-COMPUTER.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The name of an Environment Division paragraph in which the
           computer environment, within which the run-time program is
           executed, is described.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Open Mode.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The state of a file after execution of an OPEN statement for that
           file and before the execution of a CLOSE statement for that file.
          The particular open mode is specified in the OPEN statement as
          either INPUT, OUTPUT, I-O or EXTEND.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Operand.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>  Whereas the general definition of operand is 'that component which
           is operated upon', for the purposes of this publication, any
           lowercase word (or words) that appears in a statement or entry
           format may be considered to be an operand and, as such, is an
           implied reference to the data indicated by the operand.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Operational Sign.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>An algebraic sign, associated with a numeric data item or
           a numeric literal, to indicate whether its value is positive or negative.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Optional Word.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A reserved word that is included in a specified format only
           to improve the readability of the language and whose presence is
           optional to the user when the format in which the word appears is
           used in a source program.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Output File.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>   A file that is opened in either the output mode or extend mode.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Output-Mode.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>  The state of a file after execution of an OPEN statement, with
           the OUTPUT or EXTEND phrase specified for that file and before the
           execution of a CLOSE statement for that file.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Paragraph.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>In the Procedure Division, a paragraph-name followed by a period
           and a space and optionally by one, or more sentences. In the
           Identification and Environment Divisions, a paragraph header
           followed by zero, one, or more entries.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Paragraph Header.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A reserved word, followed by a period and a space that
           indicates the beginning of a paragraph in the Identification and
           Environment Divisions. The permissible paragraph headers are:
           </para>
          <para>
     In the Identification Division:
     </para>
          <programlisting>
     PROGRAM-ID.
     AUTHOR.
     INSTALLATION.
     DATE-WRITTEN.
     DATE-COMPILED.
     SECURITY.
     </programlisting>
          <para>
     In the Environment Division:
     </para>
          <programlisting>
     SOURCE-COMPUTER.
     OBJECT-COMPUTER.
     SPECIAL-NAMES.
     FILE-CONTROL.
     I-O-CONTROL.
     </programlisting>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Paragraph-Name.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>  A user-defined word that identifies and begins a paragraph
           in the Procedure Division.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Phrase.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>   A phrase is an ordered set of one or more consecutive COBOL
           character-strings that form a portion of a CIS COBOL procedural
           statement or of a COBOL clause.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Prime Record Key.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A key whose contents uniquely identify a record within an
           indexed file.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Procedure.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>  A paragraph or group of logically successive paragraphs, or a
           section or group of logically successive sections, within the
           Procedure Division.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Procedure-Name.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A user-defined word which is used to name a paragraph or
           section in the Procedure Division. It consists of a paragraph-name or a section-name.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Punctuation Character.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A character that belongs to the following set:
          </para>
          <informaltable frame="none" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
            <tgroup cols="2">
              <thead>
                <row>
                  <entry>Character</entry>
                  <entry>Meaning</entry>
                </row>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>,</entry>
                  <entry>comma</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>;</entry>
                  <entry>semicolon</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>.</entry>
                  <entry>period</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>"</entry>
                  <entry>quotation mark</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>(</entry>
                  <entry>left parenthesis</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>)</entry>
                  <entry>right parenthesis</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry> </entry>
                  <entry>space</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>=</entry>
                  <entry>equal sign</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </informaltable>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Random Access.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>An access mode in which the program-specified value of a key
             data item identifies the logical record that is obtained from,
             deleted from or placed into a relative or indexed file.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Record.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
             (see Logical Record)
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Record Area.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A storage area allocated for the purpose of processing the
             record described in a record description entry in the File
             Section.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Record Description.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>(See Record Description Entry)
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Record Description Entry.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The total set of data description entries
             associated with a particular record.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Record Key.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A key, either the prime record key or an alternate record key,
             whose contents identify a record within an indexed file.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Record-Name.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A user-defined word that names a record described in a record
             description entry in the Data Division.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Reference-Format.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A format that provides a standard method for describing
             COBOL source programs.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Relation.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>(See Relational Operator)
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Relation Character.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>  A character that belongs to the following set:</para>
          <informaltable frame="none" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
            <tgroup cols="2">
              <thead>
                <row>
                  <entry>Character</entry>
                  <entry>Meaning</entry>
                </row>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>&gt;</entry>
                  <entry>greater than</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>&lt;</entry>
                  <entry>less than</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>=</entry>
                  <entry>equal to</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </informaltable>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Relation Condition.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The proposition, for which a truth value can be
             determined, that the value of an arithmetic expression or data
             item has a specified relationship to the value of another
             arithmetic expression or data item. (See Relational Operator),
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Relational Operator.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A reserved word, a relation character, a group of
          consecutive reserved words, or a group of consecutive reserved
          words and relation characters used in the construction of a
          relation condition. The permissible operators and their meaning are:
          </para>
          <informaltable frame="none" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
            <tgroup cols="2">
              <thead>
                <row>
                  <entry>Relational Operator</entry>
                  <entry>Meaning</entry>
                </row>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>IS NOT GREATER THAN</entry>
                  <entry morerows="1">Greater than or not greater than</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>IS NOT &gt;</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>IS NOT LESS THAN</entry>
                  <entry morerows="1">Less than or not less than</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>IS NOT &lt;</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>IS NOT EQUAL THAN</entry>
                  <entry morerows="1">Equal to or not equal to</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>IS NOT =</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </informaltable>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Relative File.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>  A file with relative organization.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Relative Key.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A key whose contents identify a logical record in a relative
          file.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Relative Organization.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The permanent logical file structure in which each
          record is uniquely identified by an integer value greater than
          zero, which specifies the record's logical ordinal position in the
          file.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Reserved Word.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A COBOL word specified in the list of words which may be
          used in COBOL source programs, but which must not appear in the
          programs as user-defined words or system-names.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Routine-Name.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A user-defined word that identifies a procedure written in a
          language other than COBOL:
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Run Time Debug.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <phrase role="extension">An option available to CIS COBOL programmers entered as a
            user option enabling break-point facilities in run time programs.
          </phrase>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Run Time.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <phrase role="extension">The time at which the intermediate code produced by the compiler
            is interpreted by the Run Time System for execution.
          </phrase>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Run Time System-(RTS).</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <phrase role="extension">The software that interprets the intermediate code
            produced by the CIS COBOL compiler and enables it to be executed by providing
            interfaces to the operating system and CRT.
          </phrase>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Run Unit.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A set of one or more intermediate code programs which function, at
          run time, as a unit to provide problem solutions.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Section.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
          A set of none, one, or more paragraphs or entries, called a
          section body, the first of which is preceded by a section header.
          Each section consists of the section header and the related
          section body.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Section Header.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A combination of words followed by a period and a space that
                indicates the beginning of a section in the Environment, Data and
                Procedure Division.
                </para>
          <para>
  In the Environment and Data Divisions, a section header is composed of
  reserved words followed by a period and a space. The permissible section
  headers are:
  </para>
          <para>
        In the Environment Division:
  </para>
          <screen>
        CONFIGURATION SECTION
        INPUT-OUTPUT SECTION
</screen>
          <para>
        In the Data Division:
  </para>
          <screen>
        FILE SECTION
        WORKING-STORAGE SECTION
        LINKAGE SECTION
</screen>
          <para>
In the Procedure Division, a section header is composed of a section-name,
followed by the reserved word SECTION, followed by a segment-number
  (optional), followed by a period and a space.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Section-Name.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A user-defined word which names a section in the Procedure
                Division.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Segment-Number.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A user-defined word which classifies sections in the
                Procedure Division for purposes of segmentation. Segment-numbers
                may contain only the characters '0', '1', ... , '9'.   A
                segment-number may be expressed either as a one or two digit
                number, and is checked for syntax only.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Sentence.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A sequence of one or more statements, the last of which is
                terminated by a period followed by a space.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Separator.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A punctuation character used to delimit character-strings.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Sequential Access.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>An access mode in which logical records are obtained from
or placed into a file in a consecutive predecessor-to-successor
logical record sequence determined by the order of records in the file.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Sequential File.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A file with sequential organization.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Sequential Organization.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The permanent logical file structure in which a
record is identified by a predecessor-successor relationship
established when the record is placed into the file.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Sign Condition.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The proposition, for which a truth value can be determined,
 that the algebraic value of a data item or an arithmetic
 expression is either less than, greater than, or equal to zero.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Simple Condition.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>  Any single condition chosen from the set:
          </para>
          <simplelist>
            <member>relation condition</member>
            <member>class condition</member>
            <member>switch-status condition</member>
            <member>sign condition</member>
            <member>(simple-condition)</member>
          </simplelist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>SOURCE-COMPUTER.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>    The name of an Environment Division paragraph in which
          the computer environment, within which the source program is
          compiled, is described.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Source Program.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Although it is recognised that a source program may be
represented by other forms and symbols, in this document it always
refers to a syntactically correct set of COBOL statements
beginning with an Identification Division and ending with the end
of the Procedure Division. In contexts where there is no danger
of ambiguity, the word 'program' alone may be used in place of the
phrase 'source program'.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Special Character.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>   A character that belongs to the following set:
          </para>
          <informaltable frame="none" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
            <tgroup cols="2">
              <thead>
                <row>
                  <entry>Character</entry>
                  <entry>Meaning</entry>
                </row>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>+</entry>
                  <entry>Plus Sign</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>-</entry>
                  <entry>Minus Sign</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>*</entry>
                  <entry>Asterisk</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>/</entry>
                  <entry>Stroke (Virgule or Slash)</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>=</entry>
                  <entry>Equal Sign</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>$</entry>
                  <entry>Currency Sign</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>,</entry>
                  <entry>Comma</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>;</entry>
                  <entry>Semicolon</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>.</entry>
                  <entry>Period (Decimal Point, Fullstop)</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>'</entry>
                  <entry>Quotation Mark</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>(</entry>
                  <entry>Left Parenthesis</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>)</entry>
                  <entry>Right Parenthesis</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>&gt;</entry>
                  <entry>Greater Than Symbol</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>&lt;</entry>
                  <entry>Less Than Symbol</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </informaltable>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Special-Character Word.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A reserved word which is an arithmetic operator or
           a relation character.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>SPECIAL-NAMES.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The name of an Environment Division paragraph in which
           implementor-names are related to user specified mnemonic-names.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Special Registers.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Compiler generated storage areas whose primary use is to
           store information produced in conjunction with the user of
           specified COBOL features.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Standard Data Format.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The concept used in describing the characteristics of
data in a COBOL Data Division under which the characteristics or
properties of the data are expressed in a form oriented to the
appearance of the data on a printed page of infinite length and
breadth, rather than a form oriented to the manner in which the
data is stored internally in the computer, or on a particular
external medium.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Statement.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A syntactically valid combination of words and symbols written in
  the Procedure Division beginning with a verb.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Subprogram.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>   (See Called Program).
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Subscript.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>  An integer whose value identifies a particular element in a table.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Subscripted Data-Name.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>An identifier that is composed of a data-name
              followed by one or more subscripts enclosed in parenthesis.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Switch-Status Condition.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The proposition, for which a truth value can be
              determined, that an implementor-defined switch, capable of being
              set to an 'on' or 'off' status, has been set to a specified status.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Symbol Function.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The use of specified characters in the PICTURE clause to
              represent data types.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>System-Name.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A COBOL word which is used to communicate with the operating
              environment.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Syntax.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>   The order in which elements must be put together to form a program.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Table.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
              A set of logically consecutive items of data that are defined in
              the Data Division by means of the OCCURS clause.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Table Element.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A data item that belongs to the set of repeated items comprising a table.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Text-Name.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>    A user-defined word which identifies library text.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Text-Word.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>  Any character-string or separator, except space, in a COBOL
              library or in pseudo-text.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Unary Operator.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A plus (+) or a minus (-) sign, which precedes a variable
              or a left parenthesis in an arithmetic expression and which has
              the effect of multiplying the expression of +1 or -1 respectively.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>User-Defined Word.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A COBOL word that must be supplied by the user to
              satisfy the format of a clause or statement.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Variable.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A data item whose value may be changed by execution of the object
              program. A variable used in an arithmetic expression must be a
              numeric elementary item.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Verb.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A word that expresses an action to be taken by a COBOL compiler or
          run time program.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Word.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A character-string of not more than 30 characters which forms a
          user-defined word, a system-name, or a reserved word.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Working-Storage Section.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>The section of the Data Division that describes
          working storage data items, composed either of noncontiguous items
          or of working storage records or of both.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>77 Level-Description-Entry.</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A data description entry  that describes  a
noncontiguous data item with the level-number 77.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>
</appendix>
