<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
<!ENTITY ansileft "-[">
<!ENTITY ansiright "]-">
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>COBOL Concepts</title>
  <section>
    <title>LANGUAGE CONCEPTS</title>
    <section>
      <title>CHARACTER SET</title>
      <para>
The most basic and indivisible unit of the language is the character.
The set of characters used to form CIS COBOL character-strings and
separators includes the letters of the alphabet, digits and special
characters. The character set consists of the characters defined below:
</para>
      <informaltable frame="none" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colwidth="0.6in" colname="c1"/>
          <colspec colwidth="3.8in" colname="c2"/>
          <spanspec spanname="all" namest="c1" nameend="c2"/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry spanname="all">0 to 9</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry spanname="all">A to Z</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry spanname="all">
                <phrase role="extension">a to z (Reserved and User-defined Word Characters read as: A to Z)</phrase>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry spanname="all">Space</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>+</entry>
              <entry>Plus sign</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>-</entry>
              <entry>Minus sign or hyphen</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>*</entry>
              <entry>Asterisk</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>/</entry>
              <entry>Oblique Stroke/Slash</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>=</entry>
              <entry>Equal sign</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>$</entry>
              <entry>Dollar sign</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>.</entry>
              <entry>Full stop or decimal point</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>,</entry>
              <entry>Comma or decimal point</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>;</entry>
              <entry>Semicolon</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>"</entry>
              <entry>Quotation mark</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>(</entry>
              <entry>Left Parenthesis</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>)</entry>
              <entry>Right Parenthesis</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>&gt;</entry>
              <entry>Greater than symbol</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>&lt;</entry>
              <entry>Less than symbol</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
      <para>
The CIS COBOL language is restricted to the above character set ,but
the content of non-numeric literals, comment lines and data may include any
of the characters from the ASCII character set. See Appendix B.
</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>LANGUAGE STRUCTURE</title>
      <para>
The individual characters of the language are concatenated to form
character-strings and separators. A separator may be concatenated with
another separator or with a character- string. A character-string may only
be conca t enated with a separator. The concatenation of character-strings
and separators forms the text of a source program.
</para>
      <section>
        <title>Separators</title>
        <para>
A separator is a string of one or more punctuation characters. The
rules for formation of separators are:
</para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The punctuation character space is a separator. Anywhere a space is
used as a separator, more than one space may be used.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The punctuation characters comma,  semicolon and period,  when
immediately followed by a space, are separators. These separators
may appear in a COBOL source program only where explicitly permitted by
the general formats, by format punctuation rules (see
FORMATS AND RULES in Chapter 1), by statement and sentence structure
definitions (see STATEMENTS AND SENTENCES in this Chapter), or
reference format rules (see REFERENCE FORMAT in this Chapter).
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The punctuation characters right and left parenthesis are separators.
Parenthesis may appear only in balanced pairs of left and right
parentheses delimiting subscripts, indices, arithmetic expressions, or
conditions.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The punctuation character quotation mark is a separator. An opening
quotation mark must be immediately preceded by a space or left
parenthesis; a closing quotation mark must be immediately followed by
one of the separators space, comma, semicolon, period, or right
parenthesis.
       </para>
            <para>
Quotation marks may appear only in balanced pairs delimiting nonnumeric
literals except when the literal is continued.   (See
CONTINUATION OF LINES in this Chapter).
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The separator space may optionally immediately precede all separators except the following:
       </para>
            <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
              <listitem>
                <para>
As specified by reference format rules see REFERENCE FORMAT in this Chapter.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
The separator closing quotation mark. In this case, a preceding space is
considered as part of the nonnumeric literal and not as a separator.
</para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The separator space is optional and can immediately follow any
separator except the opening quotation mark. In this case, a following
space is considered as part of the nonnumeric literal and not as a separator.
</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>
Any punctuation character which appears as part of the specification of
a PICTURE character-string (see Chapter 3) or numeric literal is not
considered as a punctuation character, but rather as a symbol used in the
specification of that PICTURE character-string or numeric literal. PICTURE
character-strings are delimited only by the separators space, comma,
semicolon, or period.
</para>
        <para>
The rules established for the formation of separators do not apply to
the characters which comprise the contents of nonnumeric literals,
comment-entries, or comment lines.
</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Character-Strings</title>
        <para>
A character-string is a character or a sequence of contiguous
characters which forms a CIS COBOL word, a literal, a PICTURE
character-string, or a comment-entry. A character-string is delillited by
separators.
</para>
        <section>
          <title>COBOL Words</title>
          <para>
A COBOL word is a character-string of not more than 30 characters which
forms a user defined word, a system-name, or a reserved word. Within a
given source program these classes form disjoint sets; a COBOL word may
belong to one and only one of these classes.
</para>
          <para>
User-Defined Words:  A user-defined word is a COBOL word that must be
supplied by the user to satisfy the format of a clause or statement. Each
character of a user-defined word is selected from the set of characters 'A',
'B', 'C', ... 'Z', <phrase role="extension">'a', 'b', 'c', ... 'z'</phrase>, '0', ... '9', and '-', except that
the '-' may not appear as the first or last character. <phrase role="extension">The exception to
this rule is an external file-name-literal which must be a normal alphanumeric literal.</phrase>
</para>
          <para>
User-defined word types which are implemented are as follows:
</para>
          <simplelist>
            <member>alphabet-name</member>
            <member>condition-name</member>
            <member>data-name</member>
            <member>
              <phrase role="extension">external-file-name-literal</phrase>
            </member>
            <member>file-name</member>
            <member>index-name</member>
            <member>level-number</member>
            <member>mnemonic-name</member>
            <member>paragraph-name</member>
            <member>program-name</member>
            <member>record-name</member>
            <member>section-name</member>
            <member>segment-number</member>
            <member>text-name</member>
          </simplelist>
          <para>
Within a given source program, ten of these 12 types of user-defined
words are grouped into nine disjoint sets. The disjoint sets are:
</para>
          <simplelist>
            <member>alphabet-names</member>
            <member>condition-names, data-names, and record-names</member>
            <member>file-names</member>
            <member>index-names</member>
            <member>mnemonic-names</member>
            <member>paragraph-names</member>
            <member>program-names</member>
            <member>section-names</member>
            <member>text-names</member>
          </simplelist>
          <para>
All user-defined words, except segment-numbers and level-numbers, can
belong to one and only one of these disjoint sets. Further, all
user-defined words within a given disjoint set must be unique.
(See UNIQUENESS OF REFERENCE in this Section).
</para>
          <para>
With the exception of paragraph-name, section-name, level-number and
segment-number, all user-defined words mus t contain at least one alphabetic
character. Segment-numbers and level-numbers need not be unique; a given
specification of a segment-number or level-number may be ir!entical to any
other segment-number or level-number and may even be identical to a
paragraph-name or section-name.
</para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Condition-Name:</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>A condition-name is a name which is assigned to a
          specific value, set of values, or range of values,
          within a complete set of values that a data item may
          assume. The data item itself is called a conditional
          variable.
      </para>
                <para>
          Condition-names may be defined in the Data Division or
          in the SPECIAL-NAMES paragraph within the Environment
          Division where a condition-name must be assigned to the
          ON STATUS or OFF STATUS, or both, of the run time
          switches.
      </para>
                <para>
          A condition-name is used only in the RERUN clause or in
          conditions as an abbreviation for the relation
          condition; this relation condition posits that the
          associated conditional variable is equal to one of the
          set of values to which that condition-name is assigned.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Mnemonic-Name:</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>      A mnemonic-name assigns a user-defined word to an
          implementor-name. These associations are established in
          the SPECIAL-NAMES paragraph of the Environment Division.
          (See SPECIAL-NAMES in Chapter 3).</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Paragraph-Name:</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>     A paragraph-name is a word which names a paragraph in
          the Procedure Division. Paragraph-names are equivalent
          if, and only if, they are composed of the same sequence
          of the same number of digits and/or characters.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Section-Name:</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>       A section-name is a word which names a section in the
          Procedure Division. Section names are equivalent if, and
          only if, they are composed of the same sequence of the
          same number of digits and/or characters.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Other User-Defined Names:</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>See the glossary in Appendix C for definitions of all
          other types of user-defined words.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>System-Names:</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>A system-name is a COBOL word which is used to
         communicate with the operating environment. Each
          character used in the formation of a system-name must be
          selected from the set of characters 'A', 'B' , 'C', ...
          'Z', <phrase role="extension">'a','b', ... 'z',</phrase> '0' ... '9' and'-', except that
          the '- ' may not appear as the first or last character.
      </para>
                <para>
          There are three types of system-names:
      </para>
                <orderedlist spacing="compact">
                  <listitem>
                    <para>computer-name</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>implementor-name</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>language-name</para>
                  </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
                <para>
          Within a given implementation these three types of
        system-names form disjoint seta; a given system-name may
        belong to one and only one of them.
        The system-names listed above are individually defined
        in the glossary in Appendix C.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Reserved Words:</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>     A reserved word is a COBOL word that is one of a
        specified list of words which may be used in COBOL
        source programs, but which must not appear in the
        programs as user-defined words or system-names.
        Reserved words can only be used as specified in the
        general formats. (See Appendix A).
      </para>
                <para>
        There are six types of reserved words:
      </para>
                <orderedlist spacing="compact">
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Key words</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Optional words</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Connectives</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Special registers</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Figurative constants</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Special-character words</para>
                  </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Key Words:</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>A key word is a word whose presence is required when the
        format in which the word appears is used in a source
        program. Within each format, such words are uppercase
        and underlined.
      </para>
                <para>
        Key words are of three types:
      </para>
                <orderedlist spacing="compact">
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Verbs such as ADD, READ, and ENTER.</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Required words, which appear in statement and entry formats.</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Words which have a specific functional meaning such as NEGATIVE, SECTION, etc.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Optional Words:</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>Within each format, uppercase words that are not
        underlined are called optional words and may appear at
        the user's option. The presence or absence of an
        optional word does not alter the semantics of the COBOL
        program in which it appears.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Connectives:</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>Series connectives link two or more consecutive
        operands:  , (separator comma)  or ; (separator semicolon).</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Figurative Constants:</term>
              <listitem>
                <para> Certain reserved words are used to name and reference
specific constant values. These reserved words are
specified under Figurative Constant Values in this chapter.</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Literals</title>
          <para>
A literal is a character-string whose value is implied by an ordered
set of characters of which the literal is composed or by specification of a
reserved word which references a figurative constant. Every literal belongs
to one of two types, nonnumeric or numeric.
</para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Nonnumeric Literals</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
A nonnumeric literal is a character-string delimited on
both ends by quotation marks and consisting of any
allowable character in the computer's character set.
Allowed are nonnumeric literals of 1 through 128
characters in length. To represent a single quotation
mark character within a nonnumeric literal, two
contiguous quotation marks must be used. The value of a
nonnumeric literal in the object program is the string
of characters itself, except:
        </para>
                <orderedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>The delimiting quotation marks are excluded, and</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Each embedded pair of contiguous quotation marks represents a single quotation mark character.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
          <para>
All other punctuation characters are part of the value of the nonnumeric
literal rather than separators; all nonnumric literal are category alphanumeric.
(See The PICTURE Clause in chapter 3). <phrase role="extension">In addition, hexadecimal
binary values can be attributed to non-numeric literals by, expressing
literals as: X"nn", where n is a hexadecimal character in the set 0-9 A-F;
nn may be repeated up to 128 times, but the number of hex digits must be even.</phrase>
</para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Numeric Literals</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>A numeric literal is a character-string whose characters
are selected from the digits '0' through '9', the plus
sign, the minus sign, and/or the decimal point. The
implementation allows for numeric literals of 1 through
18 digits in length. The rules for the formation of
numeric literals are as follows:
</para>
                <orderedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>A literal must contain at least one digit.</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>A literal must not contain more than one sign
        character. If a sign is used, it must appear as
        the leftmost character of the literal. If the
        literal is unsigned, the literal is positive.</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>A literal must not contain more than one decimal
        point. The decimal point is treated as an assumed
        decimal point, and may appear anywhere within the
        literal except as the rightmost character. If the
        literal contains no decimal point, the literal is
        an integer.
        </para>
                    <para>
        If a literal conforms to the rules for the
        formation of numeric literals, but is enclosed in
        quotation marks, it is a nonnumeric literal and it
        is treated as such by the compiler.</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>The value of a numeric literal is the algebraic
        quality represented by the characters in the
        numeric literal. Every numeric literal is category
        numeric. (See THE PICTURE CLAUSE in Chapter 3).
        The size of a numeric literal in standard data
        format characters is equal to the number of digits
        specified by the user.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Figurative Constant Values</title>
          <para>
Figurative Constant Values are generated by the compiler and referenced
through the use of the reserved words given below. These words must not be
bounded by quotation marks when used as figurative constants. The singular
and plural forms of figurative constants are equivalent and may be used
interchangeably.
</para>
          <para>
The figurative constant values and the reserved words used to reference them
are shown in Table 2-1.
</para>
          <table frame="none" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
            <title>Figurative Constants and their Reserved Words</title>
            <tgroup cols="2">
              <colspec colwidth="2in" colname="c1"/>
              <colspec colwidth="3in" colname="c2"/>
              <thead>
                <row>
                  <entry>CONSTANT</entry>
                  <entry>REPRESENTATION</entry>
                </row>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>ZERO</entry>
                  <entry morerows="2">Represents the value '0', or one or more of the character '0' depending on context.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>ZEROS</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>ZEROES</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>SPACE</entry>
                  <entry morerows="1">Represents one or more of the character space from the computer's character set.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>SPACES</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>HIGH-VALUE</entry>
                  <entry morerows="1">Represents one or more of the character that has the highest ordinal position in the program collating sequence.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>HIGH-VALUES</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>LOW-VALUE</entry>
                  <entry morerows="1">Represents one or more of the character that has the lowest ordinal position in the program collating sequence.</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>LOW-VALUES</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>QUOTE</entry>
                  <entry morerows="1">Represents one or more of the character ' " '.
                                The word QUOTE or QUOTES cannot be used in
                                place of a quotation mark in a source program
                                to bound a nonnumeric literal. Thus, QUOTE
                                ABD QUOTE is incorrect as a way of stating
                                the nonnumeric literal "ABD".</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>QUOTES</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>ALL literal</entry>
                  <entry><phrase role="extension">Represents one of more repetitions of the
                                single character comprising the literal
                                (literal may not be more than one character
                                in length).</phrase> The literal must be either a
                                nonnumeric literal or a figurative constant
                                other than ALL literal. When a figurative
                                constant is used, the word ALL is redundant
                                and is used for readability only.</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table>
          <para>
When a figurative constant represents a string of one or more characters,
the length of the string i s determined by the compiler from context
according to the following rules:
</para>
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
When a figurative constant is associated with another data item, as
when the figurative constant is moved to or compared with another data
item, the string of characters specified by the figurative constant is
repeated character by character on the right until the size of the
resultant string is equal to the size in characters of the associated
data item. This is done prior to and independent of the application of
any JUSTIFIED clause that may be associated with the data item.
</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
When a figurative constant is not associated with another data item, as
when the figurative constant appears in a DISPLAY or STOP statement,
the length of the string is one character.
<phrase role="extension">DISPLAY SPACE is, of course, an exception.</phrase>
</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
          <para>
A figurative constant may be used wherever a literal appears in a
format, except that whenever the literal is restricted to having only
numeric characters in it, the only figurative constant permitted is ZERO
(ZEROS, ZEROES).
</para>
          <para>
When the figurative constants HIGH-VALUE(S) or LOW-VALUE(S) are used in
the source program, the artual character associated with each figurative
constant depends upon the program collating sequence specified. (See
THE OBJECT-COMPUTER PARAGRAPH, and THE SPECIAL-NAMES PARAGRAPH in Chapter 3).
</para>
          <para>
        Each reserved word which is used to reference a figurative constant
      value is a distinct character-string with the exception of the construction
      'ALL literal' which is composed of two distinct character-strings.
  </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>PICTURE Character-Strings</title>
          <para>
A PICTURE character-string consists of certain combinations of
characters in the COBOL character set used as symbols. See
The PICTURE Clause for the PICTURE character-string and for the rules that
govern their use.
</para>
          <para>
           Any punctuation character which appears as part of the specification of
      a PICTURE character-string is not considered as a punctuation character, but
      rather as a symbol used in the specification of that PICTURE
      character-string.
  </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Comment-Entries</title>
          <para>
 A comment-entry is an entry in the Identification Division that may be
      any combination of characters from the computer's character set.
  </para>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>CONCEPT OF COMPUTER INDEPENDENT DATA DESCRIPTION</title>
      <para>
           To make data as computer independent as possible, the characteristics
      or properties of the data are described in relation to a standard data
      format rather than an equipment-oriented format. This standard data format
      is oriented to general data processing applications and uses the decimal
      system to represent numbers (regardless of the radix used by the computer)
      and the remaining characters in the CIS COBOL character set to describe
      nonnumeric data items.
  </para>
      <section>
        <title>Concept of Levels</title>
        <para>
A level concept is inherent in the structure of a logical record. This
concept arises from the need to specify subdivisions of a record for the
purpose of data reference. Once a subdivision has been specified, it may be
further subdivided to permit more detailed data referral.
</para>
        <para>
The most basic subdivisions of a record, that is, those not further
subdivided, are called elementary items; consequently, a record is said to
consist of a sequence of elementary items, or the record itself may be an
elementary item.
</para>
        <para>
      In order to refer to a set of elementary items, the elementary items
are combined into groups. Each group consists of a named sequence of one or
more elementary items. Groups, in turn, may be combined into groups of two
or more groups, etc. Thus, an elementary item may belong to more than one
group.
  </para>
        <section>
          <title>Level-Numbers</title>
          <para>
      A system of level-numbers shows the organization of elementary items
and group items. Since records are the most inclusive data items,
level-numbers for records start at 01. Less inclusive data items are
assigned higher (not necessarily successive) level-numbers not greater in
value than 49. A maximum of 49 levels in a record is allowed. There is a
special level-number, 77, which is an exception to this rule (see below).
Separate entries are written in the source program for each level-number used.
</para>
          <para>
      A group includes all group and elementary items following it until a
level-number less than or equal to the level-number of that group is
encountered. All items which are immediately subordinate to a given group
item must be described using identical level-numbers greater than the
level-number used to describe that group item.
<phrase role="extension">Note that group items must not exceed 8192 Bytes in length.</phrase>
</para>
          <para>
Two types of entries exist for which there is no true concept of  level.
These are:
</para>
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
Entries that specify noncontiguous working storage and linkage data items
</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
Entries that specify condition-names.
</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
          <para>
Entries that specify noncontiguous data items, which are not
subdivisions of other items, and are not themselves subdivided, have been
assigned the special level-number 77.
</para>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Concept of Classes of Data</title>
        <para>
      The five categories of data items (see THE PICTURE CLAUSE in Chapter 3)
are grouped into three classes : alphabetic, numeric, and alphanumeric. For
alphabetic and numeric, the classes and categories are synonymous. The
alphanumeric class includes the categories of alphanumeric edited, numeric
edited and alphanumeric (without editing). Every elementary item except for
an index data item belongs to one of the classes and to one of the
categories. The class of a group item is treated at object time as
alphanumeric regardless of the class of elementary items subnrdinate to that
group item. Table 2-2 depicts the relationship of the class and categories
of data items.
</para>
        <table frame="all" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
          <title>Data Levels, classes and categories</title>
          <tgroup cols="3">
            <colspec colwidth="1.8in" align="center"/>
            <colspec colwidth="1.5in" align="center"/>
            <colspec colwidth="1.5in" align="center"/>
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>LEVEL OF ITEM</entry>
                <entry>CLASS</entry>
                <entry>CATEGORY</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry morerows="2" valign="middle">Elementary</entry>
                <entry>Alphabetic</entry>
                <entry>Alphabetic</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Numeric</entry>
                <entry>Numeric</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry valign="middle">Alphanumeric</entry>
                <entry>
                  <simplelist>
                    <member>Numeric Edited</member>
                    <member>Alphanumeric Edited</member>
                    <member>Alphanumeric</member>
                  </simplelist>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry valign="middle">Non-Elementary Group</entry>
                <entry valign="middle">Alphanumeric</entry>
                <entry>
                  <simplelist>
                    <member>Alphabetic</member>
                    <member>Numeric</member>
                    <member>Numeric Edited</member>
                    <member>Alphanumeric Edited</member>
                    <member>Alphanumeric</member>
                  </simplelist>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Selection of Character Representation and Radix</title>
        <para>
        The value of a numeric item may be represented in either binary or
   decimal form, depending on the equipment. In addition, there are several
   ways of expressing decimal. Since these representations are actually
   combinations of bits, they are commonly called binary-coded decimal forms.
   The four standard formats used for storing numeric data in CIS COBOL are as
   follows:
</para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
As alphanumeric characters stored one per byte in ASCII representation.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
As numeric characters defined by USAGE IS DISPLAY (See The USAGE Clause
        in Chapter 3) one per byte in ASCII representation. If they are signed
        and the sign is specified as rNCLUDED, bit 6 of the leading or trailing
        byte of the field is set for negative, depending on the field
        definition. rf a SEPARATE sign is specified as a one byte ASCII + or
          , a sign is added as the leading or trailing byte. If no SIGN clause
        is specified, bit 6 of the trailing digit is set to indicate negative
        by default.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
As numeric characters defined by USAGE IS COMP or COMPUTATIONAL in pure
        binary form. If the field is signed the number is held in its
        twos-complement form. Storage is then dependent on the number of 9's
        in the PICTURE clause (see The PICTURE Clause in Chapter 3) and on
        whether the field is SIGNed or not (see The SIGN Clause in Chapter 3).
        Table 2-3 shows the storage requirements for each COMP(UTATIONAL)
        PICTURE Clause.
    </para>
            <table frame="all" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
              <title>Numeric Data Storage for the COMP(UTATIONAL) PICTURE Clause.</title>
              <tgroup cols="3">
                <colspec colwidth="1.8in" align="center"/>
                <colspec colwidth="1.2in" align="center" colname="c2"/>
                <colspec colwidth="1.2in" align="center" colname="c3"/>
                <spanspec spanname="join" namest="c2" nameend="c3"/>
                <thead>
                  <row>
                    <entry morerows="1">Bytes Required</entry>
                    <entry spanname="join">Number of Characters</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>Signed</entry>
                    <entry>Unsigned</entry>
                  </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <row>
                    <entry>1</entry>
                    <entry>1-2</entry>
                    <entry>1-2</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>2</entry>
                    <entry>3-4</entry>
                    <entry>3-4</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>3</entry>
                    <entry>5-6</entry>
                    <entry>5-7</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>4</entry>
                    <entry>7-9</entry>
                    <entry>8-9</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>5</entry>
                    <entry>10-11</entry>
                    <entry>10-12</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>6</entry>
                    <entry>12-14</entry>
                    <entry>12-14</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>7</entry>
                    <entry>15-16</entry>
                    <entry>15-16</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>8</entry>
                    <entry>17-18</entry>
                    <entry>17-18</entry>
                  </row>
                </tbody>
              </tgroup>
            </table>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
As numeric characters defined by USAGE IS COMPUTATIONAL-3 or USAGE IS
   COMP-3 in packed internal decimal form. Storage is dependent on the
   number of 9's in the PICTURE clause. The decimal numbers are stored as
   signed strings of variable length of 1 through 18 digits. The sign of
   the packed decimal number is always stored in place of the least
   significant quartet of the low order byte. Each byte contains :wo
   decimal positions (four bits per digit) and the digits (0 - 9) are
   encoded as BCD numbers (0000 - 1001). Numbers are represented in the
   field as right-justified values with a + or - sign as shown in the
   example below. The maximum number of digits permitted in arithmetic
   operands is LB.
   </para>
            <para>
   EXAMPLE:
   </para>
            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
For COMPUTATIONAL-3 and PICTURE 9999, the number +1234 would be stored as follows:
   </para>
                <programlisting>
       ...      0     1     2      3      4      F
              0000   0001  0010   0011   0100   1111
                                          +---------+
                                             1 byte
   </programlisting>
                <para>
         where F represents the non-printing plus sign.
 </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
 For COMPUTATIONAL-3 and PICTURE S9999, the number +1234 would be stored as follows:
 </para>
                <para>
Storage would be as in a above except that the least significant
digit would be replaced by C (1100) representing the plus sign.
 </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
For COMPUTATIONAL-3 and PICTURE S9999, the number -1234 would be stored as follows:
   </para>
                <para>
Storage would be as in a above except that the least significant
byte would be replaced by D (1101) representing the minus sign.
 </para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <para>
Table 2-4 shows the storage requirements for each COMP-3 clause.
   </para>
            <table frame="all" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
              <title>Numeric Data Storage for the COMPUTATION-3 PICTURE Clause.</title>
              <tgroup cols="2">
                <colspec colwidth="1.8in" align="center"/>
                <colspec colwidth="2.2in" align="center" colname="c2"/>
                <thead>
                  <row>
                    <entry>Bytes Required</entry>
                    <entry>Number of Digits (Signed or Unsigned)</entry>
                  </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <row>
                    <entry>1</entry>
                    <entry>1</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>2</entry>
                    <entry>2-3</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>3</entry>
                    <entry>4-5</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>4</entry>
                    <entry>6-7</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>5</entry>
                    <entry>8-9</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>6</entry>
                    <entry>10-11</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>7</entry>
                    <entry>12-13</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>8</entry>
                    <entry>14-15</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>9</entry>
                    <entry>16-17</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>10</entry>
                    <entry>18</entry>
                  </row>
                </tbody>
              </tgroup>
            </table>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Algebraic Signs</title>
        <para>
      Algebraic signs fall into two categories: operational signs, which are
associated with signed numeric data items and signed numeric literals to
indicate their algebraic properties; and editing signs, which appear on
edited reports to identify the sign of the item.
</para>
        <para>
      The SIGN Clause permits the programmer to state explicitly, the
location of the operational sign. The Clause is optional; if it is not used
operational signs will be represented as defined by setting bit 6 of the
 trailing digit for ASCII numbers. (see above).
</para>
        <para>
      Editing signs are inserted into a data item through the use of the sign
control symbols of THE PICTURE CLAUSE.
  </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Standard Alignment Rules</title>
        <para>
      The standard rules for positioning data within an elementary item
depend on the category of the receiving item. These rules are:
</para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
If the receiving data item is described as numeric:
</para>
            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
        The data is aligned by decimal point and is moved to the receiving
             character positions with zero fill or truncation on either end as required.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
        When an assumed decimal point is not explicitly specified, the
             data item is treated as if it had an assumed decimal point
             immediately following its rightmost character and is aligned as in
             paragraph a. above.
</para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
If the receiving data item is a numeric edited data item, the data
moved to the edited item is aligned by decimal point with zero fill or
truncation at either end as required within the receiving character
positions of the data item, except where editing requirements cause
replacement of the leading zeros.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
If the receiving data item is alphanumeric (other than a numeric edited
data item), alphanumeric edited or alphabetic, the sending data is
moved to the receiving character positions and aligned at the leftmost
character position in the data item with space fill or truncation to
the right, as required.
</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>
If the JUSTIFIED Clause is specified for the receiving item, these
standard rules are modified as described in THE JUSTIFIED CLAUSE in Chapter 3.
  </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Uniqueness of Reference</title>
        <section>
          <title>Subscripting</title>
          <para>
      Subscripts can be used only when reference is made to an individual
element within a list or table of like elements that have not been assigned
individual data-names (see THE OCCURS CLAUSE in Chapter 4). The subscript
can be represented either by a numeric literal that is an integer or by a
data-name, The data-name must be a numeric elementary item that represents
an integer. The subscript may be signed and, if signed, it must be
positive. The lowest possible subscript value is 1. This value points to
the first element of the table. The next sequential elements of the table
are pointed to by subscripts whose values are 2, 3, ... . The highest
permissible subscript value, in any particular case, is the maximum number
of occurrences of the item as specified in the OCCURS clause.
</para>
          <para>
      The subscript, or set of subscripts, that identifies the table element
is delimited by the balanced pair of separators left parenthesis and right
parenthesis following the table element data-name. The table element
data-name appended with a subscript is called a subscripted data-name or an
identifier. When more than one subscript is required, they are written in
the order of successively less inclusive dimensions of the data
organization.
</para>
          <para>
The format is:
</para>
          <para>
           data-name (subscript-1    [, subscript-2 [, subscript-3 ]])
  </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Indexing</title>
          <para>
      References can be made to individual elements within a table of like
elements by specifying indexing for that reference. An index is assigned to
that level of the table by using the INDEXED BY phrase in the definition of
a table. A name given in the INDEXED BY phrase is known as an index-name
and is used to refer to the assigned index. The value of an index
corresponds to the occurrence number of an element in the associated table.
An index-name must be initialized before it is used as a table reference.
An index-name can be given an initial value by a SET statement.
</para>
          <para>
      Direct indexing is specified by using an index-name in the form of a
subscript. Relative indexing is specified when the index-name is followed
by the operator + or -, followed by an unsigned integer numeric literal all
delimited by the balanced pair of separators left parenthesis and right
parenthesis following the table element data-name. The occurrence number
resulting from relative indexing is determined by incrementing (where the
operator + is used) or decrementing (when the operator - is used), by the
value of the literal, the occurrence number represented by the value of the
index. When more than one index-name is required, they are written in the
order of successively less inclusive dimensions of the data organization.
</para>
          <para>
At the time of execution of a statement which refers to an indexed
table element, the value contained in the index referenced by the index-name
associated with the table element must neither correspond to a value less
than one nor to a value greater than the highest permissible occurrence
number of an element of the associated table. This restriction also applies
to the value resultant from relative indexing.
</para>
          <para>
The general format for indexing is:
</para>
          <cmdsynopsis>
            <group>
              <arg choice="req">
                <replaceable>data-name</replaceable>
              </arg>
              <arg choice="req">
                <replaceable>condition-name</replaceable>
              </arg>
            </group>
            <arg choice="plain">(</arg>
            <group>
              <arg choice="plain">
                <replaceable>index-name-1</replaceable>
              </arg>
              <arg choice="plain">
                <replaceable>literal-1</replaceable>
              </arg>
            </group>
            <arg choice="opt">
              <group>
                <arg choice="plain">+</arg>
                <arg choice="plain">-</arg>
              </group>
              <arg>
                <replaceable>literal-2</replaceable>
              </arg>
            </arg>
            <arg choice="opt">
              <arg choice="plain">,</arg>
              <group>
                <arg choice="plain">
                  <replaceable>index-name-2</replaceable>
                </arg>
                <arg choice="plain">
                  <replaceable>literal-3</replaceable>
                </arg>
              </group>
              <arg choice="opt">
                <group>
                  <arg choice="plain">+</arg>
                  <arg choice="plain">-</arg>
                </group>
                <arg>
                  <replaceable>literal-4</replaceable>
                </arg>
              </arg>
              <arg choice="opt">
                <arg choice="plain">,</arg>
                <group>
                  <arg choice="plain">
                    <replaceable>index-name-3</replaceable>
                  </arg>
                  <arg choice="plain">
                    <replaceable>literal-5</replaceable>
                  </arg>
                </group>
                <arg choice="opt">
                  <group>
                    <arg choice="plain">+</arg>
                    <arg choice="plain">-</arg>
                  </group>
                  <arg>
                    <replaceable>literal-6</replaceable>
                  </arg>
                </arg>
              </arg>
            </arg>
            <arg choice="plain">)</arg>
          </cmdsynopsis>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Identifier</title>
          <para>
          An identifier is a term used to reflect that a data-name, if not unique
     in a program, must be followed by a syntactically correct combination of
     subscripts or indices necessary to ensure uniqueness.
</para>
          <para>
          The general formats for identifiers are:
     Format 1:
                data-name-1    [ (subscript - 1 [,    subscript-2     [, subscript-3]] ]
     Format 2:
                                              ( j index-name-11 [{+t literal- 2]
                data-name-1
                                                ) literal-1
         [.    jindex-name-2/[{+\
               )literal-3     r -     literal-4]     [  ) literal-5    r
                                                         jindex-name-31[{ rliteral-6
                                                                            t          J]] )
          Restrictions on subscripting and indexing are:
</para>
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
A data-name must not itself be subscripted nor indexed when that
          data-name is being used as an index, or subscript.
</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
 Indexing is not permitted where subscripting is not permitted.
</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
An index may be modified only by the SET, SEARCH, and PERFORM
statements. Data items described by the USAGE IS INDEX clause permit
storage of the values associated with index-names as data in a form
specified by the implementor. Such data items are called index data items.
</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
Literal-1, literal-3, literal-5, in the above format must be positive
numeric integers. Literal-2, literal-4 , literal-6 must be unsigned
numeric integers.
</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Condition-Name</title>
          <para>
Each condition-name must be unique.
</para>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>PROGRAM STRUCTURE</title>
    <para>
          A CIS COBOL program consists of four divisions:
</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
IDENTIFICATION DIVISION - An identification of the program.
</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
ENVIRONMENT DIVISION - A description of the equipment to be used to compile and run the program.
</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
DATA DIVISION - A description of the data to be processed.
</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
PROCEDURE DIVISION - A set of procedures to specify the operations to be performed on the data.
</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>
Each division, is divided into sections which are further divided into
paragraphs, which in turn are made up of sentences.
</para>
    <section>
      <title>
        THE "ANSI SWITCH" COMPILER DIRECTIVE
      </title>
      <para>
        <phrase role="extension">Some of the 'red-tape' statements required By a strict ANSI interpretation,
are optional under CIS COBOL. It is possible to force the compiler to
insist on a strict ANSI interpretation by using the "FLAG" directive. In
the remainder of <emphasis role="underline">this Chapter</emphasis> these statements are marked &ansileft; &ansiright;. Elsewhere in
this manual a reference is made to the ANSI switch when this applies.</phrase>
      </para>
      <para>
        <phrase role="extension">If the operator enters the FLAG directive at compile time ANSI requirements
implemented in CIS COBOL are mandatory depending on their level as specified
by the Federal Compiler Testing Center under the direction of the General
Services Administration (GSA). See the description of the Compiler FLAG
directive in the <citetitle pubwork="book">CIS COBOL Operating Guide</citetitle>.</phrase>
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>IDENTIFICATION DIVISION</title>
    <section>
      <title>GENERAL DESCRIPTION</title>
      <para>
The Identification Division must be included in every ANSI COBOL source
program, This division identifies both the source program and the resultant
output listing. In addition, the user may include the date the program is
written, the date the compilation of the source program is accomplished and
such other information as desired under the paragraphs in the general format shown below.
  </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>ORGANISATION</title>
      <para>
Paragraph headers identify the type of information contained in the
paragraph. The name of the program must be given in the first paragraph,
which is the PROCRAM-ID paragraph. The other paragraphs are optional and
may be included in this division at the user's choice, in order of
presentation shown by the format below.
  </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>STRUCTURE</title>
      <para>
The following is the general format of the paragraphs in the
Identification Division and it defines the order of presentation in the source program.
   </para>
      <section>
        <title>General format</title>
        <para>
             &ansileft;IDENTIFICATION DIVISION.&ansiright;
   </para>
        <para>
             &ansileft;PROGRAN-ID. program-name.&ansiright;
   </para>
        <para>
           [AUTHOR.  [comment-entry)   ... ]
   </para>
        <para>
           [INSTALLATION.    [comment-entry]      ... ]
   </para>
        <para>
           [DATE-WRITTEN.    [comment-entry]      ... ]
   </para>
        <para>
           [DATE-COMPILED.   [comment-entry]      ... ]
   </para>
        <para>
           [SECURITY.     [comment-entry]     ... ]
  </para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>ENVIRONMENT DIVISION</title>
    <section>
      <title>GENERAL DESCRIPTION</title>
      <para>
      The Environment Division specifies a standard method of expressing
those aspects of a data processing problem that are dependent upon the
physical characteristics of a specific computer. This division allows
specification of the configuration of the compiling computer and the object
computer. In addition, information relating to input-output control,
special hardware characteristics and control techniques can be given.
</para>
      <para>
The Environment Division must be included in every COBOL source program.
</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>ORGANIZATION</title>
      <para>
      Two sections make up the Environment Division: the Configuration
Section and the Input-Output Section.
</para>
      <para>
      The Configuration Section deals with the characteristics of the source
computer and the object computer. This section is divided into three
paragraphs: the SOURCE-COMPUTER paragraph, which describes the computer
configuration on which the source program is compiled; the OBJECT-COMPUTER
paragraph, which describes the computer configuration on which the object
program produced by the compiler is to be run; and the SPECIAL-NAMES
paragraph, which relates the implementation-names used by the compiler to
the mnemonic-names used in the source program.
 </para>
      <para>
     The Input-Output Section deals with the information needed to control
transmission and handling of data between external media and the object
program. This section is divided into two paragraphs: the FILE-CONTROL
paragraph which names and associates the files with external media; and the
I-O-CONTROL paragraph which defines special control techniques to be used in the object program.
   </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>STRUCTURE</title>
      <para>
The following is the general format of the sections and paragraphs in
the Environment Division, and defines the order of presentation in the source program.
   </para>
      <section>
        <title>General Format</title>
        <para>
      &ansileft; ENVIRONMENT DIVISION. &ansiright;
   </para>
        <para>
      &ansileft; CONFIGURATION SECTION. &ansiright;
   </para>
        <para>
      &ansileft; SOURCE-COMPUTER. source-computer-entry &ansiright;
   </para>
        <para>
      &ansileft; OBJECT-COMPUTER. object-computer-entry &ansiright;
   </para>
        <para>
      [ SPECIAL-NAMES. special-names-entry ]
   </para>
        <para>
      &ansileft; INPUT-OUTPUT SECTION. &ansiright;
   </para>
        <para>
      &ansileft; FILE-CONTROL.&ansiright;    {file-control-entry} ...
   </para>
        <para>
      [ I-O-CONTROL.  input-output-control-entry ]
  </para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>DATA DIVISION</title>
    <section>
      <title>OVERALL APPROACH</title>
      <para>
            The Data Division describes the data that the object program is to
      accept as input, to manipulate, to create, or to produce as output, Data to
      be processed falls into three categories:
</para>
      <para>
</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
That which is contained in files and enters or leaves the internal
            memory of the computer from a specified area or areas.
</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
That which is developed internally and placed into intermediate or
            working storage, or placed into specific format for output reporting
            purposes.
</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
Constants which are defined by the user.
  </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>PHYSICAL AND LOGICAL ASPECTS OF DATA DESCRIPTION</title>
      <section>
        <title>Data Division Organization</title>
        <para>
The DATA DIVISION which is one of the required divisions in a program,
is subdivided into sections. These are the File, Working-Storage and
Linkage sections.
</para>
        <para>
The FILE SECTION defines the structure of data files. Each file is
defined by a file description entry and one or more record descriptions, or
by a file description entry and one or more report description entries.
Record descriptions are written immediately following the file description
entry. The WORKING-STORAGE SECTION describes records and noncontiguous data
items which are not part of external data files but are developed and
processed internally. It also describes data items whose values are
assigned in the source program and do not change during the execution of the
object program. The LINKAGE SECTION appears in the called program and
describes data items that are to be referred to by the calling program and
the called program. Its structure is the same as the WORKING-STORAGE SECTION.
</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Format</title>
        <para>
             The following gives the general fonnat of the sections in the Data
Division, and defines the order of their presentation in the source program.
             &ansileft; DATA DIVISION. &ansiright;
         [FILE SECTION. [file-description-entry  [record-description-entry]...]...]
         [WORKING-STORAGE SECTION.
         [{ 77-level-desciription-entry } J ...  ]
             record-description-entry
          [LINKAGE-SECTION.
         [{ 77-level-description-entry
             record-description-entry         ...   J
  </para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>PROCEDURE DIVISION</title>
    <section>
      <title>GENERAL DESCRIPTION</title>
      <para>
      The Procedure Division must be included in every COBOL source program.
This division may contain declarative procedures.
</para>
      <section>
        <title>Declaratives</title>
        <para>
      Declarative sections must be grouped at the beginning of the Procedure
Division preceded by the key word DECLARATIVES and followed by the key words
END DECLARATIVES. (See descriptions of the USE statement in Chapters 5, 6
and 7 and the Debug Chapter 10).
</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Procedures</title>
        <para>
A  procedure is composed of a paragraph, or group of successive
paragraphs <phrase role="extension">(the first paragraph-name is optional)</phrase>,
or a section, or a group
of successive sections within the Procedure Division. If one paragraph is in
a section, then all paragraphs must be in sections. A procedure-name is a
word used to refer to a paragraph or section in the source program in which
it occurs. It consists of a paragraph-name (which may be qualified), or a
section-name.
</para>
        <para>
      The end of the Procedure Divis i on and the physical end of the program
is that physical position in a COBOL source program after which no further
procedures appear.
</para>
        <para>
      A section consists of a section header followed by zero, one, or more
successive paragraphs. A section ends immediately before the next section
or at the end of the Procedure Division or, in the declaratives portion of
the Procedure Division, at the key words END DECLARATIVES.
</para>
        <para>
      A paragraph consists of a paragraph-name followed by a period and a
space and by zero, one, or more successiv e sentences. A paragraph ends
immediately before the next paragraph-name or section-name or at the end of
the Procedure Division or, in the declaratives portion of the Procedure
Division, at the key words END DECLARATIVES.
</para>
        <para>
          <phrase role="extension">In CIS COBOL paragraph names may be entirely omitted. If paragraph
        names are used then they may be mixed with section names as required, in any
        order. Note that is is not possible to GO TO or PERFORM a piece of code
        unless it has either a section or a paragraph name.</phrase>
        </para>
        <para>
      A sentence consists of one or more statements and is terminated by a
period followed by a space.
</para>
        <para>
A statement is a syntactically valid combination of words and symbols
beginning with a COBOL verb.
</para>
        <para>
      The term 'identifier' is defined as the word or words necessary to make
unique reference to a data item.
</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Execution</title>
        <para>
       Execution begins with the first statement of the Procedure Division,
excluding declaratives. Statements are then executed in the order in which
they are presented for compilation, except where the rules indicate some
other order.

</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Format</title>
        <section>
          <title>Procedure Division Header</title>
          <para>
       The Procedure Division is identified by and must begin with the following header:
       </para>
          <para>
             PROCEDURE DIVISION (USING data-name-1 [, data-name-2]   ...] .
</para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Procedure Division Body<indexterm><primary>Body, Procedure Division</primary></indexterm></title>
          <para>
       The body of the Procedure Division must conform to one of the following formats:
       </para>
          <para>
Format 1:
       </para>
          <para>
     [DECLARATIVES.
     ) section-name SECTION    [segment-number).       declarative-sentence
     [paragraph-name.     [sentence]    ..  ]       ! ...
       END DECLARATIVE$.]
    ){section-name SECTION      [segment-number]}.                                     ....I
                                               J ... !
    [ paragraph-name-}
       </para>
          <para>
Format 2 :
       </para>
          <para>
    ) paragraph-name.}
                          [sentence]
                          [sentence]

</para>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>STATEMENTS AND SENTENCES</title>
      <para>
       There are three types of statements:
       </para>
      <orderedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
Conditional statements,
       </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
Compiler directing statements,
       </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
Imperative statements.
       </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>
       There are three types of sentences:
       </para>
      <orderedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
Conditional sentences,
       </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
Compiler directing sentences,
       </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
Imperative sentences.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <section>
        <title>Conditional Statement<indexterm><primary>Statements, Conditional</primary></indexterm></title>
        <para>
 A conditional statement specifies that the truth value of a condition
is to be determined and that the subsequent action of the object program is
dependent on this truth value.
</para>
        <para>
     A conditional statement is one of the following:
</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
An IF statement.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
A READ statement that specifies the AT END or INVALID KEY phrase.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
A WRITE statement that specifies the INVALID KEY phrase.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
A START, REWRITE or DELETE statement that specifies the INVALID KEY phrase.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
An arithmetic statement (ADD, DIVIDE, MULTIPLY, SUBTRACT) that specifies the SIZE ERROR phrase.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
A CALL statement that specifies the ON OVERFLOW phrase.
</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Conditional Sentence</title>
        <para>
     A conditional sentence is a conditional statement, optionally preceded
by an imperative statement, terminated by a period followed by a space.
</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Compiler Directing Statement</title>
        <para>
     A compiler directing statement consists of a compiler directing verb
and its operands. The compiler directing verbs are COPY, ENTER and USE (see
THE COPY STATEMENT in Chapter 9, THE ENTER STATEMENT in Chapter 3, and THE
USE STATEMENT in Chapters 5, 6 and 7). A compiler directing statement
causes the compiler to take a specified action during compilation.
</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Compiler Directing Sentence</title>
        <para>
     A compiler directing sentence is a single compiler directing statement
terminated by a period followed by a space.
</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Imperative Statement<indexterm><primary>Statements, Imperative</primary></indexterm></title>
        <para>
     An Imperative statement indicates a specific unconditional action to be
taken by the object program. An imperative statement is any statement that
is neither a conditional statement, nor a compiler directing statement. An
imperative statement may consist of a sequence of imperative statements,
each possibly separated from the next by a separator.
</para>
        <para>
The imperative verbs are:
</para>
        <simplelist type="vert" columns="3">
          <member>ACCEPT</member>
          <member>ADD<superscript>1</superscript></member>
          <member>ALTER</member>
          <member>CALL<superscript>3</superscript></member>
          <member>CANCEL</member>
          <member>CLOSE</member>
          <member>DELETE<superscript>2</superscript></member>
          <member>DISPLAY</member>
          <member>DIVIDE<superscript>1</superscript></member>
          <member>EXIT</member>
          <member>GO</member>
          <member>INSPECT</member>
          <member>MOVE</member>
          <member>MULTIPLY<superscript>1</superscript></member>
          <member>OPEN</member>
          <member>PERFORM</member>
          <member>READ<superscript>4</superscript></member>
          <member>REWRITE<superscript>2</superscript></member>
          <member>SET</member>
          <member>START<superscript>2</superscript></member>
          <member>STOP</member>
          <member>SUBTRACT<superscript>1</superscript></member>
          <member>WRITE<superscript>5</superscript></member>
        </simplelist>
        <orderedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para>
Without the optional SIZE ERROR phrase.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Without the optional INVALID KEY phrase.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Without the optional ON OVERFLOW phrase.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Without the optional AT END phrase or INVALID KEY phrase.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Without the optional INVALID KEY phrase or END-OF-PAGE phrase.
</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>
When 'imperative-statement' appears in the general format of
statements, 'imperative-statement' refers to that sequence of consecutive
imperative statements that m1111t be ended by a period or an ELSE phrase
associated with a previous IF statement.
</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Imperative Sentence</title>
        <para>
An imperative sentence is an imperative statement terminated by a period followed by a space.
</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>REFERENCE FORMAT</title>
    <section>
      <title>GENERAL DESCRIPTION</title>
      <para>
The reference format, which provides a standard method for describing
COBOL source programs, is described in terms of character positions in a
line on an input-output medium. The CIS COBOL compiler accepts source
programs written in reference format and produces an output listing of the
source program input in reference fonnat.
</para>
      <para>
The rules for spacing given in the discussion of the reference format
take precedence over all other rules for spacing.
</para>
      <para>
The divisions of a source program must be ordered as follows: the
Identification Division, then the Environment Divisi n, then the Data
Division, then the Procedure Division. Each division must be written
according to the rules for the reference format.
</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>REFERENCE FORMAT REPRESENTATION</title>
      <para>
The reference format for a line is represented as in Figure 2-1.
</para>
      <figure>
        <title>Reference Format for a COBOL Source Line.</title>
        <programlisting width="80"><![CDATA[
|                         |      |                 |                      |
Margin               Margin      Margin       Margin                 Margin
L                         C      A                 B                      R
|                         |      |           1    1|   1    1   .  .  .   |
| 1  2    3    4    5    6|   7  | 8    9    0    1|   2    3             |
<------------------------> <----> <---------------> <------------------->
  Sequence Number Area       ^          Area A         Area B
                             |
                       Indicator Area
]]></programlisting>
        <para>
Margin L is immediately to the left of the leftmost character position of a line.
</para>
        <para>
Margin C is between the 6th and 7th character positions of a line.
</para>
        <para>
Margin A is between the 7th and 8th character positions of a line.
</para>
        <para>
Margin B is between the 11th and 12th character positions of a line.
</para>
        <para>
Margin R is immediately to the right of the rightmost character position of a line.
</para>
        <para>
The sequence number area occupies six character positions (1-6), and is between Margin L and Margin C.
</para>
        <para>
The indicator area is the 7th character position of a line.
</para>
        <para>
Area A occupies character positions 8, 9, 10 and 11, and is between margin A and margin B.
</para>
        <para>
Area B occupies character positions 12 through 72 inclusive; it begins immediately to the right of Margin 8 and terminates immediately to the left of Margin R.
</para>
      </figure>
      <section>
        <title>Sequence Numbers</title>
        <para>
A sequence number, consisting of six digits in the sequence area, may
be used to label a source program line.
</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Continuation of Lines</title>
        <para>
Whenever a sentence, entry, phrase, or clause requires more than one
line, it may be continued by starting subsequent line(s) in area B. These
subsequent lines are called the continuation line(s). The line being
continued is called the continued line. Any word or literal may be broken
in such a way that part of it appears on a continuation line.
</para>
        <para>
     A hyphen in the indicator area of a line indicates that the first
nonblank character in area B of the current line is the successor of the
last nonblank character of the preceding line without any intervening space.
However, if the continued line contains a nonnumeric literal without closing
quotation mark, the first nonblank character in area B on the continuation
line must be a quotation mark, and the continuation starts with the
character immediately after that quotation mark. All spaces at the end of
the continued line are considered part of the literal. Area A of a
continuation line must be blank.
</para>
        <para>
     If there is no hyphen in the indicator area of a line, it is assumed
that the last character in the preceding line is followed by a space.
</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Blank Lines<indexterm><primary>Blank Lines</primary></indexterm></title>
        <para>
A blank line is one that is blank from margin C to margin R, inclusive.
A blank line can appear anywhere in the source program, except immediately
preceding a continuation line. (See Figure 2-1).
</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>DIVISION, SECTION, PARAGRAPH FORMATS</title>
      <section>
        <title>Division Header</title>
        <para>
     The division header must start in area A.  (See Figure 2-1).
</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Section Header</title>
        <para>
     The section header must start in area A.  (See Figure 2-1).
</para>
        <para>
     A section consists of paragraphs in the Environment and Procedure
Divisions and Data Division entries in the Data Division.
</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Paragraph Header, Paragraph-Name and Paragraph</title>
        <para>
     A paragraph consists of a paragraph-name followed by a period and a
space and by zero, one or more sentences, or a paragraph header followed by
one or more entries. Comment entries may be included within a paragraph.
The paragraph header or paragraph-name starts in area A of any line
following the first line of a division or a section.
</para>
        <para>
       The first sentence or entry in a paragraph begins either on the same
  line as the paragraph header or paragraph-name or in area B of the next
  nonblank line that is not a comment line. Successive sentences or entries
  either begin in area B of the same line as the preceding sentence or entry
  or in area B of the next nonblank line that is not a comment line.
</para>
        <para>
          <phrase role="extension">Note that in CIS COBOL program sentences may commence anywhere in Area A or Area B.</phrase>
        </para>
        <para>
When the sentences or entries of a paragraph require more than one line
  they may be continued as described in CONTINUATION OF LINES in this Chapter.
</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>DATA DIVISION ENTRIES</title>
      <para>
        Each Data Division entry begins with a level indicator or a
  level-number, followed by a space, followed by its associated name (except
  in the Report Section), followed by a sequence of independent descriptive
  clauses. Each clause, except the last clause of an entry, may be terminated
  by either the separator semicolon or the separator comma. The last clause
  is always terminated by a period followed by a space.
<para>
</para>
        There are two types of Data Division entries: those which begin with a
  level indicator and those which begin with a level-number.
<para>
</para>
A level indicator is the indicator:  FD
(see THE FILE DESCRIPTION - COMPLETE ENTRY SKELETON in Chapters 5, 6 and 7)
<para>
</para>
        In those Data Division entries that begin with a level indicator, the
  level indicator begins in area A followed by a space and followed in area B
  with its associated name and appropriate descriptive information.
<para>
</para>
        Those Data Division entries that begin with level-numbers are called
  data description entries.
</para>
      <para>
A level-number has a value taken from the set of values 1 through 49,
77. Level-numbers in the range 1 through 9 may be written either as a
single digit or as a zero followed by a significant digit. At least one
space must separate a level-number from the word following the level-number.
</para>
      <para>
In those data description entries that begin with level-number 01 or
  77, the level-number begins in area A followed by a space and followed in
  area B by its associated record-name or item-name and appropriate
  descriptive information.
</para>
      <para>
    Successive data description entries may have the same format as the
  first or may be indented according to level-number. The entries in the
  output listing need be indented only if the input is indented. Indentation
  does not affect the magnitude of a level-number.
</para>
      <para>
When level-numbers are to be indented, each new level-number may begin
any number of spaces to tile right of margin A. The extent of indentation to
the right is determined only by the width of the physical medium.
</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>DECLARATIVES<indexterm><primary>Declaratives</primary></indexterm></title>
      <para>
The key word DECLARATIVES and the key words END DECLARATIVES that
precede and follow, respectively, the declaratives portion of the Procedure
Division must each appear on a line by themselves, Each must begin in area
A and be followed by a period and a space (see Figure 2-1).
</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>COMMENT LINES<indexterm><primary>Comment Lines</primary></indexterm></title>
      <para>
A comment line is any line with an asterisk in the continuation
indicator area of the line. A comment line can appear as any line in a
source program after the Identification Division header. Any combination of
characters from the computer's character set may be included in area A and
area B of that line (see Figure 2-1). The asterisk and the characters in
area A and area B will be produced on the listing but serve as documentation
only. A special form of comment line represented by a stroke in the
indicator area of the line causes page ejection prior to printing the
comment.
</para>
      <para>
      Successive comment lines are allowed. Continuation of comment lines is
permitted, except that each continuation line must contain an '*' in the
indicator area.
  </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>RESERVED WORDS<indexterm><primary>Reserved Words</primary></indexterm></title>
    <para>
A full list of reserved words is given in Appendix A.
</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
