<?xml version="1.0"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>THE NUCLEUS</title>
  <section>
    <title>FUNCTION OF THE NUCLEUS</title>
    <para>
The Nucleus provides a basic language capability for the internal
processing of data within the basic structure of the four divisions of a program.
</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>IDENTIFICATION DIVISION IN THE NUCLEUS</title>
    <section>
      <title>GENERAL DESCRIPTION</title>
      <para>
The Identification Division must be included in every COBOL source
program. This division identifies the source program and the resultant
output listing. In addition, the user may include the date the program is
written and such other information as desired under the paragraphs in the
general format shown below.
</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>ORGANIZATION</title>
      <para>
Paragraph headers identify the type of information contained in the
paragraph. The name of the program must be given in the first paragraph,
which is the PROGRAM-ID paragraph. The other paragraphs are optional and
may be included in this division at the user's choice, in the order of
presentation shown by the general format below.
</para>
      <section>
        <title>Structure</title>
        <para>
The general format of the paragraphs in the Identification Division is
given below and shows the order of presentation in the source program.
</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Format</title>
        <cmdsynopsis>
          <arg choice="ansi">IDENTIFICATION DIVISION</arg>
          <sbr/>
          <arg choice="ansi">PROGRAM-ID.   program-name.</arg>
          <sbr/>
          <arg choice="opt">AUTHOR.    <arg choice="opt" rep="repeat">comment-entry</arg></arg>
          <sbr/>
          <arg choice="opt">INSTALLATION.     <arg choice="opt" rep="repeat">comment-entry</arg></arg>
          <sbr/>
          <arg choice="opt">DATE-WRITTEN.     <arg choice="opt" rep="repeat">comment-entry</arg></arg>
          <sbr/>
          <arg choice="opt">DATE-COMPILED.      <arg choice="opt" rep="repeat">comment-entry</arg></arg>
          <sbr/>
          <arg choice="opt">SECURITY.    <arg choice="opt" rep="repeat">comment-entry</arg></arg>
        </cmdsynopsis>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Syntax Rules</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The Identification Division must begin with the reserved words
IDENTIFICATION DIVISION followed by a period and a space.
 </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The comment-entry may be any combination of the characters from the
computer's character set and may be written in area B on one or more
lines. The continuation of the comment-entry by the use of the hyphen
in the indicator area is not permitted.
 </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>THE PROGRAM-ID PARAGRAPH</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>PROGRAM-ID Paragraph</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <section>
        <title>Function</title>
        <para>
The PROGRAM-ID paragraph gives the name by which a program is identified.
</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Format</title>
        <cmdsynopsis>
          <command>PROGRAM-ID.</command>
          <arg choice="plain">
            <replaceable>program-name.</replaceable>
          </arg>
        </cmdsynopsis>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Syntax Rules</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The program-name must conform to the rules for formation of a user-defined word.
 </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Rules</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The PROGRAM-ID paragraph must contain the name of the program and must
be present in every program <phrase role="extension">if the FLAG directive is used.</phrase>
 </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The program-name identifies the source program and all listings
pertaining to a particular program.
 </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>THE DATE-COMPILED PARAGRAPH</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>DATE-COMPILED Paragraph</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <section>
        <title>Function</title>
        <para>
The DATE-COMPILED paragraph provides the compilation date in the
Identification Division source program listing.
</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Format</title>
        <cmdsynopsis>
          <command>DATE-COMPILED.</command>
          <arg choice="plain">
            <replaceable>comment-entry ...</replaceable>
          </arg>
        </cmdsynopsis>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Syntax Rule</title>
        <para>
The comment-entry may be any combination of the characters from the
computer's character set. The continuation of the comment entry by use of
the hyphen is not permitted; however, the comment entry may be contained on
one or more lines.
</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Rule</title>
        <para>
The paragraph-name DATE-COMPILED causes a date string to be inserted
during program compilation. If a DATE-COMPILED is present, the
comment-entry is replaced in its entirety by the date string.
<phrase role="extension">See the <citetitle pubwork="book">CIS COBOL Operating Guide</citetitle>
for details of the derivation of the comment-entry
replacement string for your implementation of CIS COBOL compile-time.</phrase>
</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>ENVIRONMENT DIVISION IN THE NUCLEUS</title>
    <section>
      <title>CONFIGURATION SECTION</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>CONFIGURATION SECTION</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <section>
        <title>The SOURCE-COMPUTER Paragraph</title>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>SOURCE-COMPUTER Paragraph</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>Paragraph, SOURCE-COMPUTER</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <section>
          <title>Function</title>
          <para>
The SOURCE-COMPUTER paragraph identifies the computer upon which the
program is to be compiled.
</para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>General Format</title>
          <cmdsynopsis>
            <command>SOURCE-COMPUTER.</command>
            <arg choice="plain">
              <replaceable>computer-name.</replaceable>
            </arg>
          </cmdsynopsis>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Syntax Rule</title>
          <para>
      Computer-name must be one COBOL word defined by the user.
      </para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>General Rules</title>
          <para>
The computer-name provides a means for identifying equipment
configuration, in which case the computer-name and its implied configuration
are specified by the user.
<phrase role="extension">The SOURCE-COMPUTER paragraph is treated as for documentation purposes only.</phrase>
</para>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>The OBJECT-COMPUTER Paragraph</title>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>OBJECT-COMPUTER Paragraph</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <section>
          <title>Function</title>
          <para>
The OBJECT-COMPUTER Paragraph identifies the computer on which the program is to be executed.
</para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>General Format</title>
          <cmdsynopsis>
            <command>OBJECT-COMPUTER.</command>
            <arg choice="plain">computer-name.</arg>
            <sbr/>
            <arg choice="opt">,MEMORY SIZE <replaceable>integer</replaceable>
              <group choice="req"><arg>WORDS</arg><arg>CHARACTERS</arg><arg>MODULES</arg></group>
            </arg>
            <sbr/>
            <arg choice="opt">,PROGRAM COLLATING SEQUENCE IS <replaceable>alphabet-name</replaceable></arg>
            <sbr/>
            <arg choice="opt">,SEGMENT-LIMIT IS <replaceable>segment-number</replaceable></arg>
          </cmdsynopsis>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Syntax Rules</title>
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
Computer-name must be one COBOL word defined by the user.
 </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
Segment-number must be an integer in the range 1 through 49.
 </para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>General Rules</title>
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
The computer-name provides a means for identifying equipment
configuration, in which case the computer-name and its implied
configurations are specified by the user. The configuration definition
contains specific information concerning the memory size.
<phrase role="extension">The computer-name, segment-limit and configuration definition are treated
as for documentation purposes only.</phrase>
</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
If the PROGRAM COLLATING SEQUENCE Clause is specified, the collating
sequence associated with alphabet-name is used to determine the truth
value of any nonnumeric comparisons:
</para>
              <para>
Explicitly specified in relation conditions
(see Relation Condition later in this Chapter).
 </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
If the PROGRAM COLLATING SEQUENCE Clause is not specified, the native
collating sequence is used. Appendix B lists the full ASCII collating
sequence (native) and those characters used in COBOL.
 </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
If the PROGRAM COLLATING SEQUENCE Clause is specified, the program
collating sequence is the collating sequence associated with the
alphabet-name specified in that Clause.
 </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
The PROGRAM COLLATING SEQUENCE Clause is also applied to any nonnumeric merge or sort keys.
 </para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>The SPECIAL-NAMES Paragraph</title>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>SPECIAL-NAMES Paragraph</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <section>
          <title>Function</title>
          <para>
The SPECIAL-NAMES paragraph provides a means of relating
implementor-names to user-specified mnemonic-names and of relating
alphabet-names to character sets and/or collating sequences.
</para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>General Format</title>
          <cmdsynopsis>
            <command>SPECIAL-NAMES.</command>
            <sbr/>
            <arg>SWITCH</arg>
            <arg choice="req">0 ... 7</arg>
            <arg choice="opt">IS mnemonic-name</arg>
            <group choice="req">
              <arg>,ON STATUS IS condition-name-1</arg>
              <arg choice="opt">,OFF STATUS IS condition-name-2</arg>
              <arg>,OFF STATUS IS condition-name-2</arg>
              <arg choice="opt">,ON STATUS IS condition-name-1</arg>
            </group>
            <sbr/>
            <arg choice="opt">
              <group choice="req">
                <arg>,SYSIN</arg>
                <arg>,SYSOUT</arg>
              </group>
              <arg>IS mnemonic-name</arg>
            </arg>
            <sbr/>
            <arg choice="opt">, TAB IS mnemonic-name</arg>
            <sbr/>
            <arg choice="opt" rep="repeat">
              <arg>, alphabet-name IS</arg>
              <group choice="req">
                <arg>STANDARD-1</arg>
                <arg>NATIVE</arg>
              </group>
            </arg>
            <sbr/>
            <arg choice="opt">, CURRENCY SIGN IS literal-9</arg>
            <sbr/>
            <arg choice="opt">, DECIMAL-POINT IS COMMA</arg>
            <sbr/>
            <arg choice="opt">
              <phrase role="extension">, CONSOLE IS CRT</phrase>
            </arg>
            <sbr/>
            <arg choice="opt">
              <phrase role="extension">, CURSOR IS data-name-1</phrase>
            </arg>
            <arg>.</arg>
          </cmdsynopsis>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>General Rules</title>
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
The status of the switch is specified by condition-names and
interrogated by testing the condition-names
(see Switch-Status Condition later in this Chapter).
 </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
The alphabet-name clause provides a means for relating a name to a
specified character code set and/or collating sequence. When
alphabet - name is referenced in the PROGRAM COLLATING SEQUENCE clause
(see THE OBJECT-COMPUTER PARAGRAPH in this Chapter).
The alphabet-name clause specifies a collating sequence. When alphabet-name is
referenced in a CODE-SET clause in a file description entry
(see The File Description Complete Entry Skeleton in Chapter 5),
the alphabet-name clause specifies a character code set.
</para>
              <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
                <listitem>
                  <para>
If the STANDARD-1 phrase is specified, the character code set or
collating sequence identified is that defined in American National
Standard Code for Information Interchange, X3.4-1968 . Appendix B
defines the correspondence between the characters of the standard
character set and the characters of the native character set.
 </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
If the NATIVE phrase is specified, the native character code set
or native collating sequence is used. The native collating
sequence is as in ANSI publication X3.4-1968 (see Appendix B) .
</para>
                </listitem>
              </orderedlist>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
The character that has the highest ordinal position in the program
collating sequence specified is associated with the figurative constant
HIGH- VALUE. If more than one character has the highest position in the
program collating sequence, the last character specified.
</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
The character that has the lowest ordinal position in the program
collating sequence specified is associated with the figurative constant
LOW-VALUE. If more than one character has the lowest position in the
program collating sequence, the first character specified is associated
with the figurative constant LOW-VALUE.
 </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
The literal which appears in the CURRENCY SIGN IS literal clause is
used in the PICTURE clause to represent the currency symbol. The
literal is limited to a single character and must not be one of the
following characters.
</para>
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
digits 0 thru 9;
</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
alphabetic characters A, B, C, D, L, P, R, S, V, X, Z, or the space;
</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
special characters '*', '+', '-', ',', '.', ';', '(', ')', '"', '/' or '='.
</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
              <para>
If this clause is not present, only the currency sign is used in the PICTURE clause.
</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
The clause DECIMAL - POINT IS COMMA means that the function of comma and
period are exchanged in the character-string of the PICTURE clause and
in numeric literals.
 </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <phrase role="extension">The clause CONSOLE IS changes the defaults in the ACCEPT and DISPLAY
statements to the CIS COBOL interactive extension that enables data to
be accepted or displayed at any specified point on the screen.
See THE ACCEPT STATEMENT and the DISPLAY STATEMENT in this Chapter.</phrase>
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <indexterm>
                  <primary>CURSOR IS Clause</primary>
                </indexterm>
                <indexterm>
                  <primary>Clause, CURSOR IS</primary>
                </indexterm>
                <phrase role="extension">The clause CURSOR IS specifies the data-name to contain the CRT cursor
address as used by the ACCEPT statement. If CURSOR IS is not specified
the default cursor position on executing an ACCEPT statement is the
'Home' position at top left of the CRT screen. The CURSOR IS clause
enables a program to retain a position at the end of execution of the
last ACCEPT statement or to specify the initial position at the start of
any ACCEPT statement. This is a useful facility when programming
menu-type operator prompts. The operator need then only move the
cursor to the selected option prompt and press RETURN or just press
RETURN for the default option.</phrase>
              </para>
              <para>
                <phrase role="extension">Data-name contains the name of the PIC 9999 field in which the most
significant 99 represents a line count in the range one to the maximum
number of lines on the user screen, and the least significant 99
represents a character position in the range one to the maximum
positions allowed by the width of the user screen. If data-name is
zero, the effect is as if the CURSOR clause was not used, i.e.,
initial cursor position is top left of the screen.
(See also the ACCEPT STATEMENT later in this Chapter).</phrase>
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <phrase role="extension">SYSIN and SYSOUT specify the system input stream and system output
stream respectively.
At this release they are treated as for documentation purposes only.</phrase>
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <phrase role="extension">TAB specifies the skip-to-head-of-form system function that can be used
with WRITE ADVANCING. It is treated as for documentation purposes only at this release.</phrase>
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>DATA DIVISION IN THE NUCLEUS</title>
    <section>
      <title>WORKING STORAGE SECTION</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>WORKING STORAGE Section</primary>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>WORKING-STORAGe Section</primary>
        </indexterm>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
The Working-Storage Section is composed of the section header, followed
by data description entries for noncontiguous data items and/or record
description entries. Each Working-Storage Section record name and
noncontiguous item name must be unique.
</para>
      <section>
        <title>Noncontiguous Working-Storage</title>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>Working-Storage Noncontiguous</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>Data Description, Entry</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>
Items and constants in Working-Storage which bear no hierarchical
relationship to one another need not be grouped into records, provided they
do not need to be further subdivided. Instead, they are classified and
defined in a separate data description entry which begins with the special
level-number, 77.
</para>
        <para>
The following data clauses are required in each data description entry:
</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Level-number 77</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Data-name</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The PICTURE clause or the USAGE IS INDEX clause</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>
Other data description clauses are optional and can be used to complete
the description of the item if necessary.
</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Working-Storage Records</title>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>Working-Storage Records</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>
      Data elements and constants in Working-Storage which bear a definite
hierarchic relationship to one another must be grouped into records
according to the rules for formation of record descriptions. All clauses
which are used in record descriptions in the File Section can be used in
record descriptions in the Working-Storage Section.
</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Initial Values</title>
        <para>
     The initial value of any item in the Working-Storage Section except an
index data item is specified by using the VALUE clause with the data item.
The initial value of any index data item is unpredictable.
</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="c03.skeleton">
      <title>THE DATA DESCRIPTION - COMPLETE ENTRY SKELETON</title>
      <section>
        <title>Function</title>
        <para>
      A data description entry specifies the characteristics of a particular
item of data.
      </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Format</title>
        <cmdsynopsis>
          <arg>level-number</arg>
          <group choice="req">
            <arg>data-name-1</arg>
            <arg>FILLER</arg>
          </group>
          <sbr/>
          <arg choice="opt">; REDEFINES data-name-2</arg>
          <sbr/>
          <arg choice="opt">
            <group choice="req">
              <arg>PICTURE</arg>
              <arg>PIC</arg>
            </group>
            <arg>IS character-string</arg>
          </arg>
          <sbr/>
          <arg choice="opt">
            <arg>;</arg>
            <arg choice="opt">USAGE IS</arg>
            <group choice="req">
              <arg>COMPUTATIONAL</arg>
              <arg>COMP</arg>
              <arg>COMPUTATIONAL-3</arg>
              <arg>COMP-3</arg>
              <arg>DISPLAY</arg>
            </group>
          </arg>
          <sbr/>
          <arg choice="opt">
            <arg>;</arg>
            <arg choice="opt">SIGN IS</arg>
            <group choice="req">
              <arg>LEADING</arg>
              <arg>TRAILING</arg>
            </group>
            <arg choice="opt">SEPARATE CHARACTER</arg>
          </arg>
          <sbr/>
          <arg choice="opt">
            <arg>;</arg>
            <group choice="req">
              <arg>SYNCHRONIZED</arg>
              <arg>SYNC</arg>
            </group>
            <group choice="req">
              <arg>LEFT</arg>
              <arg>RIGHT</arg>
            </group>
          </arg>
          <sbr/>
          <arg choice="opt">
            <arg>;</arg>
            <group choice="req">
              <arg>JUSTIFIED</arg>
              <arg>JUST</arg>
            </group>
            <arg>RIGHT</arg>
          </arg>
          <arg choice="opt">
            <arg>;</arg>
            <arg>BLANK WHEN ZERO</arg>
          </arg>
          <sbr/>
          <arg choice="opt">
            <arg>;</arg>
            <arg>VALUE IS literal</arg>
          </arg>
        </cmdsynopsis>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Syntax Rules</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The level-number may be any number from 01-49 or 77.
 </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The clauses may be written in any order with two exceptions: the
      data-name-1 or FILLER clause must immediately follow the level-number;
      the REDEFINES clause, when used, must immediately follow the
      data-name-1 clause.
 </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The PICTURE clause must be specified for every elementary item except
an index data item, in which case use of this clause is prohibited.
 </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Rule</title>
        <para>
The clauses SYNCHRONIZED, PICTURE, JUSTIFIED, and BLANK WHEN ZERO, must
not be specified except for an elementary data item.
</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>THE BLANK WHEN ZERO CLAUSE</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>BLANK WHEN ZERO Clause</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Clause, BLANK WHEN ZERO</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <section>
        <title>Function</title>
        <para>
The BLANK WHEN ZERO clause permits the blanking of an item when its value is zero.
       </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Format</title>
        <cmdsynopsis>
          <command>BLANK WHEN ZERO</command>
        </cmdsynopsis>
      </section>
      <section><title>Syntax Rules</title>
       The BLANK WHEN ZERO clause can be used only for an elementary item
whose   PICTURE is specified as numeric with implicit or explicit USAGE IS
DISPLAY, or numeric edited. (See <xref linkend="c03.picture"/> later in this Chapter).
</section>
      <section>
        <title>General Rules</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
When the BLANK WHEN ZERO clause is used, the item will contain nothing
but spaces if the value of the item is zero.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
When the BLANK WHEN ZERO clause is used for an item whose PICTURE is
numeric, the category of the item is considered to be numeric edited.
</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>THE DATA-NAME OR FILLER CLAUSE</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Clause, DATA-NAME or FILLER</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>DATA-NAME or FILLER Clause</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <section>
        <title>Function</title>
        <para>
A data-name specifies the name of the data being described. The word
FILLER specifies an elementary item of the logical record that cannot be
referred to explicitly.
</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Format</title>
        <cmdsynopsis>
          <group choice="req">
            <arg>data-name</arg>
            <arg>FILLER</arg>
          </group>
        </cmdsynopsis>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Syntax Rule</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
In the File, Working-Storage, Communication and Linkage Sections, a
data-name or the key word FILLER must be the first word following the
level-number in each data description entry.
        </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Rule</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The key word FILLER may be used to name an elementary item in a record.
Under no circumstances can a FILLER item be referred to explicitly.
       </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>THE JUSTIFIED CLAUSE</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Clause, JUSTIFIED</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>JUSTIFIED Clause</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <section>
        <title>Function</title>
        <para>
The JUSTIFIED clause specifies non-standard positioning of data within
a receiving data item.
    </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Format</title>
        <cmdsynopsis>
          <group choice="req">
            <arg>JUSTIFIED</arg>
            <arg>JUST</arg>
          </group>
          <arg>RIGHT</arg>
        </cmdsynopsis>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Syntax Rules</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The JUSTIFIED clause can be specified only at the elementary item level.
          </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
JUST is an abbreviation for JUSTIFIED.
     </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The JUSTIFIED clause cannot be specified for any data item described as
numeric or for which editing is specified.
         </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Rules</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
When a receiving data item is described with the JUSTIFIED clause and
the sending data item is larger than the receiving data item, the
leftmost characters are truncated. When the receiving data item is
described with the JUSTIFIED clause and it is larger than the sending
data item, the data is aligned at the rightmost character position in
the data item with space fill for the leftmost character positions.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
When the JUSTIFIED clause is omitted, the standard rules for aligning
data within. an elementary item apply. (See Standard Alignment Rules.)
</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>LEVEL NUMBER</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Levels, Number</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <section>
        <title>Function</title>
        <para>
The level-number shows the hierarchy of data within a logical record.
In addition, it is used to identify entries for working storage items, linkage items.
</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Format</title>
        <cmdsynopsis>
          <arg>
            <replaceable>level-number</replaceable>
          </arg>
        </cmdsynopsis>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Syntax Rules</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
A level-number is required as the first element in each data description entry.
 </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Data description entries subordinate to a File Description entry must
have level-numbers with the values 01-49. (See THE FILE DESCRIPTION in Chapter 5).
 </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Data description entries in the Working-Storage Section and Linkage
Section must have level-numbers with the values 01-49.
 </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Rules</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The level-number 01 identifies the first entry in each record
description or a report group.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The level-number 77 is assigned to identify noncontiguous working
storage data items, noncontiguous linkage data items, and can be used
only as described by Format 1 of the data description skeleton.
(See <xref linkend="c03.skeleton"/> in this Chapter).
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Multiple level 01 entries subordinate to any given level indicator,
represent implicit redefinitions of the same area.
</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="c03.picture">
      <title>THE PICTURE CLAUSE</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Clause, PICTURE</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>PICTURE Clause</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <section>
        <title>Function</title>
        <para>
The PICTURE clause describes the general characteristics and editing
requirements of an elementary item.
</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Format</title>
        <cmdsynopsis>
          <group choice="req">
            <arg>PICTURE</arg>
            <arg>PIC</arg>
          </group>
          <arg>IS character-string</arg>
        </cmdsynopsis>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Syntax Rules</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
A PICTURE clause can be specified only at the elementary item level.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
A character-string consists of certain allowable combinations of
characters in the COBOL character set used as symbols. The allowable
combinations determine the category of the elementary item.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The maximum number of characters allowed in the character-string is 30.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The PICTURE clause must be specified for every elementary item except
an index data item, in which case use of this clause is prohibited.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
PIC is an abbreviation for PICTURE
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The asterisk when used as the zero suppression symbol and the clause
BLANK WHEN ZERO may not appear in the same entry.
</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Rules</title>
        <para>
There are five categories of data that can be described with a PICTURE
clause: alphabetic, numeric, alphanumeric, alphanumeric edited, and numeric
edited. General rules within these categories are given below:
          </para>
        <section>
          <title>Alphabetic Data Rules</title>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Alphabetic Data Rules</primary>
          </indexterm>
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
Its PICTURE character-string can only contain the symbols 'A', 'B'; and
</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
Its contents when represented in standard data format must be any
combination of the twenty-six (26) upper-case letters of the Roman
alphabet and the space from the COBOL character set.
</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Numeric Data Rules</title>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Numeric Data Rules</primary>
          </indexterm>
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
The PICTURE character-string can only contain the symbols '9', 'P',
'S', and 'V'. The number of digit positions that can be described by
the PICTURE character-string must range from 1 to 18 inclusive.
</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
If unsigned, the data in standard data format must be a combination of
      the Arabic numerals '0', '1', '2', '3', '4', '5', '6', '7', '8', and
     '9'; if signed, the item may also contain a '+', '-' or other
     representation of an operational sign.
     (See THE SIGN CLAUSE later in this Chapter).
</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Alphanumeric Data Rules</title>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Alphanumeric Data Rules</primary>
          </indexterm>
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
The PICTURE character-string is restricted to certain combinations of
the symbols 'A', 'X', '9', and the item is treated as if the
character-string contained all X's. A PICTURE character-string which
contains all A's or all 9's does not define an alphanumeric item; and
</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
The contents when represented in standard data format can consist of
any characters in the computer's character set.
</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Alphanumeric Edited Data Rules</title>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Alphanumeric Edited Data Rules</primary>
          </indexterm>
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
Its PICTURE character-string is restricted to certain combinations of
the following symbols:  'A', 'X', '9', 'B', '0', and'/' as follows:
     </para>
              <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
The character-string must contain at least one 'B' and at least
one 'X' or at least one '0' (zero) and at least one 'X' or at
least one '/' (stroke) and at least one 'X'; or
</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
The character-string must contain at least one '0' (zero) and at
least one 'A' or at least one '/' (stroke) and at least one 'A'.
</para>
                </listitem>
              </orderedlist>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
The contents when represented in standard data format are allowable
 characters in the computer's set.
</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Numeric Edited Data Rules</title>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Numeric Edited Data Rules</primary>
          </indexterm>
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
Its PICTURE character-string is restricted to certain combinations of
the symbols 'B', '/', 'P', 'V', 'Z', '0', '9', ',', '.', '*', '+', '-',
'CR', 'DB', and the currency symbol. The allowable combinations are
determined from the order of precedence of symbols and the editing
rules as follows:
     </para>
              <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
The number of digit positions that can be represented in the
PICTURE character-string must range from 1 to 18 inclusive.
</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
The character-string must contain at least one '0', 'B', '/', 'Z',
'*', '+', ',', '.', '-', 'CR', 'DB', or currency symbol.
</para>
                </listitem>
              </orderedlist>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
The contents of the character positions of these symbols that are
allowed to represent a digit in standard data format, must be one of the numerals.
</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Elementary Item Size</title>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Elementary Item Size Rules</primary>
          </indexterm>
          <para>
The size of an elementary item, where size means the number of
character positions occupied by the elementary item in standard data format,
is determined by the number of allowable symbols that represent character
positions. An integer which is enclosed in parentheses following the symbols
'A', ',', 'X', '9', 'P', 'Z', '*', 'B', '/', '0', '+', '-', or the currency
symbol indicates the number of consecutive occurrences of the symbol. Note
that the following symbols may appear only once in a given PICTURE: 'S',
'V', '.', 'CR', and 'DB'.
</para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Symbols Used</title>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Symbols Used Rules</primary>
          </indexterm>
          <para>
The functions of the symbols used to describe an elementary item are
   explained as follows:
</para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>A -</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
Each 'A' in the character-string represents a character position which
can contain only a letter of the alphabet or a space.
        </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>B -</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>Each 'B' in the character-string represents a character position into
which the space character will be inserted.
        </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>P -</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>Each 'P' indicates an assumed decimal scaling position and is used to
specify the location of an assumed decimal point when the point is not
within the number that appears in the data item. The scaling position
character 'P' is not counted in the size of the data item. Scaling
position characters are counted in determining the maximum number of
digit positions (18) in numeric edited items or numeric items. The
scaling position character 'P' can appear only to the left or right as
a continuous string of 'P's within a PICTURE description; since the
scaling position character 'P' implies an assumed decimal point (to the
left of 'P's if 'P's are leftmost PICTURE characters and to the right
if 'P's are rightmost PICTURE characters), the assumed decimal point
symbol 'V' is redundant as either the leftmost or rightmost character
within such a PICTURE description. The character 'P' and the insertion
character '.' (period) cannot both occur in the same PICTURE
character-string. If, in any operation involving conversion of data
from one form of internal representation to another, the data item
being converted is described with the PICTURE character 'P', each digit
position described by a 'P' is considered to contain the value zero,
and the size of the data item is considered to include the digit
positions so described.
</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>S -</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>  The letter 'S' is used in a character-string to indicate the presence,
but neither the representation nor, necessarily, the position of an
operational sign; it must be written as the leftmost character in the
PICTURE. The s is not counted in determining the size (in terms of
standard data format characters) of the elementary item unless the
entry is subject to a SIGN clause which specifies the optional SEPARATE
CHARACTER phrase. (See the SIGN Clause in this Chapter.)
</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>V -</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
The 'V' is used in a character-string to indicate the location of the
assumed decimal point and may only appear once in a character-string.
The 'V' does not represent a character position and therefore is not
counted in the size of the elementary item. When the assumed decimal
point is to the right of the rightmost symbol in the string the 'V' is
        redundant.
        </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>X -</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>
Each 'X' in the character-string is used to represent a character
position which contains any allowable character from the computer's
character set.
</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Z -</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>  Each 'Z' in a character-string may only be used to represent the
leftmost numeric character positions which will be replaced by a space
character when the contents of that character position is zero. Each
'Z' is counted in the size of the item.
</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>9 -</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>  Each '9' in the character-string represents a character position which
contains a numeral and is counted in the size of the item.
</para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>0 -</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>  Each '0' (zero) in the character-string represents a character position
     into which the numeral zero will be inserted. The '0' is counted in
     the size of the item.
        </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>/ -</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>  Each '/' (stroke) in the character-string represents a character
     position into which the stroke character will be inserted. The '/' is
     counted in the size of the item.
        </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>, -</term>
              <listitem>
                <para> Each ',' (comma) in the character-string represents a character
     position into which the character ','  will be inserted. This character
     position is counted in the size of the item. The insertion character
     ',' must not be the last character in the PICTURE character-string.
        </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>. -</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>The character '.' (period) in the character-string is an editing symbol
     which represents the decimal point for alignment purposes and in
     addition, represents a character position into which the character '.'
     will be inserted. The character '.' is counted in the size of the
     item. For a given program the functions of the period and comma are
     exchanged if the clause DECIMAL-POINT IS COMMA is stated in the
     SPECIAL-NAMES paragraph. In this exchange the rules for the period
     apply to the comma and the rules for the comma apply to the period
     wherever they appear in a PICTURE clause. The insertion character '.'
     must not be the last character in the PICTURE character-string.
        </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>+, -, CR, DB -</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>These symbols are used as editing sign control symbols. When
                used, they represent the character position into which the
                editing sign control symbol will be placed. The symbols are
                mutually exclusive in any one character-string and each
                character used in the symbol is counted in determining the
                size of the data item.
        </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>* -</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>  Each '*' (asterisk) in the character-string represents a leading
     numeric character position into which an asterisk will be placed when
     the contents of that position is zero. Each '*' is counted in the size
     of the item.
        </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>cs -</term>
              <listitem>
                <para> The currency symbol in the character-string represents a character
     position into which a currency symbol is to be placed. The currency
     symbol in a character-string is represented by either the currency sign
     or by the single character specified in the CURRENCY SIGN clause in the
     SPECIAL-NAMES paragraph. The currency symbol is counted in the size of
     the item.
        </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Editing Rules</title>
        <para>
      There are two general methods of performing editing in the PICTURE
clause, either by insertion or by suppression and replacement. There are
four types of insertion editing available. They are:
</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Simple insertion</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Special insertion</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Fixed insertion</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Floating insertion</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>
      There are two types of suppression and replacement editing:
    </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Zero suppression and replacement with spaces</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Zero suppression and replacement with asterisks</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>
      The type of editing which may be performed upon an item is dependent
upon the category to which the item belongs. Table 3-1 specifies which type
of editing may be performed upon a given category.
    </para>
        <table frame="all" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
          <title>Editing Types for Data Categories</title>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Editing Types for Data Categories</primary>
          </indexterm>
          <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colwidth="2.0in" colname="c1"/>
            <colspec colwidth="2.5in" colname="c2"/>
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>CATEGORY</entry>
                <entry>TYPE OF EDITING</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Alphabetic</entry>
                <entry>Simple insertion 'B' only</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Numeric</entry>
                <entry>None</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Alphanumeric</entry>
                <entry>None</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Alphanumeric Edited</entry>
                <entry>Simple insertion '0', 'B' and '/'</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Numeric Edited</entry>
                <entry>All, but see NOTE below</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
        <note>
          <para>
Floating insertion editing and editing by zero suppression and
replacement are mutually exclusive in a PICTURE clause. Only one type
of replacement may be used with zero suppression in a PICTURE clause.
  </para>
        </note>
        <section>
          <title>Simple Insertion Editing</title>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Simple Insertion Editing Rules</primary>
          </indexterm>
          <para>
Simple Insertion Editing. The ',' (comma), 'B' (space), '0' (zero),
and '/' (stroke) are used as the insertion characters. The insertion
characters are counted in the size of the item and represent the position in
the item into which the character will be inserted.
</para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Special Insertion Editing</title>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Special Insertion Editing Rules</primary>
          </indexterm>
          <para>
Special Insertion Editing. The '.' (period) is used as the insertion
character. In addition to being an insertion character it also represents
the decimal point for alignment purposes. The insertion character used for
the actual decimal point is counted in the size of the item. The use of the
assumed decimal point, represented by the symbol 'V' and the actual decimal
point, represented by the insertion character, in the same PICTURE
character-string is disallowed. The result of special insertion editing is
the appearance of the insertion character in the item in the same position
as shown in the character-string.
</para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Fixed Insertion Editing</title>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Fixed Insertion Editing Rules</primary>
          </indexterm>
          <para>
Fixed Insertion Editing. The currency symbol and the editing sign
control symbols,'+','-', 'CR', 'DB', are the insertion characters. Only
one currency symbol and only one of the editing sign control symbols can be
used in a given PICTURE character-string. When the symbols 'CR' or 'DB' are
used they represent two character positions in determining the size of the
item and they must represent the rightmost character positions that are
counted in the size of the item. The symbol '+' or '-', when used, must be
either the leftmost or rightmost character position to be counted in the
size of the item. The currency symbol must be the leftmost character.
</para>
          <table frame="all" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
            <title>Editing Symbols in PICTURE Character-Strings</title>
            <indexterm>
              <primary>Editing Symbols</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <tgroup cols="3">
              <colspec colwidth="2in" colname="c1"/>
              <colspec colwidth="1.5in" colname="c2"/>
              <colspec colwidth="1.5in" colname="c3"/>
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry morerows="1">EDITING SYMBOL IN PICTURE CHARACTER-STRING</entry>
                  <entry namest="c2" nameend="c3">RESULT</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>DATA ITEM POSITIVE OR ZERO</entry>
                  <entry>DATA ITEM NEGATIVE</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>+</entry>
                  <entry>+</entry>
                  <entry>-</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>-</entry>
                  <entry>space</entry>
                  <entry>-</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>CR</entry>
                  <entry>2 spaces</entry>
                  <entry>CR</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>DB</entry>
                  <entry>2 spaces</entry>
                  <entry>DB</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Floating Insertion Editing</title>
          <para>
      The currency symbol and editing sign control symbols '+' or '-' are the
floating insertion characters and as such are mutually exclusive in a given
PICTURE character-string.
</para>
          <para>
      Floating insertion editing is indicated in a PICTURE character-string
by using a string of at least two of the floating insertion characters.
This string of floating insertion characters may contain any of the fixed
insertion symbols or have fixed insertion characters immediately to the
right of this string. These simple insertion characters are part of the
floating string.
</para>
          <para>
      The leftmost character of the floating insertion string represents the
leftmost limit of the floating symbol in the data item. The rightmost
character of the floating string represents the rightmost limit of the
floating symbols in the data item.
</para>
          <para>
      The second floating character from the left represents the leftmost
 limit of the numeric data that can be stored in the data item. Non-zero
 numeric data may replace all the characters at or to the right of this
 limit.
</para>
          <para>
     In a PICTURE character-string, there are only two ways of representing
floating insertion editing. One way is to represent any or all of the
leading numeric character positions on the left of the decimal point by the
insertion character. The other way is to represent all of the numeric
character positions in the PICTURE character-string by the insertion
character.
</para>
          <para>
      If the insertion characters are only to the left of the decimal point
in the PICTURE character-string, the result is that a single floating
insertion character will be placed into the character position immediately
preceding either the decimal point or the first non-zero digit in the data
represented by the insertion symbol string, whichever is farther to the left
in the PICTURE character-string. The character positions preceding the
insertion character are replaced with spaces.
</para>
          <para>
      If all numeric character positions in the PICTURE character-string are
represented by the insertion character, the result depends upon the value of
the data. If the value is zero the entire data item will contain spaces.
If the value is not zero, the result is the same as when the insertion
character is only to the left of the decimal point.
</para>
          <para>
     To avoid truncation, the minimum size of the PICTURE character-string
for the receiving data item must be the number of characters in the sending
data item, plus the number of non-floating insertion characters being edited
into the receiving data item, plus one for the floating insertion character.
</para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Zero Suppression Editing</title>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Zero-Suppression Editing Rules</primary>
          </indexterm>
          <para>
    The suppression of leading zeros in numeric character positions is
indicated by the use of the alphabetic character 'Z' or the character '*'
(asterisk) as suppression symbols in a PICTURE character-string. These
symbols are mutually exclusive in a given PICTURE character-string. Each
suppression symbol is counted in determining the size of the item. If 'Z'
is used, the replacement character will be the space and if the asterisk is
used, the replacement character will be '*'.
</para>
          <para>
      Zero suppression and replacement is indicated in a   PICTURE
character-string by using a string of one or more of the allowable symbols
to represent leading numeric character positions which are to be replaced
when the associated character position in the data contains a zero. Any of
the simple insertion characters embedded in the string of symbols or to the
immediate right of this string are part of the string.
</para>
          <para>
      In a PICTURE character-string, there are only two ways of representing
zero suppression. One way is to represent any or all of the leading numeric
character positions to the left of the decimal point by suppression symbols.
The other.way is to represent all of the numeric character positions in the
PICTURE character-string by suppression symbols.
</para>
          <para>
      If the suppression symbols appear only to the left of the decimal
point, any leading zero in the data which corresponds to a symbol in the
string is replaced by the replacement character. Suppression terminates at
the first non-zero digit in the data represented by the suppression symbol
string or at the decimal point, whichever is encountered first.
</para>
          <para>
     If all numeric character positions in the PICTURE character-string are
represented by suppression symbols and the value of the data is not zero,
the result is the same as if the suppression characters were only to the
left of the decimal point. If the value is zero and the suppression symbol
is 'Z', the entire data item will be spaces. If the value is zero and the
suppression symbol is '*', the data item will be all '*' except for the
actual decimal point.
</para>
          <para>
     The symbols '+', '-', '*' 'Z', and the currency symbol, when used as
floating replacement characters, are mutually exclusive within a given
character-string.
</para>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Precedence Rules</title>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>Precedence Rules</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>
     Table 3-3 shows the order of precedence when using characters as
symbols in a character-string. An 'X' at an intersection indicates that the
symbol(s) at the top of the column may precede, in a given character-string,
the symbol(s) at the left of the row. Arguments appearing in braces
indicate that the symbols are mutually exclusive. The currency symbol is
indicated by the symbol 'cs'.
</para>
        <para>
At least one of the symbols 'A', 'X', 'Z', '9' or '*', or at least two
of the symbols '+', '-' or 'cs' must be present in a PICTURE string.
</para>
        <xi:include href="table3.3.xml"/>
        <para>
In Table 3-3, non-floating insertion symbols '+' and '-', floating
insertion symbols 'Z', '*' '+', '-', and 'cs', and other symbol 'P' appear
twice in the PICTURE character precedence chart.  The leftmost column and
uppermost row for each symbol represents its use to the left of the decimal
point position.   The second appearance of symbol in the row and column
represents its use to the right of the decimal point position.
</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>THE REDEFINES CLAUSE</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Clause, REDEFINES</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>REDEFINES Clause</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <section>
        <title>Function</title>
        <para>
The REDEFINES clause allows the same computer storage area to be
described by different data description entries.
</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Format</title>
        <cmdsynopsis>
          <arg><replaceable>level-number</replaceable><replaceable>data-name-1</replaceable>; REDEFINES <replaceable>data-name-2</replaceable></arg>
        </cmdsynopsis>
        <note>
          <para>
Level-number, data-name-1 are shown in the above format to improve
clarity. Level-number and data-name-1 are not part of the REDEFINES clause.
            </para>
        </note>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Syntax Rules</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The REDEFINES clause, when specified, must immediately follow data-name-1.
 </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The level-numbers of data-name-1 and data-name-2 must be identical.
 </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
This clause must not be used in level 01 entries in the File Section.
      (See General Rule 2 of THE DATA RECORDS CLAUSE in Chapter 5).
 </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
This clause must not be used in level 01 entries in the Communication
      Section.
 </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The data description entry for data-name-2 cannot contain an OCCURS clause.
Neither the original definition nor the redefinition can
include an item whose size is variable as defined in the OCCURS clause.
(See THE OCCURS CLAUSE in Chapter 4).
 </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
No entry having a level-number numerically lower than the level-number
of data-name-2 and data-name-1 may occur between the data description
entries of data-name-2 and data-name-1.
 </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Rules</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Redefinition starts at data-name-2 and ends when a level-number less
than or equal to that of data-name-2 is encountered.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
When the level-number of data-name-1 is other than 01, it must specify
      the same number of character positions that the data item referenced by
      data-name-2 contains. It is important to observe that the REDEFINES
      clause specifies the redefinition of a storage area, not of the data
      items occupying the area.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Multiple redefinitions of the same character positions are permitted.
   The entries giving the new descriptions of the character positions must
   follow the entries defining the area being redefined, without
   intervening entries that define new character positions. Multiple
   redefinitions of the same character positions must all use the
   data-name of the entry that originally defined the area.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The entries giving the new description of the character positions must
   not contain any VALUE clauses.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Multiple level 01 entries subordinate to any given level indicator
   represent implicit redefinitions of the same area.
</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>THE SIGN CLAUSE</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Clause, SIGN</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>SIGN Clause</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <section>
        <title>Function</title>
        <para>
The SIGN clause specifies the position and the mode of representation
of the operational sign when it is necessary to describe these properties explicitly.
</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Format</title>
        <cmdsynopsis>
          <arg choice="opt">SIGN IS</arg>
          <group choice="req">
            <arg>LEADING</arg>
            <arg>TRAILING</arg>
          </group>
          <arg choice="opt">SEPARATE CHARACTER</arg>
        </cmdsynopsis>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Syntax Rules</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The SIGN clause may be specified only for a numeric data description
entry whose PICTURE contains the character 'S', or a group item
containing at least one such numeric data description entry.
 </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The numeric data description entries to which the SIGN clause applies
must be described as USAGE IS DISPLAY.
 </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
At most one SIGN clause may apply to any given numeric data description entry.
 </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
If the CODE-SET clause is specified, any signed numeric data
description entries associated with that file description entry must be
described with the SIGN IS SEPARATE clause.
 </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Rules</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The optional SIGN clause, if present, specifies the position and the
mode of representation of the operational sign for the numeric data
description entry to which it applies, or for each numeric data
description entry subordinate to the group to which it applies. Th,
SIGN clause applies only to numeric data description entries whose
PICTURE contains the character 'S'; the 'S' indicates the presence of,
but neither the representation nor, necessarily, the position of the
operational sign.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
A numeric data description entry whose picture contains the character
'S', but to which no optional SIGN clause applies, has an operational
sign, but neither the representation nor, necessarily, the position of
the operational sign is specified by the character 'S' In this
(default) case, general rules 3 through 5 do not apply to such signed
numeric data items. The representation of the default operational sign
is defined in Chapter 2, <xref linkend="c02.charrep"/>.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
If the optional SEPARATE CHARACTER phrase is not present, then:
</para>
            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
The operational sign will be presumed to be associated with the
leading (or, respectively, trailing) digit position of the
elementary numeric data item.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
The letter 'S' in a PICTURE character-string is not counted in
determining the size of the item (in terms of standard data format characters).
</para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
If the optional SEPARATE CHARACTER phrase is present,  then:
</para>
            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
The operational sign will be presumed to be the leading
(or, respectively, trailing) character position of the elementary
numeric data item; this character position is not a digit position.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
The letter 'S' in a PICTURE character-string is counted in
determining the size of the item (in terms of standard data format characters).
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
The operational signs for positive and negative are the standard
data format characters '+' and '-', respectively.
</para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Every numeric data description entry whose PICTURE contains the
character 'S' is a signed numeric data description entry. If a SIGN
clause applies to such an entry and conversion is necessary for
   purposes of computation or comparisons, conversion takes place
   automatically.
</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>THE SYNCHRONIZED CLAUSE</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>SYNCHRONIZED Clause</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Clause, SYNCHRONIZED</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <section>
        <title>Function</title>
        <para>
The SYNCHRONIZED clause specifies the alignment of an elementary item
on the natural boundaries of the computer memory.
</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Format</title>
        <cmdsynopsis>
          <group choice="req">
            <arg>SYNCHRONIZED</arg>
            <arg>SYNC</arg>
          </group>
          <arg choice="opt">
            <group choice="req">
              <arg>LEFT</arg>
              <arg>RIGHT</arg>
            </group>
          </arg>
        </cmdsynopsis>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Syntax Rules</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
This clause may only appear with an elementary item.
 </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
SYNC is an abbreviation for SYNCHRONIZED.
 </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Rules</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <phrase role="extension">The SYNCHRONIZED clause is accepted for documentation purposes only.</phrase>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
This clause specifies that the subject data item is to be aligned in
the computer such that no other data item occupies any of the character
positions between the leftmost and rightmost natural boundaries
delimiting this data item. If the number of character positions
required to store this data item is less than the number of character
positions between those natural boundaries, the unused character
positions (or portions thereof) must not be used for any other data
item. Such unused character positions, however, are included in:
      </para>
            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
The size of any group item(s)  to which the elementary item
belongs; and
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
The character positions redefined when this data item is the
object of a REDEFINES clause.
</para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
SYNCHRONIZED not followed by either RIGHT or LEFT specifies that the
elementary item is to be positioned between natural boundaries in such
a way as to effect efficient utilization of the elementary data item.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
SYNCHRONIZED LEFT specifies that the elementary item is to be
positioned such that it will begin at the left character position of
the natural boundary in which the elementary item is placed.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
SYNCHRONIZED RIGHT specifies that the elementary item is to be
positioned such that it will terminate on the right character position
of the natural boundary i.n which the elementary item is placed.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Whenever a SYNCHRONIZED item is referenced in the source program, the
original size of the item, as shown in the PICTURE clause, is used in
determining any action that depends on size, such as justification,
truncation or overflow.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
If the data description of an item contains the SYNCHRONIZED clause and
an operational sign, the sign of the item appears in the normal
operational sign position, regardless of whether the item is
SYNCHRONIZED LEFT or SYNCHRONIZED RIGHT.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
When the SYNCHRONIZED clause is specified in a data description entry
of a data item that also contains an OCCURS clause, or in a data
description entry of a data item subordinate to a data description
entry that contains an OCCURS clause, then:
</para>
            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
Each occurrence of the data item is SYNCHRONIZED.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
Any implicit FILLER generated for other data items within that
same table are generated tor each occurrence of those data items.
</para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
This clause is hardware dependent.
</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>THE USAGE CLAUSE</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Clause, USAGE</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>USAGE Clause</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <section>
        <title>Function</title>
        <para>
    The USAGE clause specifies the format of a data item in the computer storage.
    </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Format</title>
        <cmdsynopsis>
          <arg choice="opt">USAGE IS</arg>
          <group choice="req">
            <arg>COMPUTATIONAL</arg>
            <arg>COMP</arg>
            <arg>DISPLAY</arg>
            <arg>COMPUTATIONAL-3</arg>
            <arg>COMP-3</arg>
          </group>
        </cmdsynopsis>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Syntax Rules</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The PICTURE character-string of a COMPUTATIONAL or COMPUTATIONAL-3 item
can contain only '9's, the operational sign character 'S', the implied
decimal point character 'V', one or more 'P's.
(See <xref linkend="c03.picture"/> earlier in this Chapter).
 </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
COMP is an abbreviation for COMPUTATIONAL.
 </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Rules</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The USAGE clause can be written at any level. If the USAGE clause is
written at group level, it applies to each elementary item in the
group. The USAGE clause of an elementary item cannot contradict the
USAGE clause of a group to which the item belongs.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
This clause specifies the manner in which a data item is represented in
the storage of a computer. It does not affect the use of the data
item, although the specifications for some statements in the Procedure
Division may restrict the USAGE clause of the operands referred to.
The USAGE clause may affect the radix or type of character
representation of the item.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
A COMPUTATIONAL or COMPUTATIONAL-3 item is capable of representing a
value to be used in computations and must be numeric. If a group item
is described as COMPUTATIONAL(-3), the elementary items in the group
are COMPUTATIONAL(-3). The group item itself is not COMPUTATIONAL(-3)
and cannot be us ed in computations.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The USAGE IS DISPLAY clause indicates that the format of the data is a standard data format.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
If the USAGE clause is not specified for an elementary item, or for any
group to which the item belongs, the usage is implicitly DISPLAY.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Space requirements for the various USAGE storage options are given
under <xref linkend="c02.charrep"/> in Chapter 2.
    </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>THE VALUE CLAUSE</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>VALUE Clause</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Clause, VALUE</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <section>
        <title>Function</title>
        <para>
     The VALUE clause defines the value of constants, the initial value of
working storage items, the initial value of data items in the Communication
Section.
</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Format</title>
        <cmdsynopsis>
          <command>VALUE</command>
          <arg choice="plain">is literal</arg>
        </cmdsynopsis>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Syntax Rules</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The VALUE clause cannot be stated for any items whose size is variable.
(See THE OCCURS CLAUSE in Chapter 4).
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
A signed numeric literal must have associated with it a signed numeric
PICTURE character-string.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
All numeric literal in a VALUE clause of an item must have a value
which is within the range of values indicated by the PICTURE clause,
and must not have a value which would require truncation of nonzero
digits. Nonnumeric literals in a VALUE clause of an item must not
exceed the size indicated by the PICTURE clause.
     </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Rules</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The VALUE clause must not conflict with other clauses in the data
description of the item or in the data description within the hierarchy
of the item. The following rules apply:
</para>
            <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
              <listitem>
                <para>
If the category of the item is numeric, all literals in the VALUE
clause must be numeric. If the literal defines the value of a
working storage item, the literal is aligned in the data item
according to the standard alignment rules. (See Standard Alignment Rules in Chapter 2).
     </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
If the category of the item is alphabetic, alphanumeric,
alphanumeric edited or numeric edited, all literals in the VALUE
clause must be nonnumeric literals. The literal is aligned in the
data item as if the data item had been described as alphanumeric.
(See STANDARD ALIGNMENT RULES in Chapter 2). Editing characters
in the PICTURE clause are included in determining the size of the
data item (see <xref linkend="c03.picture"/> earlier in this Chapter) but
have,no effect on initialization of the data item. Therefore, the
VALUE for an edited item is presented in an edited form.
     </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
Initialization takes place independent of any BLANK WHEN ZERO or
JUSTIFIED clause that may be specified.
     </para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Data Description Entries</title>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>Data Description, Entries</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>
Rules governing the use of the VALUE clause differ with the respective
sections of the Data Division:
</para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The VALUE clause cannot be used in the File Section.
     </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
In the Working-Storage Section, the VALUE clause may be used to specify
the initial value of a data item; in which case the clause causes the
item to assume the specified value at the start of the object program.
If the VALUE clause is not used in an item's description, the initial
value is undefined.
     </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The VALUE clause cannot be used in the Linkage Section.
     </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The VALUE clause must not be stated in a data description entry that
contains an OCCURS clause, or in an entry that is subordinate to an
entry containing an OCCURS clause. (See THE OCCURS CLAUSE in Chapter 4).
     </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The VALUE clause must not be stated in a data description entry that
contains a REDEFINES clause, or in an entry that is subordinate to an
entry containing a REDEFINES clause.
     </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
If the VALUE clause is used in an entry at the group level, the literal
must be a figurative constant or a nonnumeric literal, and the group
area is initialized without consideration for the individual elementary
or group items contained within this group. The VALUE clause cannot be
stated at the subordinate levels within this group.
     </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The VALUE clause must not be written for a group containing items with
descriptions, including JUSTIFIED, SYNCHRONIZED, or USAGE (other than
USAGE IS DISPLAY).
     </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>PROCEDURE DIVISION IN THE NUCLEUS</title>
    <section>
      <title>CONDITIONAL EXPRESSIONS</title>
      <para>
         Conditional expressions identify conditions that art, tested to enable
  the object program to select between alternate paths of control depending
 upon the truth value of the condition. Conditional expressions are
 specified in the IF and PERFORM statements. There are two categories of
 conditions associated with conditional expressions: simple conditions and
  relation conditions. Each may be enclosed within any number of paired
 parentheses, in which case its category is not changed.
</para>
      <section>
        <title>Simple Conditions</title>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>Simple Conditions</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>Conditions, Simple</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>
         The simple conditions are the relation, class, switch-status,
  conditions. A simple condition has a truth value of 'true' or 'false'. The
  inclusion in parentheses of simple conditions does not change the simple
  truth value.
</para>
        <section>
          <title>Relation Condition</title>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Conditions, Relation</primary>
          </indexterm>
          <para>
         A relation condition causes a comparison of two operands, each of which
 may be the data item referenced by an identifier, a literal. A relation
  condition has a truth value of 'true' if the relation exists between the
  operands. Comparison of two numeric operands is permitted regardless of the
  formats specified in their respective USAGE clauses. However, for all other
  comparisons the operands must have the same usage. If either of the
  operands is a group item, the nonnumeric comparison rules apply.
  </para>
          <para>
The general format of a relation condition is as follows:
</para>
          <cmdsynopsis>
            <group choice="req">
              <arg>identifier-1</arg>
              <arg>literal-1</arg>
            </group>
            <group choice="req">
              <arg>IS [NOT] GREATER THAN</arg>
              <arg>IS [NOT] LESS THAN</arg>
              <arg>IS [NOT] EQUAL TO</arg>
              <arg>IS [NOT] &gt;</arg>
              <arg>IS [NOT] &lt;</arg>
              <arg>IS [NOT] =</arg>
            </group>
            <group choice="req">
              <arg>identifier-2</arg>
              <arg>literal-2</arg>
            </group>
          </cmdsynopsis>
          <note>
            <para>
The required relational characters '&lt;', '&gt;' and '=' are not
underlined to avoid confusion with other symbols such as '&#x2265;'
(Greater than or equal to)
</para>
          </note>
          <para>
 The first operand (identifier-1 or literal-1) is called the subject of
  the condition;    the second operand (identifier-2 or literal-2) is called the
  object of the condition. The relation condition must contain at least one
  reference to a variable.
  </para>
          <para>
The relational operator specifies the type of comparison to be made in
  a relation condition. a space must precede and follow each reserved word
  comprising the relational operator. When used, 'NOT' and the next key word
  or relation character are one relational operator that defines the
  comparison to be executed for truth value; e.g., 'NOT EQUAL' is a truth test
  for an 'unequal'.
  </para>
          <para>
Comparison 'NOT GREATER' is a truth test for an 'equal' or 'less'
comparison. The meaning of the relational operators is as shown in Table 3-4.
</para>
          <table frame="all" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
            <title>Relational Operators</title>
            <tgroup cols="2">
              <colspec colname="c1"/>
              <colspec colname="c2"/>
              <thead>
                <row>
                  <entry>Meaning</entry>
                  <entry>Relational Operator</entry>
                </row>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry morerows="1">Greater than or not greater than</entry>
                  <entry>IS [NOT] GREATER THAN</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>IS [NOT]  &gt;</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry morerows="1">Less than or not less than</entry>
                  <entry>IS [NOT] LESS THAN</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>IS [NOT] &lt;</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry morerows="1">Equal to or not equal to</entry>
                  <entry>IS [NOT] EQUAL TO</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry>IS [NOT] =</entry>
                </row>
                <row>
                  <entry namest="c1" nameend="c2">The required relational characters '&gt;', '&amp;', and '=' are not
underlined to avoid confusion with other symbols such as '&#x2265;' (Greater than or equal to).</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table>
          <section>
            <title>Comparison of Numeric Operands:</title>
            <indexterm>
              <primary>Comparison of Numeric</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>
For operands whose class is numeric a
comparison is made with respect to the algebraic value of the operands. The
length of the literal, in terms of number of digits represented, is not
significant. Zero is considered a unique value regardless of the sign.
Comparison of these operands is permitted regardless of the manner in which
their usage is described. Unsigned numeric operands are considered positive
for purposes of comparison.
</para>
          </section>
          <section>
            <title>Comparison of Nonnumeric Operands:</title>
            <indexterm>
              <primary>Comparison of Nonnumeric</primary>
            </indexterm>
            <para>
For nonnumeric operands, or one numeric
and one nonnumeric operand, a comparison is made with respect to a specified
collating sequence of characters (see The OBJECT-COMPUTER Paragraph in this
Chapter). If one of the operands is specified as numeric, it must be an
integer data item or an integer literal and:
</para>
            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
If the nonnumeric operand is an elementary data item or a nonnumeric
literal, the numeric operand is treated as though it were moved to an
elementary alphanumeric data item of the same size as the numeric data
item (in terms of standard data format characters), and the contents of
this alphanumeric data item were then compared to the nonnumeric
operand.    (See THE MOVE STATEMENT in this Chapter, and the PICTURE
Character 'P' under the heading Symbols Used earlier in this Chapter).
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
If the numeric operand is a group item, the numeric operand is treated
as though it were moved to a group item of the same size as the numeric
data item (in terms of standard data format characters), and the
contents of this group item were then compared to the nonnumeric
operand.    (See THE MOVE STATEMENT in this Chapter, and the PICTURE
character 'P' under the Heading Symbols Used earlier in this Chapter).
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
A non-integer numeric operand cannot be compared to a  nonnumeric operand.
</para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <para>
     The size of an operand is the total number of standard data format
characters in the operand. Numeric and nonnumeric operands may be compared
only when their usage is the same.
</para>
            <para>
     There are two cases to consider:
</para>
            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
Operands of equal size - If the operands are of equal size, comparison
effectively proceeds by comparing characters in corresponding character
positions starting from the high order end and continuing until either
a pair of unequal characters is encountered or the low order end of the
operand is reached, whichever comes first. The operands are determined
to be equal if all pairs of characters compare equally through the last
pair, when the low order end is reached.
</para>
                <para>
The first encountered pair of unequal characters is compared to determine
their relative position in the collating sequence. The operand
that contains the character that is positioned higher in the collating
sequence is considered to be the greater operand.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
Operands of unequal size - If the operands are of unequal size,
comparison proceeds as though the shorter operand were extended on the
right by sufficient spaces to make the operands of equal size.
</para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </section>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Class Condition</title>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Class Condition</primary>
          </indexterm>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Conditions, Class</primary>
          </indexterm>
          <para>
The class condition determines whether the operand is numeric, that is,
consists entirely of the characters '0', '1', '2', '3', ...,   '9', with or
without the operational sign, or alphabetic, that is, consists entirely of
the characters 'A', 'B', 'C', ..., 'Z', space. The general format for the
class condition is as follows:
</para>
          <cmdsynopsis>
            <arg>identifier</arg>
            <arg>IS</arg>
            <arg choice="opt">NOT</arg>
            <group choice="req">
              <arg>NUMERIC</arg>
              <arg>ALPHABETIC</arg>
            </group>
          </cmdsynopsis>
          <para>
The usage of the operand being tested must be described as display.
When used, 'NOT' and the next key word specify one class condition that
defines the class test to be executed for truth value; e.g. 'NOT NUMERIC'
is a truth test for determining that an operand is nonnumeric.
</para>
          <para>
     The NUMERIC test cannot be used with an item whose data description
describes the item as alphabetic or as a group item composed of elementary
items whose data description indicates the presence of operational sign(s).
If the data description of the item being tested does not indicate the
presence of an operational sign, the item being tested is determined to be
numeric only if the contents are numeric and an operational sign is not
present. If the data description of the item does indicate the presence of
an operational sign, the item being tested is determined to be numeric only
if the contents are numeric and a valid operational sign is present. Valid
operational signs for data items described with the SIGN IS SEPARATE clause
are the standard data format characters, '+' and '-'
</para>
          <para>
The ALPHABETIC test cannot be used with an item whose data description
describes the item as numeric. The item being tested is determined to be
alphabetic only if the contents consist of any combination of the alphabetic
characters 'A' thru 'Z' and the space.
</para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Switch-Status Condition</title>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Switch Status Condition</primary>
          </indexterm>
          <indexterm>
            <primary>Conditions, Switch-Status</primary>
          </indexterm>
          <para>
A switch-status condition determines the 'on' or 'off' status of an
implementor-defined switch. The implementor-name and the 'on' or 'off'
value associated with the condition must be named in the SPECIAL-NAMES
paragraph of the Environment Division. The general format for the
switch-status condition is as follows:
      </para>
          <cmdsynopsis>
            <arg>condition-name</arg>
          </cmdsynopsis>
          <para>
The result of the test is true if the switch is set to the specified
position corresponding to the condition-name.
</para>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>COMMON PHRASES AND GENERAL RULES FOR STATEMENT FORMATS</title>
      <para>
In the statement descriptions that follow, several phrases appear
frequently: the ROUNDED phrase, the SIZE ERROR phrase.
</para>
      <para>
These are described below. A resultant-identifier is that identifier
associated with a result of an arithmetic operation.
</para>
      <section xml:id="c03.rounded">
        <title>The Rounded Phrase</title>
        <para>
If, after decimal point alignment, the number of places in the fraction
of the result of an arithmetic operation is greater than the number of
places provided for the fraction of the resultant-identifier, truncation is
relative to the size provided for the resultant-identifier. When rounding
is requested the absolute value of the resultant-identifier is increased by
one whenever the most significant digit of the the excess is greater than or
equal to five.
           </para>
        <para>
When the low-order integer positions in a resultant-identifier are
represented by the character 'P' in the PICTURE for the
resultant-identifier, rounding or truncation occurs relative to the
rightmost integer position for which storage is allocated.
           </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>The Size Error Phrase</title>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>SIZE ERROR Phrase</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>
If, after decimal point alignment, the absolute value of a result
exceeds the largest value that can be contained in the associated
resultant-identifier a size error condition exists. Division by zero always
causes a size error condition. The size error condition applies only to the
final results, except in MULTIPLY and DIVIDE statements, in which case the
size error condition applies to the intermediate results as well, If the
ROUNDED phrase is specified rounding takes place before checking for size
error. When such a size error condition occurs, the subsequent action
depends on whether or not the SIZE ERROR phrase is specified as follows:
</para>
        <section>
          <title>SIZE ERROR Phrase Not Specified</title>
          <para>
When a size error condition occurs, the value of those
resultant-identifier(s) affected is undefined. Values of
resultant-identifier(s) for which no size error condition occurs are
unaffected by size errors that occur for other resultant-identifier(s)
during execution of this operation.
</para>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>SIZE ERROR Phrase Specified</title>
          <para>
When a size error condition occurs, then the values of
resultant-identifier(s) affected by the size errors are not altered.
After completion of the execution of this operation, the imperative statement in
the SIZE ERROR phrase is executed.
</para>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Arithmetic Statements</title>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>Arithmetic Statements</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>
        The arithmetic statements are the ADD, DIVIDE, MULTIPLY, and SUBTRACT
   statements. Common features are as follows:
</para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The data descriptions of the operands need not be the same; any
necessary conversion and decimal point alignment are supplied
throughout the calculation.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The maximum size of each operand is 18 decimal digits. The composite
of operands, which is a hypothetical data item resulting from the
superimposition of specified operands in a statement aligned on their
decimal points
(See <xref linkend="c03.add"/>, THE DIVIDE STATEMENT, THE MULTIPLY STATEMENT and THE SUBTRACT STATEMENT later in this Chapter)
must not contain more than 18 decimal digits.
</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Overlapping Operands</title>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>Overlapping Operands</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>
When a sending and a receiving item in an arithmetic statement or an
INSPECT, MOVE, SET, statement share a part of their storage areas, the
result of the execution of such a statement is undefined.
</para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="c03.incom">
        <title>Incompatible Data</title>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>Incompatible Data</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>
Except for the class condition (See Class Condition in this Chapter),
when the contents of a data item are referenced in the Procedure Division
and the contents of that data item are not compatible with the class
specified for that data item by its PICTURE clause, then the result of such
a reference is undefined. If a numeric display field contains one or more
spaces the spaces are usually treated as if they were zero. This may
present problems in portability if relied upon.
</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>CRT Devices</title>
        <indexterm>
          <primary>CRT Devices</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>
The CRT is driven directly by the run time system via a buffer. The
COBOL programmer moves data into and out of this buffer by means of ACCEPT
and DISPLAY statements. Each ACCEPT or DISPLAY action is relative to the
start of the CRT buffer unless POSITION is specified. The syntax is limited
to inputting to or outputting from a single data name. The data name may be
a group item and several such group items may redefine the same area of storage.
   </para>
        <para>
The use of FILLER data items in record descriptions used for input or
output to a CRT device is subject to special rules. On output, any FILLER
item in a record results in suppression of output for the character
positions it defines. On input, any FILLER item suppresses operator keying
into the character positions it defines.
</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>THE ACCEPT STATEMENT</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>ACCEPT Statement</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Statement, ACCEPT</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <section>
        <title>Function</title>
        <para>
The ACCEPT statement causes data keyed at the CRT console to be made
available to the program in a specified data item
</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Formats</title>
        <para>Format 1</para>
        <cmdsynopsis>
          <command>ACCEPT</command>
          <arg>identifier</arg>
          <arg choice="opt">FROM CONSOLE</arg>
        </cmdsynopsis>
        <para>Format 2</para>
        <cmdsynopsis>
          <command>ACCEPT</command>
          <arg>data-name-1</arg>
          <arg choice="opt">
            <arg>AT</arg>
            <group choice="req">
              <arg>data-name-2</arg>
              <arg>literal-1</arg>
            </group>
          </arg>
          <arg>FROM CRT</arg>
        </cmdsynopsis>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Syntax Rule</title>
        <para>
Literal-1 must be numeric.
</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Rules</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Format 1 is the standard ANSI ACCEPT statement
</para>
            <para>
              <phrase role="extension">Format 2 is the extended ACCEPT format.
The two formats are distinguished by their FROM phrases and the default
assumes FROM CONSOLE. The default can, however, be changed by
specifying CONSOLE IS CRT in the SPECIAL-NAMES clause so that FROM CRT
becomes the default. This changed default is not shown in the syntax
above. Note: Specifying the AT phrase implies Format 2, even if FROM CRT is omitted.</phrase>
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>
Format 1
</para>
        <orderedlist continuation="continues">
          <listitem>
            <para>
The ACCEPT statement reads one line of input data from the system
console device. This input data replaces the contents of the data item
named by the identifier.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The line of input is line-edited according to the operating system
rules for line-editing (see Operating Systems User Guide). The line is
terminated by pressing the CR (Carriage Return) key or by exceeding 120
characters in length.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
If the input line is of the same size as the receiving data item, the
transferred data is stored in the receiving data item.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
If the input line is not of the same size as the receiving data item, then:
</para>
            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
If the size of the receiving data item exceeds the size of the
input line, the transferred data is stored aligned to the left in
the receiving data item and the data item is filled with trailing spaces.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
If the size of the transferred data exceeds 120 bytes, only the
first 120 characters of the input line are stored in the receiving
data item. The remaining characters of the input line which do
not fit into the receiving data item are ignored.
  </para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>
          <phrase role="extension">
Format 2</phrase>
        </para>
        <orderedlist continuation="continues">
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <phrase role="extension">
The ACCEPT statement causes the transfer of data from the CRT to
  data-name-1. The contents of data-name-1 is replaced by this data.
</phrase>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <phrase role="extension">
data-name-1 is taken as a definition of the screen area in which elementary
data items correspond to areas on the screen into which the operator can key
information. FILLER fields correspond to areas on the screen which are
inaccessible to the operator. data-name-1 must not be subscripted.
              </phrase>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <phrase role="extension">
Elementary data items within data-name-1 may be alphanumeric, numeric usage
display, or edited. Numeric items are treated as two separate
integer numeric fields and edited fields are treated as Alphanumeric fields
except as described in rule 12.
              </phrase>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <phrase role="extension">
AT data-name-2 or literal-1 defines the position on the screen of the leftmost
character of the data. Either form must refer to a PIC 9999 field.
The most significant 99 is taken as the line count in the range one to the
maximum lines on the user screen. The least significant 99 is taken as a
character position in the range one to the maximum positions allowed by the
screen width of the user CRT.
              </phrase>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <phrase role="extension">
data-name-1 may refer to a record, group or elementary item, but it may not
be subscripted. REDEFINES may be used within data-name-1, in which case
the first description of the data is used and subsequent descriptions are
ignored. OCCURS and nested OCCURS may also be used with the effect that
the repeated data-item is expanded into the full number of items it occurs and
one definition is thus automatically repeated for many fields.
              </phrase>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <phrase role="extension">
Immediately upon execution of the ACCEPT statement the cursor is
positioned to the CRT location corresponding to the left-most non-FILLER
character position in data-name-1. Alternatively, when CURSOR is
specified in the SPECIAL-NAMES paragraph, the cursor is positioned at
the position held in the CURSOR data-name in the same format as the screen
position is held in data-name-2. If the cursor data-name has the value SPACE
or ZERO, the effect is as if the CURSOR was not specified; if a valid screen
position is specified that is not within a non-FILLER item, the cursor
is positioned at the nearest non-FILLER character position.
CURSOR data-name holds the last cursor position at the end of execution
of an ACCEPT statement.
              </phrase>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <phrase role="extension">
If FROM CRT is not specified, the default is FROM CONSOLE (see rule 1 above).
              </phrase>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <phrase role="extension">
As the operator keys characters, the cursor moves to the right one
character position at a time in locations corresponding to data fields.
The operator always keys into the current cursor position. At the end
of a line the cursor moves down one line and to the leftmost non-FILLER
character position.
</phrase>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <phrase role="extension">
If the data item is integer numeric, only numeric characters (0 - 9)
will be accepted into that item. Keying the decimal point character
(. or , as specified in the DECIMAL POINT phrase) when accepting a
numeric item causes the item to be right justified and zero-filled from the left.
</phrase>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <phrase role="extension">
When the cursor location reaches a position corresponding to a FILLER
item in a data-name, it immediately skips to the next non-FILLER
character position, or if there is no such position remaining in the
portion of the CRT specified by the data-name, it remains in its current position.
</phrase>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <phrase role="extension">
The operator can terminate input by pressing the CR (Carriage Return)
key at which time control is passed to the next statement after ACCEPT.
Before control is passed to the next statement the following takes place:
</phrase>
            </para>
            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <phrase role="extension">
The numeric value of each numeric-edited data-field is formed
internally from only the keyed characters 0 to 9, +, -, . or , and
then moved back to the numeric-edited field with the ANSI PICTURE
editing applied. The field may thus be different to that shown on
the CRT just before the Carriage Return was pressed.
</phrase>
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <phrase role="extension">
When CURSOR IS is specified in the SPECIAL-NAMES paragraph, the
cursor position when the Carriage Return is pressed is
returned in the data-name specified by the CURSOR IS clause,
except when its value at the start of the ACCEPT function caused
it the be treated as unspecified.
</phrase>
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <phrase role="extension">
Before keying CR, the operator can reposition the cursor to
overwrite data already keyed or to skip character positions by use
of the character position keys shown in Table 3-5.
</phrase>
            </para>
            <para>
              <phrase role="extension">
NOTE: The actual key identification and functions shown in this table
 vary according to the CRT used and the way it is configured
 (See the <citetitle pubwork="book">CIS COBOL Operating Guide</citetitle>).
</phrase>
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <table>
          <title>Cursor Repositioning Keys</title>
          <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colwidth="1.0in" colname="c1"/>
            <colspec colwidth="4in" colname="c2"/>
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Key</entry>
                <entry>Function</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>&#x2190;</entry>
                <entry>Backs up the cursor one position</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>&#x2191;</entry>
                <entry>Backs up the cursor to the start of the non-FILLER field prior to the current cursor position.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>&#x2193;</entry>
                <entry>Moves the cursor on to the start of the next non-FILLER field in advance of the current cursor position.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>&#x2192;</entry>
                <entry>Moves the cursor on one position without overwriting existing contents.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>&#x2196;</entry>
                <entry>Moves the cursor back to the start of the first non-FILLER field in the CRT area corresponding to data-name-1.</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="c03.add">
      <title>THE ADD STATEMENT</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>ADD Statement</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Statement, ADD</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <section>
        <title>Function</title>
        <para>
     The ADD statement causes two or more numeric operands to be summed and
the result to be stored.
</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Format</title>
        <para>
Format 1
        </para>
        <cmdsynopsis>
          <command>ADD</command>
          <group choice="req">
            <arg>identifier-1</arg>
            <arg>literal-1</arg>
          </group>
          <arg choice="opt" rep="repeat">
            <arg>,</arg>
            <group choice="req">
              <arg>identifier-2</arg>
              <arg>literal-2</arg>
            </group>
          </arg>
          <arg>TO identifier-m</arg>
          <arg choice="opt">ROUNDED</arg>
          <sbr/>
          <arg choice="opt" rep="repeat">, identifier-n<arg choice="opt">ROUNDED</arg></arg>
          <arg choice="opt">; ON SIZE ERROR imperative-statement</arg>
        </cmdsynopsis>
        <para>
Format 2
        </para>
        <cmdsynopsis>
          <command>ADD</command>
          <group choice="req">
            <arg>identifier-1</arg>
            <arg>literal-1</arg>
          </group>
          <arg>,</arg>
          <group choice="req">
            <arg>identifier-2</arg>
            <arg>literal-2</arg>
          </group>
          <arg choice="opt" rep="repeat">
            <arg>,</arg>
            <group choice="req">
              <arg>identifier-3</arg>
              <arg>literal-3</arg>
            </group>
          </arg>
          <arg>GIVING identifier-m</arg>
          <arg choice="opt">ROUNDED</arg>
          <arg choice="opt">, identifier-n <arg choice="opt">ROUNDED</arg></arg>
          <arg choice="opt">; ON SIZE ERROR imperative-statement</arg>
        </cmdsynopsis>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Syntax Rules</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
In Formats 1 and 2, each identifier must refer to an elementary numeric
item, except that in Format 2 each identifier following the word GIVING
must refer to either an elementary numeric item or an elementary
numeric edited item.
 </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Each literal must be a numeric literal.
 </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The composite of operands must not contain more than 18 digits
(see The Arithmetic Statements in this Chapter).
     </para>
            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
 In Format 1 the composite of operands is determined by using all
          of the operands in a given statement.
 </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
In Format 2 the composite of operands is determined by using all
          of the operands in a given statement excluding the data items that
          follow the word GIVING.
 </para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Rules</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
See <xref linkend="c03.rounded"/>, The Size Error Phrase,
The Arithmetic Statements, Overlapping Operands and <xref linkend="c03.incom"/> in this Chapter.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
If Format 1 is used, the values of the operands preceding the word TO
are added together, then the sum is added to the current value of
identifier-m storing the result immediately into identifier-m.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
If Format 2 is used, the value of the operands preceding the word
GIVING are added together, then the sum is stored as the new value of
identifier-m, the resultant identifiers.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The compiler ensures that enough places are carried so as not to lose
any significant digits during execution.
</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>THE ALTER STATEMENT</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>ALTER Statement</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Statement, ALTER</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <section>
        <title>Function</title>
        <para>
       The ALTER statement modifies a predetermined sequence of operations.
       </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Format</title>
        <cmdsynopsis>
          <command>ALTER</command>
          <arg>procedure-name-1 TO</arg>
          <arg choice="opt">PROCEED TO</arg>
          <arg>procedure-name-2</arg>
        </cmdsynopsis>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Syntax Rule</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Procedure-name-1 is the name of a paragraph that contains a single
sentence consisting of a GO TO statement without the DEPENDING phrase.
 </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Procedure-name-2 is the name of a paragraph or section in the Procedure Division.
        </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Rule</title>
        <para>
       Execution of the ALTER statement modifies the GO TO statement in the
paragraph named procedure-name-1, so that subsequent executions of the
modified GO TO statements cause transfer of control to procedure-name-2.
Modified GO TO statements in independent segments may, under some
circumstances, be returned to their initial states
(see Independent Segments in Chapter 8).
       </para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>THE DISPLAY STATEMENT</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>DISPLAY Statement</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Statement, DISPLAY</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <section>
        <title>Function</title>
        <para>
The DISPLAY statement causes data to be transferred from specified data
items to the CRT screen.
</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Formats</title>
        <para>
Format 1</para>
        <cmdsynopsis>
          <command>DISPLAY</command>
          <group choice="req">
            <arg>identifier-1</arg>
            <arg>literal-1</arg>
          </group>
          <arg choice="opt" rep="repeat">
            <arg>,</arg>
            <group choice="req">
              <arg>identifier-2</arg>
              <arg>literal-2</arg>
            </group>
          </arg>
          <arg choice="opt">UPON CONSOLE</arg>
        </cmdsynopsis>
        <para>
Format 2</para>
        <cmdsynopsis role="extension">
          <command>DISPLAY</command>
          <group choice="req">
            <arg>data-name-1</arg>
            <arg>literal-3</arg>
          </group>
          <arg choice="opt">
            <arg>AT</arg>
            <group choice="req">
              <arg>data-name-2</arg>
              <arg>literal-4</arg>
            </group>
          </arg>
          <arg>UPON</arg>
          <group choice="req">
            <arg>CRT</arg>
            <arg>CRT-UNDER</arg>
          </group>
        </cmdsynopsis>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Syntax Rules</title>
        <para>
Format 1
</para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Each literal may be any figurative constant, except ALL.
 </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
If the literal is numeric, it must be an unsigned integer.
 </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>
Format 2
</para>
        <orderedlist continuation="continues">
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <phrase role="extension">Literal-3 must be alphanumeric. Literal-4 must be numeric.</phrase>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <phrase role="extension">data-name-1 may refer to a record, group or elementary item, but it must not be subscripted.</phrase>
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Rules</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <phrase role="extension">Format 1 is the standard ANSI DISPLAY statement.</phrase>
            </para>
            <para>
              <phrase role="extension">Format 2 is the extended DISPLAY format.</phrase>
            </para>
            <para>
              <phrase role="extension">The two formats are distinguished by their UPON phrases and the default
assumes UPON CONSOLE. The default can, however, be changed by
specifying CONSOLE IS CRT in the SPECIAL-NAMES clause so the UPON CRT
becomes the default. This changed default is not shown in the syntax above.
Note: Specifying the AT phrase implies Format 2, even if the UPON phrase is omitted.</phrase>
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>
Format 1
</para>
        <orderedlist continuation="continues">
          <listitem>
            <para>
The DISPLAY statement causes the contents of each operand to be
        transferred to the CRT in the order listed as one line of output data.
 </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The size of the data transfer can be up to 132 bytes.
 </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
If a figurative constant is specified as one of the operands, only a
single occurrence of the figurative constant is displayed.
 </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
If the CRT is capable of displaying data of the same size as the data
item being output, the data item is transferred.
 </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
If the CRT is not capable of displaying data of the same size as the
     data item being transferred, one of the following applies.
</para>
            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
If the size of the data item being displayed exceeds the size of
the data that the CRT is capable of receiving in a single
transfer, the data beginning with the leftmost character is stored
aligned to the left in the receiving CRT.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
If the size of the data item that the CRT is capable of receiving
exceeds the size of the data being transferred, the transferred
data is stored aligned to the left in the receiving CRT.
</para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
When a DISPLAY statement contains more than one operand, the size of
the sending item is the sum of the sizes associated with the operands,
and the values of the operands are transferred in the sequence in which
the operands are encountered.
 </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>
Format 2
</para>
        <orderedlist continuation="continues" role="extension">
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <phrase role="extension">The DISPLAY statement is used to output data to the CRT in the screen
positions specified.</phrase>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <phrase role="extension">data-name-1 is taken as a definition of the screen area into which data
items that correspond to areas on the screen are moved. FILLER fields
correspond to areas on the screen into which data is not moved.</phrase>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <phrase role="extension">Elementary data items within data-name-1 may be alphanumeric, integer
numeric, numeric or edited.</phrase>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <phrase role="extension">AT data-name-2 or literal-4 defines the position on the screen of the
leftmost character of the. data. Either form must refer to a PIC 9999
field. The most significant 99 is taken as a line count in the range
one to the maximum number of lines on the user screen. The least
significant 99 is taken as a character position in the range one to the
maximum of characters per line on the user screen.</phrase>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <phrase role="extension">data-name-1 may refer to a record, group or elementary item, but it may
not be subscripted. REDEFINES may be used, in which case the first
description of the data is used and subsequent descriptions are
ignored. OCCURS and nested OCCURS may also be used with the effect that
the repeated data-item is expanded into the full number of times it
occurs and one definition is thus automatically repeated for many fields.</phrase>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <phrase role="extension">DISPLAY SPACE has the effect of clearing the screen at run time (i.e.
filling the whole screen with spaces). DISPLAY " " (one space
character), however, displays only one space character.</phrase>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <phrase role="extension">The CRT-UNDER phrase causes the elementary items moved to the CRT to be
displayed with the underline feature present.  This feature is
dependent on the CRT hardware functions and is not available on all makes of CRT
 (see the <citetitle pubwork="book">CIS COBOL Operating Guide</citetitle>).</phrase>
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>THE DIVIDE STATEMENT</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>DIVIDE Statement</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Statement, DIVIDE</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <section>
        <title>Function</title>
        <para>
     The DIVIDE statement divides one numeric data item into others and sets
the values of data items equal to the quotient.
</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Format</title>
        <para>
Format 1
        </para>
        <cmdsynopsis>
          <command>DIVIDE</command>
          <group choice="req">
            <arg>identifier-1</arg>
            <arg>literal-1</arg>
          </group>
          <arg>INTO</arg>
          <arg>identifier-2</arg>
          <arg choice="opt">ROUNDED</arg>
          <sbr/>
          <arg choice="opt" rep="repeat">, identifier-3 <arg choice="opt">ROUNDED</arg></arg>
          <arg choice="opt">; ON SIZE ERROR imperative-statement</arg>
        </cmdsynopsis>
        <para>
Format 2
        </para>
        <cmdsynopsis>
          <command>DIVIDE</command>
          <group choice="req">
            <arg>identifier-1</arg>
            <arg>literal-1</arg>
          </group>
          <arg>INTO</arg>
          <group choice="req">
            <arg>identifier-2</arg>
            <arg>literal-2</arg>
          </group>
          <arg>GIVING</arg>
          <arg>identifier-3</arg>
          <arg choice="opt">ROUNDED</arg>
          <arg choice="opt" rep="repeat">
            <arg>,</arg>
            <arg>identifier-4</arg>
            <arg choice="opt">ROUNDED</arg>
          </arg>
          <arg choice="opt">; ON SIZE ERROR imperative-statement</arg>
        </cmdsynopsis>
        <para>
Format 3
        </para>
        <cmdsynopsis>
          <command>DIVIDE</command>
          <group choice="req">
            <arg>identifier-1</arg>
            <arg>literal-1</arg>
          </group>
          <arg>BY</arg>
          <group choice="req">
            <arg>identifier-2</arg>
            <arg>literal-2</arg>
          </group>
          <arg>GIVING</arg>
          <arg>identifier-3</arg>
          <arg choice="opt">ROUNDED</arg>
          <arg choice="opt" rep="repeat">
            <arg>,</arg>
            <arg>identifier-4</arg>
            <arg choice="opt">ROUNDED</arg>
          </arg>
          <arg choice="opt">; ON SIZE ERROR imperative-statement</arg>
        </cmdsynopsis>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Syntax Rules</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Each identifier must refer to an elementary numeric item, except that
any identifier associated with the GIVING phrase must refer to either
an elementary numeric item or an elementary numeric edited item.
 </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Each literal must be a numeric literal.
 </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Rules</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
See <xref linkend="c03.rounded"/>, The Size Error Phrase,
The Arithmetic Statements, Overlapping Operands and <xref linkend="c03.incom"/> in this Chapter
     for a description of these functions.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
When Format is used, the value of identifier-1 or literal-1 is
divided into the value of identifier-2. The value of the dividend
(identifier-2) is replaced by this quotient.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
When Format 2 is used, the value of identifier-1 or literal-1 is
divided into identifier-2 or literal-2 and the result is stored in identifier-3.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
When Format 3 is used, the value of identifier-1 or literal-1 is
divided by the value of identifier-2 or literal-2 and the result is
stored in identifier-3.
</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>THE ENTER STATEMENT</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>ENTER Statement</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Statement, ENTER</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <section>
        <title>Function</title>
        <para>
 The ENTER statement provides a means of allowing the use of more than
one language in the same program.
</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Format</title>
        <cmdsynopsis>
          <command>ENTER</command>
          <arg>language-name</arg>
          <arg choice="opt">routine-name</arg>
        </cmdsynopsis>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Syntax Rule</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <phrase role="extension">This statement is for documentation purposes only.</phrase>
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Rule</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Access to other languages can be achieved by means of CALL.
</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>THE EXIT STATEMENT</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>EXIT Statement</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Statement, EXIT</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <section>
        <title>Function</title>
        <para>
The EXIT statement provides a common end point for a series of procedures.
     </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Format</title>
        <cmdsynopsis>
          <command>EXIT</command>
        </cmdsynopsis>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Syntax Rules</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The EXIT statement must appear in a sentence by itself.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The EXIT sentence must be the only sentence in the paragraph.
</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Rule</title>
        <para>
An EXIT statement serves only to enable the user :o assign a
procedure-name to a given point in a program. Such an EXIT statement
has no other effect on the compilation or execution of the program.
     </para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>THE GO TO STATEMENT</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>GO TO Statement</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Statement, GO TO</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <section>
        <title>Function</title>
        <para>
The GO TO statement causes control to be transferred from one part of
the Procedure Division to another.
</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Format</title>
        <para>
Format 1
</para>
        <cmdsynopsis>
          <command>GO TO</command>
          <arg choice="req">procedure-name-1</arg>
        </cmdsynopsis>
        <para>
Format-2
</para>
        <cmdsynopsis>
          <command>GO TO</command>
          <arg>procedure-name-1</arg>
          <arg choice="opt" rep="repeat">, procedure-name-2</arg>
          <arg>, procedure-name-n</arg>
          <arg>DEPENDING ON identifier</arg>
        </cmdsynopsis>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Syntax Rules</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Identifier is the name of a numeric elementary item described without
 any positions to the right of the assumed decimal point.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
When a paragraph is referenced by an ALTER statement, that paragraph
can consist only of a paragraph header followed by a Format 1 GO TO statement.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
If a GO TO statement represented by Format 1 appears in a consecutive
sequence of imperative statements within a sentence, it appears as the
last statement in that sequence.
</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Rules</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
When a GO TO statement, represented by Format 1 is executed, control is
     transferred to procedure-name-1 or to another procedure-name if the GO
     TO statement has been modified by an ALTER statement.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
When a GO TO statement represented by Format 2 is executed, control is
transferred to procedure-name-1, procedure-name-2, etc., depending on
the value of the identifier being 1, 2, ... , n. If the value of the
identifier is anything other than the positive or unsigned integers
1, 2, ..., n, then no transfer occurs and control passes to the next
statement in the normal sequence for execution.
    </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>THE IF STATEMENT</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>IF Statement</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Statement, IF</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <section>
        <title>Function</title>
        <para>
   The IF statement causes a condition to be evaluated
   (see CONDITIONAL EXPRESSIONS in this Chapter).
   The subsequent action of the object program
depends on whether the value of the condition is true or false.
</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Format</title>
        <cmdsynopsis>
          <command>IF</command>
          <arg>condition;</arg>
          <phrase role="extension">
            <arg choice="opt" role="extension">THEN</arg>
          </phrase>
          <group choice="req">
            <arg>statement-1</arg>
            <arg>NEXT SENTENCE</arg>
          </group>
          <group choice="req">
            <arg>; ELSE statement-2</arg>
            <arg>; ELSE NEXT SENTENCE</arg>
          </group>
        </cmdsynopsis>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Syntax Rules</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Statement-1 and statement-2 represent either an imperative statement or
a conditional statement, and either may be followed by a conditional statement.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The ELSE NEXT SENTENCE phrase may be omitted if it immediately precedes
the terminal period of the sentence.
</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Rules</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
When an IF statement is executed, the following transfers of control occur:
</para>
            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
If the condition is true, statement-1 is executed if specified. If
statement-1   contains a procedure branching or conditional
statement, control is explicitly transferred in accordance with
the rules of that statement. If statement-1 does not contain a
procedure branching or conditional statement, the ELSE phrase, if
specified, is ignored and control passes to the next executable sentence.
      </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
If the condition is true and the NEXT SENTENCE phrase is specified
instead of statement-1, the ELSE phrase, if specified, is ignored
and control passes to the next executable sentence.
          </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
If the condition is false, statement-1 or its surrogate NEXT
SENTENCE is ignored, and statement-2, if specified, is executed.
If statement-2 contains a procedure branching or conditional
statement, control is explicitly transferred in accordance with
the rules of that statement. If statement-2 does not contain a
procedure branching or conditional statement, control passes to
the next executable sentence. If the ELSE statement-2 phrase is
not specified, statement-1 is ignored and control passes to the
next executable sentence.
          </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
If the condition is false, and the ELSE NEXT SENTENCE phrase is
specified, statement-1 is ignored, if specified, and control
passes to the next executable sentence.
</para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Statement-1 and/or statement-2 may contain an IF statement. In this
case the IF statement is said to be nested.
</para>
            <para>
IF statements within IF statements may be considered as paired IF and
ELSE combinations, proceeding from left to right. Thus, any ELSE
encountered is considered to apply to the immediately preceding IF that has
not been already paired with an ELSE.
</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>THE INSPECT STATEMENT</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>INSPECT Statement</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Statement, INSPECT</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <section>
        <title>Function</title>
        <para>
The INSPECT statement provides the ability to tally (Format 1), replace
(Format 2), or tally and replace (Format 3) occurrences of single characters
in a data item.
</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Format</title>
        <para>
Format 1
</para>
        <cmdsynopsis>
          <command>INSPECT</command>
          <arg>identifier-1</arg>
          <arg>TALLYING</arg>
          <arg>identifier-2 FOR</arg>
          <arg>,</arg>
          <group choice="req">
            <arg>ALL</arg>
            <arg>LEADING</arg>
            <arg>CHARACTERS</arg>
          </group>
          <group choice="req">
            <arg>identifier-3</arg>
            <arg>literal-1</arg>
          </group>
          <arg choice="opt">
            <group choice="req">
              <arg>BEFORE</arg>
              <arg>AFTER</arg>
            </group>
            <arg>INITIAL</arg>
            <group choice="req">
              <arg>identifier-7</arg>
              <arg>literal-5</arg>
            </group>
          </arg>
        </cmdsynopsis>
        <para>
Format 2
</para>
        <cmdsynopsis>
          <command>INSPECT</command>
          <arg>identifier-1</arg>
          <arg>REPLACING</arg>
          <sbr/>
          <group choice="req">
            <arg>CHARACTERS BY <group><arg>identifier-6</arg><arg>literal-4</arg></group></arg>
            <arg>
              <arg>,</arg>
              <group choice="req">
                <arg>ALL</arg>
                <arg>LEADING</arg>
                <arg>FIRST</arg>
              </group>
              <arg>,</arg>
              <group choice="req">
                <arg>identifier-5</arg>
                <arg>literal-3</arg>
              </group>
              <arg>BY</arg>
              <group choice="req">
                <arg>identifier-6</arg>
                <arg>literal-4</arg>
              </group>
            </arg>
          </group>
          <sbr/>
          <arg choice="opt">
            <group choice="req">
              <arg>BEFORE</arg>
              <arg>AFTER</arg>
            </group>
            <arg>INITIAL</arg>
            <group choice="req">
              <arg>identifier-7</arg>
              <arg>literal-5</arg>
            </group>
          </arg>
        </cmdsynopsis>
        <para>
Format 3
</para>
        <cmdsynopsis>
          <command>INSPECT</command>
          <arg>identifier-1</arg>
          <arg>TALLYING</arg>
          <arg>identifier-2 FOR</arg>
          <arg>,</arg>
          <group choice="req">
            <arg>ALL</arg>
            <arg>LEADING</arg>
            <arg>CHARACTERS</arg>
          </group>
          <group choice="req">
            <arg>identifier-3</arg>
            <arg>literal-1</arg>
          </group>
          <arg choice="opt">
            <group choice="req">
              <arg>BEFORE</arg>
              <arg>AFTER</arg>
            </group>
            <arg>INITIAL</arg>
            <group choice="req">
              <arg>identifier-4</arg>
              <arg>literal-2</arg>
            </group>
          </arg>
          <sbr/>
          <arg>REPLACING</arg>
          <sbr/>
          <group choice="req">
            <arg>CHARACTERS BY <group><arg>identifier-6</arg><arg>literal-4</arg></group></arg>
            <arg>
              <arg>,</arg>
              <group choice="req">
                <arg>ALL</arg>
                <arg>LEADING</arg>
                <arg>FIRST</arg>
              </group>
              <arg>,</arg>
              <group choice="req">
                <arg>identifier-5</arg>
                <arg>literal-3</arg>
              </group>
              <arg>BY</arg>
              <group choice="req">
                <arg>identifier-6</arg>
                <arg>literal-4</arg>
              </group>
            </arg>
          </group>
          <sbr/>
          <arg choice="opt">
            <group choice="req">
              <arg>BEFORE</arg>
              <arg>AFTER</arg>
            </group>
            <arg>INITIAL</arg>
            <group choice="req">
              <arg>identifier-7</arg>
              <arg>literal-5</arg>
            </group>
          </arg>
        </cmdsynopsis>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Syntax Rules</title>
        <para>
All Formats
</para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Identifier-1 must reference either a group item or any category of
 elementary item, described (either implicitly or explicitly) as usage
 is DISPLAY.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Identifier-3 ... identifier-n must reference either an elementary
     alphabetic, alphanumeric or numeric item described (either implicitly
     or explicitly) as usage is DISPLAY.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Each literal must be nonnumeric and may be any figurative constant, except ALL.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
In Level 1, literal-1, literal-2, literal-3, literal-4, and literal-5,
     and the data items referenced by identifier-3, identifier-4,
     identifier-5, identifier-6, and identifier-7 must be one character in
     length.
</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>
Formats 1 and 3 Only
          </para>
        <orderedlist continuation="continues">
          <listitem>
            <para>
Identifier-2 must reference an elementary numeric data item.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
If either literal-1 or literal-2 is a figurative constant, the
figurative constant refers to an implicit one character data item.
</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>
Formats 2 and 3 Only
          </para>
        <orderedlist continuation="continues">
          <listitem>
            <para>
The size of the data referenced by literal-4 or identifier-6 must be
equal to the size of the data referenced by literal-3 or identifier-5.
When a figurative constant is used as literal-4, the size of the
figurative constant is equal to the size of literal-3 or the size of
the data item referenced by identifier-5.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
When the CHARACTERS phrase is used, literal-4, literal-5, or the size
of the data item referenced by identifier-6, identifier-7 must be one character in length.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
When a figurative constant is used as literal-3, the data referenced by
literal-4 or identifier-6 must be one character in length.
</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Rules</title>
        <para>
All Formats
</para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Inspection (which includes the comparison cycle, the establishment of
     boundaries for the BEFORE or AFTER phrase, and the mechanism for
     tallying and/or replacing) begins at the leftmost character position of
     the data item referenced by identifier-1, regardless of its class, and
     proceeds from left to right to the rightmost character position as
     described in general rules 4 through 6.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
For use in the INSPECT statement, the contents of the data item
referenced by identifier-1, identifier-3, identifier-4, identifier-5,
identifier-6 or identifier-7 will be treated as follows:
</para>
            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
If any of identifier-1, identifier-3, identifier-4, identifier-5,
identifier-6 or identifier-7 are described as alphanumeric, the
INSPECT statement treats the contents of each such identifier as a
character-string.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
If any of identifier-1, identifier-3, identifier-4, identifier-5,
identifier-6 or identifier-7 are described as alphanumeric edited,
numeric edited or unsigned numeric, the data item is inspected as
though it had been redefined as alphanumeric (see general rule 2a)
and the INSPECT statement had been written to reference the
redefined data item.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
If any of the identifier-1,   identifier-3,  identifier-4,
identifier-5, identifier-6 or identifier-7 are described as signed
numeric, the data item is inspected as though it had been moved to
an unsigned numeric data item of the same length and then the
rules in general rule 2b had been applied.
(See THE MOVE STATEMENT later in this Chapter).
           </para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
In general rules 4 through 11 all references to literal-1, literal-2,
literal-3, literal-4, and literal-5 apply equally to the contents of
the data item referenced by identifier-3, identifier-4, identifier-5,
identifier-6, and identifier-7, respectively.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
During inspection of the contents of the data item referenced by
identifier-1, each properly matched occurrence of literal-1 is tallied
(Formats 1 and 3) and/or each properly matched occurrence of literal-3
is replaced by literal-4 (Formats 2 and 3). Data items to be
referenced by the INSPECT verb should be placed such that they Lie
within the first 10,000 bytes of intermediate code.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The comparison operation to determine the occurrences of literal-1 to
be tallied and/or occurrences of literal-3 to be replaced, occurs as follows:
     </para>
            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
The operands of the TALLYING and REPLACING phrases are considered
in the order they are specified in the INSPECT statement from left
to right. The first literal-1, literal-3 is compared to an equal
number of contiguous characters, starting with the leftmost
character position in the data item referenced by identifier-1.
Literal-1, literal-3 and that portion of the contents of the data
item referenced by identifier-1 match if, and only if, they are
equal, character for character.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
If no match occurs in the comparison of the first literal-1,
literal-3, the comparison is repeated with each successive
literal-1, literal-3, if any, until either a match is found or
there ls no next successive literal-1, literal-3. When there is
no next successive literal-1, literal-3, the character position in
the data item referenced by identifier-1 immediately to the right
of the leftmost character position considered in the last
comparison cycle is considered as the leftmost character position,
and the comparison cycle begins again with the first literal-1, literal-3.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
Whenever a match occurs, tallying and/or replacing takes place as
described in general rules 8 through 10. The character position
in the data item referenced by identifier-1 immediately to the
right of the rightmost character position that participated in the
match is now considered to be the leftmost character position of
the data item referenced by identifier-1, and the comparison cycle
starts again with the first literal-1, literal-3.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
The comparison operation continues until the rightmost character
position of the data item referenced by identifier-1 has
participated in a match or has been considered as the leftmost
character position. When this occurs, inspection is terminated.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
If the CHARACTERS phrase is specified,    an implied one character
operand participates in the cycle described in paragraphs 5a
through 5d above, except that no comparison to the contents of the
data item referenced by identifier-1 takes place. This implied
character is considered always to match the leftmost character of
the contents of the data item referenced by identifier-1
participating in the current comparison cycle.
</para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The comparison operation defined in general rule 5 is affected by the
   BEFORE and AFTER phrases as follows:
   </para>
            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
If the BEFORE or AFTER phrase is not specified, literal-1,
literal-3 or the implied operand of the CHARACTERS phrase
participates in the comparison operation as described in general
rule 5.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
If the BEFORE phrase is specified, the associated literal-1,
literal-3 or the implied operand of the CHARACTERS phrase
participates only in those comparison cycles which involve that
portion of the contents of the data item referenced by
identifier-1 from its leftmost character position up to, but not
including, the first occurrence of literal-2, literal-5 within the
contents of the data item referenced by identifier-1. The
position of this first occurrence is determined before the first
cycle of the comparison operation described in general rule S is
begun. If, on any comparison cycle, literal-1, literal-3 or the
implied operand of the CHARACTERS phrase is not eligible to
participate, it is considered not to match the contents of the
data item referenced by identifier-1. If there is no occurrence
of literal-2 literal-5 within the contents of the data item
referenced by identifier-1, its associated literal-1, literal-3,
or the implied operand of the CHARACTERS phrase participates in
the comparison operation as though the BEFORE phrase had not been
specified.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
If the AFTER phrase is specified, the associated literal-1,
literal-3 or the implied operand of the CHARACTERS phrase may
participate only in those comparison cycles which involve that
portion of the contents of the data item referenced by
identifier-1 from the character position immediately to the right
of the rightmost character position of the first occurrence of
literal-2, literal-5 within the contents of        .the data item
referenced by identifier-1 and the rightmost character position
of the data item referenced by identifier-1. The position of this
first occurrence is determined before the first cycle of the
comparison operation described in general rule S is begun. If, on
any comparison cycle, literal-1, literal-3 or the implied operand
of the CHARACTERS phrase is not eligible to participate, it is
considered not to match the contents of the data item referenced
by identifier-1. If there is no occurrence of literal-2,
literal-5 within the contents of the data item referenced by
identifier-1, its associated literal-1, literal-3, or the implied
operand of the CHARACTERS phrase is never eligible to participate
in the comparison operation.
</para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>
      Format 1
</para>
        <orderedlist continuation="continues">
          <listitem>
            <para>
The contents of the data item referenced by identifier-2 are not
initialized by the execution of the INSPECT statement.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
      The rules for tallying are as follows:
      </para>
            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
If   the ALL phrase is specified, the contents of the data item
referenced by identifier-2 is incremented by one for each
occurrence of literal-1 matched within the contents of the data
item referenced by identifier-1.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
If the LEADING phrase is specified, the contents of the data item
referenced by identifier-2 are incremented by one for each
contiguous occurrence of literal-1 matched within the contents of
the data item referenced by identifier-1, provided that the
leftmost such occurrence is at the point where comparison began in
the first comparison cycle in which literal-1 was eligible to
participate.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
If the CHARACTERS phrase is specified,   the contents of the data
item referenced by identifier-2 are incremented by one for each
character matched, in the sense of general rule Se, within the
contents of the data item referenced by identifier-1.
</para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>
Format 2
</para>
        <orderedlist continuation="continues">
          <listitem>
            <para>
The required words ALL, LEADING, and FIRST are adjectives.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The rules for replacement are as follows:
      </para>
            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
When the CHARACTERS phrase is specified, each character matched
in the sense of general rule Se in the contents of the data item
referenced by identifier-1 is replaced by literal-4.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
When the adjective ALL is specified, each occurrence of literal-3
matched in the contents of the data item referenced by
identifier-1 is replaced by literal-4.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
When the adjective LEADING is specified, each contiguous
occurrence of literal-3 matched in the contents of the data item
referenced by identifier-1 is replaced by literal-4, provided that
the leftmost occurrence is at the point where comparison began in
the first comparison cycle in which literal-3 was eligible to
participate.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
When the adjective FIRST is specified, the leftmost occurrence of
literal-3 matched within the contents of the data item referenced
by identifier-1 is replaced by literal-4.
</para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>
Format 3
</para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>                                                                             -.
A Format 3 INSPECT statement is interpreted and executed as though two
successive INSPECT statements specifying the same identifier-1 had been
written with one statement being a Format 1 statement with TALLYING
phrases identical to those specified in the Format 3 statement, and the
other statement being a Format 2 statement with REPLACING phrases
identical to those specified in the Format 3 statement. The general
rules given for matching and counting apply to the Format 1 statement
and the general rules given for matching and replacing apply to the
Format 2 statement.
</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>
EXAMPLES
</para>
        <para>
Four examples of the use of the INSPECT statement follow:
</para>
        <programlisting>
INSPECT word TALLYING count FOR ALL "L", REPLACING LEADING "A" BY "E" AFTER
INITIAL "L".
</programlisting>
        <para>
          <literallayout>
     Where word = CALLAR, count   2, word = CALLAR.
     Where word = SALAMI, count   1, word= SALEMI.
     Where word = LATTER, count   1, word   LETTER.
</literallayout>
        </para>
        <programlisting>
INSPECT word REPLACING ALL "A" BY "G" BEFORE INITIAL "X".
</programlisting>
        <para>
          <literallayout>
      Where word = ARXAX, word = GRXAX.
      Where word = HANDAX, word = HGNDGX.
</literallayout>
        </para>
        <programlisting>
INSPECT word TALLYING count FOR CHARACTERS AFTER INITIAL "J" REPLACING ALL
"A" BY "B"
</programlisting>
        <para>
          <literallayout>
      Where word = ADJECTIVE, count = 6, word = BDJECTIVE.
      Where word = JACK, count = 3, word = JBCK.
      Where word = JUJMAB, count = 5, word = JUJMBB.
</literallayout>
        </para>
        <programlisting>
INSPECT word REPLACING CHARACTERS BY "B" BEFORE INITIAL "A".
</programlisting>
        <para>
          <literallayout>
      word before:   1 2   X Z A B C D
      word after:    B B B B B A B C D
</literallayout>
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>THE MOVE STATEMENT</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>MOVE Statement</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Statement, MOVE</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <section>
        <title>Function</title>
        <para>
The MOVE statement transfers data, in accordance with the rules of
editing, to one or more data areas.
</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Format</title>
        <para>
Format 1
</para>
        <cmdsynopsis>
          <command>MOVE</command>
          <group choice="req">
            <arg>identifier-1</arg>
            <arg>literal</arg>
          </group>
          <arg>TO</arg>
          <arg>identifier-2</arg>
          <arg choice="opt">,  identifier-3  ...</arg>
        </cmdsynopsis>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Syntax Rules</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Identifier-1 and literal represent the sending area;  identifier-2,
identifier-3, ... represent the receiving area.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
An index data item cannot appear as an operand of a MOVE statement.
      (See THE USAGE CLAUSE in this Chapter).
</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Rules</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The data designated by the literal or identifier-1 is moved first to
identifier-2, then to identifier-3, ... . The rules referring to
identifier-2 also apply to the other receiving areas. Any subscripting
or indexing associated with identifier-2, ..., is evaluated immediately
before the data is moved to the respective data item.
     </para>
            <para>
Any subscripting or indexing associated with identifier-1 is evaluated
only once, immediately before data is moved to the first of the
receiving operands. The result of the statement:
     </para>
            <programlisting>
           MOVE a (b) TO b, c (b)
                       </programlisting>
            <para>
     is equivalent to:
     </para>
            <programlisting>
           MOVE a (b) TO temp
           MOVE temp TO b
           MOVE temp TO c (b)
                       </programlisting>
            <para>
where 'temp' is an intermediate result item provided by the implementor.
      </para>
            <para>
See <xref linkend="c03.incom"/> in this Chapter.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Any MOVE in which the sending and receiving items are both elementary
items is an elementary move. Every elementary item belongs to one of
the following categories: numeric, alphabetic, alphanumeric, numeric
edited, alphanumeric edited. These categories are described in the
PICTURE clause. Numeric literals belong to the category numeric, and
nonnumeric literals belongs to the category alphanumeric. The
figurative constant ZERO belongs to the category numeric. The
figurative constant SPACE belongs to the category alphabetic. All
other figurative constants belong to the category alphanumeric.
The following rules apply to an elementary move between these categories:
</para>
            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
The figurative constant SPACE, alphanumeric edited, or alphabetic
data item must not be moved to a numeric or numeric edited data item.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
A numeric literal, the figurative cons t ant ZERO, a numeric data
item or a numeric edited data item must not be moved to an alphabetic data item.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
A non-integer numeric literal or a non-integer numeric data item
must not be moved to an alphanumeric or alphanumeric edited data item.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  <phrase role="extension">A move from a numeric edited field to a numeric field will work provided:</phrase>
                </para>
                <orderedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>
                      <phrase role="extension">the source field is not blank</phrase>
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>
                      <phrase role="extension">the source field does not contain non-stored editing characters i.e. P, S or V</phrase>
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>
                      <phrase role="extension">zero is not used as an edited character.</phrase>
                    </para>
                  </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
All other elementary moves are legal and are performed according
to the rules given in general rule 4.
</para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Any necessary conversion of data from one form of internal
representation to another takes place during legal elementary moves,
along with any editing specified for the receiving data item:
</para>
            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
When an alphanumeric edited or alphanumeric item is a receiving
item, alignment and any necessary space filling takes place as
defined under STANDARD ALIGNMENT RULES in this Chapter. If the
size of the sending item is greater than the size of the receiving
item, the excess characters are truncated on the right after the
receiving item is filled. If the sending item is described as
being signed numeric, the operational sign will not be moved; if
the operational sign occupies a separate character position
(see THE SIGN CLAUSE in this Chapter), that character will not be moved
and the size of the sending item will be considered to be one less
than its actual size (in terms of standard data format characters).
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
When a numeric or numeric edited item is the receiving item,
alignment by decimal point and any necessary zero-filling takes
place as defined under the STANDARD ALIGNMENT RULES in Chapter 2,
except where zeroes are replaced because of editing requirements.
When a signed numeric item is the receiving item, the sign of the
sending item is placed in the receiving item.
(See THE SIGN CLAUSE in this Chapter). Conversion of the representation of
the sign takes place as necessary. If the sending item is
unsigned, a positive sign is generated for the receiving item.
</para>
                <para>
When an unsigned numeric item is the receiving item, the absolute
value of the sending item is moved and no operational sign is
generated for the receiving item.
</para>
                <para>
When a data item described as alphanumeric is the sending item,
data is moved as if the sending item were described as an unsigned
numeric integer.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
When a receiving field is described as alphabetic, justification
and any necessary space-filling takes place as defined under the
STANDARD ALIGNMENT RULES in Chapter 2. If the size of the sending
item is greater than the size of the receiving item, the excess
characters are truncated on the right after the receiving item is filled.
</para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Any move that is not an elementary move is treated exactly as if it
were an alphanumeric to alphanumeric elementary move, except that there
is no conversion of data from one form of internal representation to
another. In such a move, the receiving area will be filled without
consideration for the individual elementary or group items contained
within either the sending or receiving area.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Data in Table 3-6 summarizes the legality of the various types of MOVE
statements. The general rule reference indicates the rule that
prohibits the move or the behavior of a legal move.
</para>
            <table>
              <title>MOVE Statement Data Categories.</title>
              <tgroup cols="5">
                <colspec colwidth="2.0in" colname="c1"/>
                <colspec colwidth="1.0in" colname="c2"/>
                <colspec colwidth="1.0in" colname="c3"/>
                <colspec colwidth="1.0in" colname="c4"/>
                <colspec colwidth="1.0in" colname="c5"/>
                <thead>
                  <row>
                    <entry>Category of Sending Data Item</entry>
                    <entry namest="c2" nameend="c5">Category of Receiving Data Item<superscript>1</superscript></entry>
                  </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <row>
                    <entry morerows="2">ALPHABETIC</entry>
                    <entry morerows="1">Alphabetic</entry>
                    <entry>Alphanumeric Edited</entry>
                    <entry>Numeric Integer</entry>
                    <entry morerows="1">Numeric Edited</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>Alphanumeric</entry>
                    <entry>Numeric Non-Integer</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>Yes/3c</entry>
                    <entry>Yes/3a</entry>
                    <entry>No/2a</entry>
                    <entry>No/2a</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>ALPHANUMERIC</entry>
                    <entry>Yes/3c</entry>
                    <entry>Yes/3a</entry>
                    <entry>Yes/3b</entry>
                    <entry>Yes/3b</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>ALPHANUMERIC EDITED</entry>
                    <entry>Yes/3c</entry>
                    <entry>Yes/3a</entry>
                    <entry>No/2a</entry>
                    <entry>No/2a</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>NUMERIC INTEGER</entry>
                    <entry>No/2b</entry>
                    <entry>Yes/3a</entry>
                    <entry>Yes/3b</entry>
                    <entry>Yes/3b</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>NUMERIC NON-INTEGER</entry>
                    <entry>No/2b</entry>
                    <entry>No/2c</entry>
                    <entry>Yes/3b</entry>
                    <entry>Yes/3b</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry>NUMERIC EDITED</entry>
                    <entry>No/2b</entry>
                    <entry>Yes/3a</entry>
                    <entry>Yes/2d</entry>
                    <entry>No/2a</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry namest="c1" nameend="c5">1 - The relevant rule number is quoted in these columns</entry>
                  </row>
                </tbody>
              </tgroup>
            </table>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>THE MULTIPLY STATEMENT</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>MULTIPLY Statement</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Statement, MULTIPLY</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <section>
        <title>Function</title>
        <para>
The MULTIPLY statement causes numeric data items to be multiplied and
sets the values of data items equal to the results.
</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Format</title>
        <para>
     Format 1
</para>
        <cmdsynopsis>
          <command>MULTIPLY</command>
          <group choice="req">
            <arg>identifier-1</arg>
            <arg>literal-1</arg>
          </group>
          <arg>BY identifier-2</arg>
          <arg choice="opt">ROUNDED</arg>
          <sbr/>
          <arg choice="opt" rep="repeat">, identifier-3 <arg choice="opt">ROUNDED</arg></arg>
          <arg choice="opt">; ON SIZE ERROR imperative-statement</arg>
        </cmdsynopsis>
        <para>
Format 2
</para>
        <cmdsynopsis>
          <command>MULTIPLY</command>
          <group choice="req">
            <arg>identifier-1</arg>
            <arg>literal-1</arg>
          </group>
          <arg>BY</arg>
          <group choice="req">
            <arg>identifier-2</arg>
            <arg>literal-2</arg>
          </group>
          <arg>GIVING</arg>
          <arg>identifier-3</arg>
          <arg choice="opt">ROUNDED</arg>
          <sbr/>
          <arg choice="opt" rep="repeat">, identifier-4 <arg choice="opt">ROUNDED</arg></arg>
          <arg choice="opt">; ON SIZE ERROR imperative-statement</arg>
        </cmdsynopsis>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Syntax Rules</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Each identifier must refer to a numeric elementary item, except that in
     Format 2 each identifier following the word GIVING must refer to either
     an elementary numeric item or an elementary numeric edited item.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Each literal must be a numeric literal.
</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Rules</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
See <xref linkend="c03.rounded"/>, The Size Error Phrase,
The Arithmetic Statements, Overlapping Operands and <xref linkend="c03.incom"/> in this Chapter.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
  When Format 1 is used, the value of identifier-1 or literal-1 is
     multiplied by the value of identifier-2. The value of the multiplier
     (identifier-2) is replaced by this product; similarly for identifier-1
     or literal-1 and identifier-3, etc.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
   When Format 2 is used, the value of identifier-1 or literal-1 is
     multiplied by identifier-2 or literal-2 and the result is stored in
     identifier-3, identifier-4, etc.
    </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>THE PERFORM STATEMENT</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>PERFORM Statement</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Statement, PERFORM</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <section>
        <title>Function</title>
        <para>
The PERFORM statement is used to transfer control explicitly to one or
more procedures and to return control implicitly whenever execution of the
specified procedure is complete.
</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Format</title>
        <para>
  Format 1
</para>
        <cmdsynopsis>
          <command>PERFORM</command>
          <arg>procedure-name-1</arg>
          <arg choice="opt">
            <group choice="req">
              <arg>THROUGH</arg>
              <arg>THRU</arg>
            </group>
            <arg>procedure-name-2</arg>
          </arg>
        </cmdsynopsis>
        <para>
   Format 2
</para>
        <cmdsynopsis>
          <command>PERFORM</command>
          <arg>procedure-name-1</arg>
          <arg choice="opt">
            <group choice="req">
              <arg>THROUGH</arg>
              <arg>THRU</arg>
            </group>
            <arg>procedure-name-2</arg>
          </arg>
          <group choice="req">
            <arg>identifier-1</arg>
            <arg>integer-1</arg>
          </group>
          <arg>TIMES</arg>
        </cmdsynopsis>
        <para>
   Format 3
</para>
        <cmdsynopsis>
          <command>PERFORM</command>
          <arg>procedure-name-1</arg>
          <arg choice="opt">
            <group choice="req">
              <arg>THROUGH</arg>
              <arg>THRU</arg>
            </group>
            <arg>procedure-name-2</arg>
          </arg>
          <arg>UNTIL</arg>
          <arg>condition-1</arg>
        </cmdsynopsis>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Syntax Rules</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Each identifier represents a numeric elementary item described in the
Data Division. In Format 2, identifier-1 must be described as a numeric integer.
   </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The words THRU and THROUGH are equivalent.
   </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Where procedure-name-1 and procedure-name-2 are both specified and
either is the name of a procedure in the declarative section of the
program then both must be procedure-names in the same declarative section.
   </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Rules</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
 When the PERFORM statement is executed, control is transferred to the
first statement of the procedure named procedure-name-1 (except as
indicated in general rules 4b, 4c, and 4d). This transfer of control
occurs only once for each execution of a PERFORM statement. For those
cases where a transfer of control to the named procedure does take
place, an implicit transfer of control to the next executable statement
following the PERFORM statement is established as follows:
</para>
            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
If procedure-name-1 is a paragraph-name and procedure-name-2 is
not specified, then the return is after the last statement of procedure-name-1.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
If procedure-name-1 is a section-name and procedure-name-2 is not
specified, then the return is after the last statement of the last
paragraph in procedure-name-1.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
If procedure-name-2 is specified and it is a paragraph-name, then
the return is after the last statement of the paragraph.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
If procedure-name-2 is specified and it is a section-name, then
the return is after the last statement of the last paragraph in the section.
</para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
There is no necessary relationship between procedure-name-1     and
procedure-name-2 except that a consecutive sequence of operations is to
be executed beginning at the procedure named procedure-name-1 and
ending with the execution of the procedure named procedure-name-2. In
particular, GO TO and PERFORM statements may occur between
procedure-name-1 and the end of procedure-name-2. If there are two or
more logical paths to the return point, then procedure-name-2 may be
the name of a paragraph consisting of the EXIT statement, to which all
of these paths must lead.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
If control passes to these procedures other than via a PERFORM
statement the procedures are executed right through to the next
executable statement in the main program as if they were just part of
the main program,
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The PERFORM statements operate as follows with rule 3 above applying to
all formats:
</para>
            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
Format 1 is the basic PERFORM statement. A procedure referenced
by this type of PERFORM statement is executed once and then
control passes to the next executable statement following the
PERFORM statement.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
Format 2 is the PERFORM TIMES. The procedures are performed the
number of times specified by integer-1 or by the initial value of
the data item referenced by identifier-1 for that execution. If,
at the time of execution of a PERFORM statement, the value of the
data item referenced by identifier-1 is equal to zero or is
negative, control passes to the next executable statement
following the PERFORM statement. Following the execution of the
procedures the specified number of times, control is transferred
to the next executable statement following the PERFORM statement.
During execution of the PERFORM statement, references to
identifier-1 cannot alter the number of times the procedures are to be
executed from that which was indicated by the initial value of identifier-1.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
         Format 3 is the PERFORM...UNTIL. The specified procedures are
          performed until the condition specified by the UNTIL phrase is
           true. When the condition is true, control is transferred to the
          next executable statement after the PERFORM statement. If the
            condition is true when the PERFORM statement is entered, no
            transfer to procedure-name-1 takes place, and control is passed to
            the next executable statement following the PERFORM statement.
    </para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
If a sequence of statements referred to by a PERFORM statement includes
another PERFORM statement, the sequence of procedures associated with
the included PERFORM must itself either be totally included in, or
totally excluded from, the logical sequence referred to by the first
PERFORM. Thus, an active PERFORM statement, whose execution point
begins within the range of another active PERFORM statement, must not
allow control to pass to the exit of the other active PERFORM
statement; furthermore, two or more such active PERFORM statements may
not have a common exit. See Figure 3-1.
</para>
            <figure>
              <title>PERFORM Statement in Sequence.</title>
              <programlisting>
            x   PERFORM a THRU m             x   PERFORM a THRU m

            a   -------------------+         a   -------------------+
                                   |                                |
            d   PERFORM f THRU j   |         d   PERFORM f THRU j   |
                                   |                                |
            f   ---------------+   |         h                      |
                               |   |                                |
            j   &lt;--------------+   |         m   &lt;------------------+
                                   |
            m   &lt;------------------+         f  -------------------+
                                                                   |
                                             j  &lt;------------------+

            x   PERFORM a THRU m
  
            a   -------------------+
                                   |
            f   ---------------+   |
                               |   |
            m   &lt;------------------+
                               |
            j   &lt;--------------+

            d   PERFORM f THRU j
</programlisting>
            </figure>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
A PERFORM statement that appears in a section that is not an
       independent segment can have within its range, in addition to any
       declarative sections whose execution is caused within that range, only
       one of the following:
</para>
            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
          Sections and/or paragraphs wholly contained in one or more non-independent segments.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
          Sections and/or paragraphs wholly contained in a single independent segment.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
</para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
A PERFORM statement that appears in an independent segment can have
   within its range, in addition to any declarative sections whose
   execution is caused within that range, only one of the following:
</para>
            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
      Sections and/or paragraphs wholly contained in one or more
        non-independent segments.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
Sections and/or paragraphs wholly contained in the same
independent segment as that PERFORM statement.
</para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <phrase role="extension">PERFORM statements must not be nested to greater than 22 levels.</phrase>
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>THE STOP STATEMENT</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>STOP Statement</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Statement, STOP</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <section>
        <title>Function</title>
        <para>
The STOP statement causes a permanent or temporary suspension of the
execution of the object program.
</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Format</title>
        <cmdsynopsis>
          <command>STOP</command>
          <group choice="req">
            <arg>RUN</arg>
            <arg>literal</arg>
          </group>
        </cmdsynopsis>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Syntax Rules</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The literal may be numeric or non-numeric or may be any figurative constant, except ALL.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
If the literal is numeric, then it must be an unsigned integer.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
If a STOP RUN statement appears in a consecutive sequence of imperative
statements within a sentence, it must appear as the last statement in that sequence.
</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Rules</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
If the RUN phrase is used, then the operating system ending procedure is instituted.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
If STOP literal is specified, the literal is communicated to the
operator. Continuation of the object program begins with the execution
of the next executable statement in sequence.
 </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>THE SUBTRACT STATEMENT</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>SUBTRACT Statement</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>Statement, SUBTRACT</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <section>
        <title>Function</title>
        <para>
The SUBTRACT statement is used to subtract one, or the sum of two or
more, numeric data items from one or more items, and set the values of one
or more items equal to the results.
</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Format</title>
        <para>
Format 1
        </para>
        <cmdsynopsis>
          <command>SUBTRACT</command>
          <group choice="req">
            <arg>identifier-1</arg>
            <arg>literal-1</arg>
          </group>
          <arg>,</arg>
          <group choice="req" rep="repeat">
            <arg>identifier-2</arg>
            <arg>literal-2</arg>
          </group>
          <arg>...</arg>
          <arg>FROM</arg>
          <arg>identifier-m</arg>
          <arg choice="opt">ROUNDED</arg>
          <arg choice="opt" rep="repeat">
            <arg>, identifier-n</arg>
            <arg choice="opt">ROUNDED</arg>
          </arg>
          <arg choice="opt">; ON SIZE ERROR imperative-statement</arg>
        </cmdsynopsis>
        <para>
Format 2
        </para>
        <cmdsynopsis>
          <command>SUBTRACT</command>
          <group choice="req">
            <arg>identifier-1</arg>
            <arg>literal-1</arg>
          </group>
          <arg>,</arg>
          <group choice="req" rep="repeat">
            <arg>identifier-2</arg>
            <arg>literal-2</arg>
          </group>
          <arg>...</arg>
          <arg>FROM</arg>
          <arg>identifier-m</arg>
          <arg>GIVING</arg>
          <arg>identifier-n</arg>
          <arg choice="opt">ROUNDED</arg>
          <arg choice="opt" rep="repeat">
            <arg>, identifier-o</arg>
            <arg choice="opt">ROUNDED</arg>
          </arg>
          <arg choice="opt">; ON SIZE ERROR imperative-statement</arg>
        </cmdsynopsis>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Syntax Rules</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
 Each identifier must refer to a numeric elementary item except that in
Format 2, each identifier following the word GIVING must refer to
  either an elementary numeric item or an elementary numeric edited item.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Each literal must be a numeric literal.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The composite of operands must not contain more than 18 digits.
(See The Arithmetic Statements in this Chapter).
</para>
            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
In Format 1 the composite of operands is determined by using all of the operands in a given statement.
</para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
In Format 2 the composite of operands is determined by using all
of the operands in a given statement excluding the data items that follow the word GIVING.
</para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>General Rules</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
See <xref linkend="c03.rounded"/>, The Size Error Phrase,
The Arithmetic Statement, Overlapping Operands and <xref linkend="c03.incom"/> in this Chapter.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
In Format 1, all literals or identifiers preceding the word FROM are
added together and this total is subtracted from the current value of
identifier-m storing the result immediately into identifier-m, and
repeating this process respectively for each operand following the word FROM.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
In Format 2, all literals or identifiers preceding the word FROM are
added together, the sum is subtracted from literal-m or identifier-m
and the result of the subtraction is stored as the new value of
identifier-n, identifier-n, etc.
</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
The compiler ensures enough places are carried so as not to lose
significant digits during execution.
    </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
