<?xml version="1.0"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>LIBRARY</title>
  <section>
    <title>INTRODUCTION TO THE LIBRARY MODULE</title>
    <indexterm><primary>Library Module</primary></indexterm>
    <para>
     The Library module provides a capability for specifying text that is to
be copied from a source user-library file. This is usually created using
any suitable source text editor.
</para>
    <para>
     CIS COBOL   libraries consist of disk files that contain source to be
made available to the compiler. The effect of the interpretation of the
COPY statement is to insert text into the source program, where it will be
treated by the compiler as part of the source program.
</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>THE COPY STATEMENT</title>
    <indexterm><primary>COPY Statement</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm><primary>Statement, COPY</primary></indexterm>
    <section>
      <title>FUNCTION</title>
      <para>
     The COPY statement incorporates text into a CIS COBOL source program.
     </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>GENERAL FORMAT</title>
      <cmdsynopsis>
        <arg>COPY</arg>
        <group>
          <arg>text-name</arg>
          <arg>external-file-name-literal</arg>
        </group>
        <arg>.</arg>
      </cmdsynopsis>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>SYNTAX RULES</title>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
Text-name defines a unique external file name which conforms to the
rules for COBOL user-defined words. In a text-name lower case is
translated into upper case. <phrase role="extension">External-file-name-literal is an
alphanumeric literal enclosed in quotes that conforms to the operating
system rules for filenames.</phrase>

</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
The COPY statement must be preceded by a space and terminated by the
separator period.
</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
A COPY statement may occur in the source program anywhere a
character-string or a separator may occur except that a COPY statement
must not occur within a COPY statement.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>GENERAL RULES</title>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
The compilation of a source program containing COPY statement is
logically equivalent to processing all COPY statements prior to the
processing of the resulting source program.
</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
The effect of processing a COPY statement is that the library text
associated with text-name is copied into the source program, logically
replacing the entire COPY statement, beginning with the reserved word
COPY and ending with the punctuation character period, inclusive.
</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
The library text is copied unchanged.
</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <phrase role="extension">If the unit identifier is not explicitly specified, default is to the
drive from which the compiler is loaded.</phrase>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
The text produced as a result of the complete processing of a COPY
statement must not contain a COPY statement.
</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
