<?xml version="1.0"?>
<appendix xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <!-- This appendix appears in revision D of the CC guide as appendix B. -->
  <title>Using and Linking to User Defined Libraries</title>
  <para>
A library consists of a group of <quote>C</quote> procedures or functions that
have been separately compiled into Relocatable Object Files (ROF)
and subsequently merged into on library file.
</para>
  <para>
If, hypothetically, you had created a set of higher level mathematic
functions, that you wanted to convert into a <quote>C</quote> library. First you
would separately compile each one using the <option>-R</option>. Then you
would merge them all into one large library file. If you need to
scan the library file for available functions you can use the
example program <quote>RDUMP.C</quote> to inspect any <quote>C</quote> library file.
</para>
  <para>
For example:
</para>
  <screen>
OS9:CC1 SIN.C COS.C TAN.C ARCOS.C -R
OS9:CC1 ARCSIN.C ARCTAN.C EXP.C LOG.C -R
OS9:CC1 NLOG.C SQRT.C SQR.C CUBE.C -R
</screen>
  <para>
Then you would:
</para>
  <screen>
OS9:MERGE SIN.R COS.R TAN.R ARCOS.R &gt;TEMP1
OS9:MERGE ARCSIN.R ARCTAN.R EXP.R LOG.R &gt;TEMP2
OS9:MERGE NLOG.R SQRT.R SQR.R CUBE.R &gt;TEMP3
OS9:MERGE TEMP1 TEMP2 TEMP3 &gt;TRIG.L
</screen>
  <para>
Then to use the library simply use the <option>-l=&lt;pathlist&gt;</option> option in your
command line when you compile your program.
</para>
  <para>
When the linker is executed the pathlist specified will be searched
to resolve any references made to the functions within the library.
The linker searches all specified libraries in the order specified
before searching the standard library. The linker will resolve all
references on a first found basis. This means that the linker will
use the first procedure or function whose name matches a reference
to that name and will ignore any additional functions found that
have the same name.
</para>
  <para>
Procedures or functions within a library that use other functions
within the same library should always appear first. For example, in
the above example if the <quote>ARCSIN</quote> routine used the <quote>SIN</quote> routine,
the <quote>SIN</quote> routine should be merged into the library after the
<quote>ARCSIN</quote>. Another way of putting this is that all references to
other procedures within a library should be forward references.
</para>
</appendix>
