<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
<title>Introduction</title>

<para>OS-9 Level One is a versatile multiprogramming/multitasking
operating system for computers utilizing the Motorola 6809
microprocessor. OS-9 is well-suited for a wide range of applications
on 6809 computers of almost any size or complexity.
Its main features are:</para>

<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
	<listitem><para>Comprehensive management of all system resources: memory,
	input/output and CPU time.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>A powerful user interface that is easy to learn and use.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>True multiprogramming operation.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Efficient operation in typical microcomputer configuratjons.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Expandable, device-independent unified I/O system.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Full support for modular ROMed software.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Level One version for small and medium sized systems.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Level Two version for large systems with memory management.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>This manual is intended to provide the information necessary to
install, maintain, expand, or write assembly-language software for
OS-9 systems. It assumes that the reader is familiar with the 6809
architecture, instruction set, and assembly language.</para>

<sect1>
<title>History And Design Philosophy</title>

<para>OS-9 Level One is one of the products of the BASIC09 Advanced 6809
Programming Language development effort undertaken by Microware and
Motorola from 1978 to 1980. During the course of the project it
became evident that a fairly sophisticated operating system would be
required to support BASIC09 and similar high-performance 6809
software.</para>

<para>OS-9's design was modeled after Bell Telephone
Laboratories' <trademark class="registered">UNIX</trademark> operating system, which is becoming
widely recognized as a standard for mini and micro multiprogramming
operating systems because of its versatility and relatively simple,
yet elegant structure. 
By no means, however, is OS-9 a direct duplication of UNIX. Even though the system
functions and interfaces are generally compatible, OS-9 has been designed
for better efficiency, greater reliability, and compact size. OS-9 also
pioneers several new concepts such as support of reentrant, position-independent
software that can be shared by several users simultaneously
to reduce overall memory requirements.
</para>

<para>Perhaps the most innovative part of OS-9 is its <quote>memory
module</quote> management system, which provides extensive support for
modular software, particularly ROMed software. This will play an
increasingly important role in the future as a method of reducing
software costs. The <quote>memory module</quote> and LINK capabilities of OS-9
permit modules to be automatically identified, linked together,
shared, updated or repaired. Individual modules in ROM which are
defective may be repaired (without reprogramming the ROM) by placing
a <quote>fixed</quote> module, with the same name, but a higher revision number
into memory. Memory modules have many other advantages, for example,
OS-9 can allow several programs to share a common math subroutine
module. The same module could automatically be replaced with a module
containing drivers for a hardware arithmetic processor without any
change to the programs which call the module.</para>

<para>Users experienced with UNIX should have little difficulty adapting
to OS-9. Here are some of the main differences between the two
systems: 
</para>
<orderedlist  numeration="arabic">
<listitem><para>OS-9 is written in 6809 assembly language, not C. This
improves program size and speed characteristics.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>OS-9 was designed for a mixed RAM/ROM microcomputer memory
environment and more effectively supports reentrant,
position-independent code.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>OS-9 introduces the <quote>memory module</quote> concept for
organizing object code with built-in dynamic inter-module linkage.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>OS-9 supports multiple file managers, which are modules that
interface a class of devices to the file system.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><quote>Fork</quote> and <quote>Execute</quote> calls are faster and
more memory efficient than the UNIX equivalents.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>OS-9 can be dynamically reconfigured by the user, even while
the system is running.</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>System Hardware Requirements</title>

<para>
Because OS-9 is so flexible, the <quote>minimum</quote> hardware requirements are
difficult to define. A bare-bones LEVEL I system requires 4K of ROM and
2K of RAM, which may be expanded to 56K RAM.
</para>
<para>
Shown below are the requirements for a typical OS-9 software
development system. Actual hardware requirements may vary depending upon
the particular application.
</para>
<para>OS-9 LEVEL ONE</para>
<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
<listitem><para>24K Bytes RAM Memory for Assembly Language Development. 40K
Bytes RAM Memory for High Level Languages such as BASIC09 (RAM Must
Be Contiguous From Address Zero Upward) 
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>4K Bytes of ROM: 2K must be addressed at $F800 - $FFFF, the
other 2K is position-independent and self-locating. Some disk
systems may require three 2K ROMs.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Console terminal and interface using serial, parallel, or
memory mapped video.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Optional printer using serial or parallel interface.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Optional real-time clock hardware.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>OS-9 LEVEL TWO</para>

<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
<listitem><para>Memory Management Unit with Dynamic Address Translation with
selectable memory maps.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>64K bytes RAM Memory plus approximately 32K per user.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Console Terminal plus additional user terminal ports.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Floppy and/or Hard Disk system(s).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Real Time Clock hardware.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Optional printer(s) using serial or parallel interfaces.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect1>
</chapter>
