<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
<!-- page-112.png -->
<title>Adapting OS-9 to a New System</title>

<sect1>
<title>Adapting OS-9 Level I to a New System</title>
<para>
Thanks to OS-9's modular structure, OS-9 is easily portable to almost
any 6809-based computer, and in fact, it has been installed on an
incredible variety of hardware. Usually only device driver and device
descriptor modules need to be rewritten or modified for the target
system's specific hardware devices. The larger and more complex kernel
and file manager modules almost never need adaptation.
</para>
<para>
One essential point is that you will need a functional OS-9
development system to use during installation of OS-9 on a new target
system. Although it is possible to use a non-OS-9 system, or if you are
truly masochistic, the target system itself, lack of facilities to
generate and test memory modules and create system disks can make an
otherwise straightforward job a time consuming headache that is seldom
less costly than a commercial OS-9 equipped computer. Over a dozen
manufacturers offer OS-9 based development systems in all price ranges
with an excellent selection of time saving options such as hard disks,
line printers, PROM programmers, etc.
</para>
<para>
Microware sells source code for standard I/O drivers, and a
<quote>User Source Code Package</quote> (on OS-9 format disk only) which contains source
code to the Shell, INIT, SYSGO, device driver and descriptor modules, and
a selection of utility commands which can be useful when moving OS-9 to a
new target system.
</para>
<warning>
<para>
Standard OS-9 software packages are licensed for use on a
single system. OS-9 cannot be resold or otherwise distributed (even if
modified) without a license. Contact Microware for information regarding
software licenses.
</para>
</warning>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Adapting OS-9 to Disk-based Systems</title>
<para>
Usually, most of the work in moving OS-9 to a disk-based target system
is writing a device driver module for the target system's disk
controller. Part of this task involves producing a subset of the driver
(mostly disk read functions) for use as a bootstrap module.
</para>
<para>
If terminal and/or parallel I/O for terminals, printers, etc., will
use ACIA and/or PIA-type devices, the standard ACIA and PIA device driver
modules may be used, or device drivers of your own design may be used in
place of or in addition to these standard modules. Device descriptor
modules may also require adaptation to match device addresses and
initialization required by the target system.
</para>
<para>
A CLOCK module may be adapted from a standard version, or a new one
may be created. All other component modules, such as IOMAN, RBF, SCF,
SHELL, and utilities, seldom require modification.
</para>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Using OS-9 in ROM-based Systems</title>
<para>
One of OS-9's major features is its ability to reside in ROM and work
effectively with ROMed applications programs written in assembler or
high-level languages such as Basic09, Pascal, and C.
</para>
<para>
All the component modules of OS-9 (including all commands and
utilities) are directly ROMable without modification. In some cases,
particularly when the target system is to automatically execute an
application program upon system start-up, it may be necessary to
reassemble the two modules used during system startup (INIT, and SYSGO).
</para>
<para>
The first step in designing a ROM-based system is to select which OS-9
modules to include in ROM. The following checklist is designed to help
you do so:
</para>

<orderedlist  numeration="loweralpha">
    <listitem><para>Include OS9P1, OS9P2, SYSGO, and INIT. These modules are
    required in any OS-9 system.</para></listitem>


    <listitem><para>If the target system is to perform any I/O or interrupt
    functions include IOMAN.</para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>If the target system is to perform I/O to character-oriented
    I/O devices using ACIAs, PIAs, etc., include SCF, required
    device drivers (such as ACIA and PIA, and/or your own), and device
    descriptors as needed (such as TERM, T1, P, and/or your own). If
    device addresses and/or initialization functions need to be changed,
    the device descriptor modules must be modified before being ROMed.</para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>If the target system is to perform disk I/O, include RBF,
    and appropriate disk driver and device descriptor modules. As in (c)
    above, change device addresses and initialization if needed. If
    RBF <emphasis>will not</emphasis> be included, the INIT and SYSGO modules
    <emphasis>must</emphasis> be
    altered to remove references to disk files.</para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>If the target system requires multiprogramming, time-of-day,
    or other time-related functions, include a CLOCK module for the
    target system's real-time clock. Also consider how the clock is to
    be started,. You may want to ROM the <command>Setime</command> command, or
    have SYSGO start the clock.</para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>It the target system will receive commands manually, or if
    any application program uses <application>Shell</application> functions, include the SHELL and
    SYSGO modules, otherwise include a modified SYSGO module which calls
    your application program instead of <application>Shell</application>.</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>



</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Adapting the Initialization Module</title>
<para>INIT is a module that contains system startup parameters.
It <emphasis>must</emphasis> be
in ROM in any OS-9 system (it usually resides in the same ROM as the
kernel). It is a non-executable module named <quote>INIT</quote> and has type
<quote>system</quote> (code $C). It is scanned once during the system startup. It
begins with the standard header followed by:</para>
<informaltable frame="none" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<tgroup cols="2">
<colspec colwidth="1.1in"/>
<colspec colwidth="3.9in"/>
<thead>
<row>
<entry>MODULE OFFSET</entry>
<entry></entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry>$9,$A,$B</entry>
<entry>This location contains an upper limit RAM memory address
used to override OS-9's automatic end-of-RAM search so that memory
may be reserved for I/O device addresses or other special purposes.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>$C</entry>
<entry>Number of entries to create in the IRQ polling table. One entry is
required for each interrupt- generating device control register.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>$D</entry>
<entry>Number of entries to create in the system device table. One entry
is required for each device in the system.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>$E,$F</entry>
<entry>Offset to a string which is the name of the first module to
be executed after startup, usually <quote>SYSGO</quote>. There must
always be a startup module.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>$10,$11</entry>
<entry>Offset to the default
directory name string (normally /D0). This device is assumed when
device names are omitted from pathlists. If the system will not use
disks (e.g., RBF will not be used) this offset <emphasis>must</emphasis>
be zero.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>$12,$13</entry>
<entry>Offset to the initial standard path string
(typically /TERM). This path is opened as the standard paths for the
initial startup module. This offset <emphasis>must</emphasis> contain zero if there
is none.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>$14,$15</entry>
<entry>Offset to bootstrap module name string. If OS-9 does not
find IOMAN in ROM during the start-up module search, it will execute
the bootstrap module named to load additional modules from a file on
a mass-storage device.</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry>$16 to N</entry>
<entry>All name strings referred to above go here. Each must
have the sign bit (bit 7) of the last character set.</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Adapting the SYSGO Module</title>

<para>SYSGO is a program which is the first process started after the
system start-up sequence. Its function is threefold:</para>

<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
<listitem><para>It does additional high-level system initialization, for
example, disk system SYSGO call the <application>shell</application> to process the
<filename>Startup</filename> shell procedure file.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>It starts the first <quote>user</quote> process.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>It thereafter remains in a <quote>wait</quote> state as insurance against all
user processes terminating, thus leaving the system halted. If this
happens. SYSGO can restart the first user program.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>The standard SYSGO module for disk systems cannot be used on
non-disk based systems unless it is modified to:</para>

<orderedlist  numeration="arabic">
<listitem><para>Remove initialization of the working execution directory.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Remove processing of the <filename>Startup</filename> procedure file.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Possibly change the name of the first user program from <application>Shell</application>
to the name of a applications program. Here are some example name strings:</para>

    <informaltable frame="none" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
    <tgroup cols="2">
    <tbody>
    <row>
	<entry>fcs /userpqm/</entry>
	<entry>(object code module <quote>userpgm</quote>)</entry>
    </row>
    <row>
	<entry><literallayout>fcs /RunB /
fcc /userprg/
fcb $0D</literallayout></entry>
    <entry><literallayout>(Module name to fork to)
(Parameter to pass)
(expects carriage return terminator)</literallayout></entry>
    </row>
    <row>
	<entry>fcs /Basic09 /</entry>
	<entry>(Start in Basic09)</entry>
    </row>
    </tbody>
    </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect1>
</chapter>
